<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"

	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	>

  <channel>
    <title>method &#038; matter</title>
    <atom:link href="https://methodandmatter.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <link>https://methodandmatter.com</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <generator>Middleman (Ruby)</generator>
    <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>
		<description>From the desk of Andrea Mignolo</description>
		<meta property="og:image" content="https://methodandmatter.com/images/mm-round.png" />
    <image>
      <url>https://methodandmatter.com/images/mm-round.png</url>
      <title>method &#038; matter</title>
      <link>https://methodandmatter.com</link>
    </image>


			<item>
        <title>[Notes] Reorienting.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/notes/009/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/notes/009/</guid>
				<pubDate>Fri, 08 Dec 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<p>Well, I just completed watching and annotating a three and a half hour conversation between Daniel Schmachtenberger, Iain McGilchrist, and John Verveake diving into the <a href="https://youtu.be/-6V0qmDZ2gg?si=mfN9puqg25N3nsic">psychological drivers of the meta crisis</a>. There is much to synthesize and integrate, but a few things I wanted to capture here that are standing out to me:</p>

<ol>
  <li>The difference between the left and right hemispheres of the brain is important to understand, along with the implications of being in a world where the left hemisphere is dominant. The left hemisphere provides a representation, a map, a program, a theory, a diagram of the world that is abstract and categorical - it does not have the characteristics of the world it is intending to map. The right hemisphere is in touch with presence and the experiential realms, what we inhabit directly. These correlate to different modes of attention and perceiving the world. A study that suppressed first one side of the brain and then the other found that when the left hemisphere was active (and the right suppressed) everything - including living things - appeared inanimate, mechanistic, and broken down into parts. While an active right hemisphere transformed the world into one where even inanimate objects were imbued with life and <a href="https://www.ted.com/talks/jill_bolte_taylor_my_stroke_of_insight?language=en">everything was felt as deeply interconnected</a>. The left hemisphere historically worked in service of the right hemisphere but something happened along the way (the development of stone tools?) that lead to the left hemisphere dominant and the philosophical error of this hemisphere ruling our perception is that we believe the world is made of parts, when the opposite is true - the world emerges out of the coming together of complex wholes. And of course a left hemisphere dominant world creates the conditions for the left hemisphere to thrive which perpetuates the dominance of the left hemisphere and round and round and round we go. There is a VERY big connection with Gestalt here and I intend to explore this further. I also think there is an interesting connection with some of the themes in The Goddess Versus the Alphabet, despite some of my reservations about the book.</li>
  <li>One note on the brief mention of stone tools in parens - as I wrote that I thought about Andrew Feenberg’s theory of instrumentalization and the step of abstraction that allows us to extract a single property from a complex whole (e.g, roundness from the trunk of a tree). So I think perhaps the development of stone tools is the correct starting point for the shift. But today the dominance of the left hemisphere, combined with the power of the technology we have, has put us in a position to self-destruct which was impossible in the time of stone tools.</li>
  <li>Values, purpose, a sense of the sacred - these are wall ways of orienting ourselves in what Verveake calls the meaning crises. I appreciate the distinction made in this conversation that values aren’t something we choose, but rather something that call us forward. And this conversation with values, in this sensing that pulls us forward, is a very <em>real</em> experience - values and purpose are essential to the cosmos.</li>
  <li>Going back to Gestalt, polarities also weave throughout the conversation - one called out explicitly in the beginning, and then in the background throughout. I think what really stands out is the attention brought to the characteristic in all of nature of“opponent processing” - the idea that two systems coexist and are mutually dependent but also anti-correlated - when one is active the other isn’t. This happens with the sympathetic and parasympathetic nervous system, the default and task positive networks of the brain, and with the hemispheres. There is clearly something in polarities that is essential to life or the expression of life. One thing to clarify - we may not currently have oppositional processing in our hemispheres but rather adversarial processing, which has lead to such an unbalanced and dangerous perception of the world and our relationship to it.</li>
  <li>Relationships are the foundation of everything. The divine being needs to create something other than itself to have a relationship with it, the ground of being requires a response. I can see how The Realization Process would provide powerful somatic inquiries and contact with the ground of being, opening up to the flow and responsiveness of life.</li>
  <li>Practices are how we create the world, not beliefs. What we practice every day creates our reality, so pay attention to what you practice and the world your practices create. Pair this with the foundational nature of relationships and it becomes important to practice your practices in a relational way.</li>
  <li><strong>Falling in love with being is an antidote to game theoretics.</strong></li>
  <li>It is critical that we remember our relationship to the cosmos. And to hold mystery at the center.</li>
  <li>It is our sacred obligation to see clearly. When we can see clearly and open to life we come in direct contact with the beauty of reality. I think the way The Realization Process unbinds us from deep constrictions gives us access to this direct contact in a deeply embodied way. I can see how potent these practices could be when it comes to reconfiguring our orientation to life in way that that builds positive feedback loops of wisdom, reverence, and care.</li>
  <li>“Leadership in service of the sacred.” This wasn’t something that was called out directly, but as I listened to the conversation as well as what was calling to me at a deeper level, I thought about <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/notes/003/">Mary Parker Follet</a> and the idea that the one true leader is common purpose. The common purpose is bigger than a single leader, and leaders service of this dethrone themselves and become followers as well. What I have always found evocative about this idea is that leadership is shared or distributed according to the emerging situation. And if we are always trying to sense into the situation, which is always changing and never completely knowable, it makes sense we would require a leadership that acknowledges the benefit of multiple cycles of awareness that begin and end a different times and that are attentive to the emergence of a variety of figures from the ground.</li>
</ol>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Notes] Domination is not influence!</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/notes/008/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/notes/008/</guid>
				<pubDate>Tue, 21 Nov 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<p>The Harvard Business Review popped into my inbox today with a <a href="https://hbr.org/2015/05/understand-the-4-components-of-influence?utm_medium=email&amp;utm_source=circ_other&amp;utm_campaign=subbenemail_readinglists&amp;hideIntromercial=true&amp;tpcc=subbenemail&amp;deliveryName=DM304097#how-to-develop-influence">reading list about Developing Influence</a>. I work with clients at every level of leadership and one of the most common areas of development is around deepening the capacity to influence, so I’m always curious what traditional business and leadership institutes have to say.</p>

<p>The Center for Creative Leadership <a href="https://www.ccl.org/articles/leading-effectively-articles/4-keys-strengthen-ability-influence-others/">defines influence as</a>, “the ability to affect the behavior of others in a particular direction, leveraging key tactics that involve, connect, and inspire them.” Influence is tricky, but I find this definition fairly reasonable as far as something to get your hands around. But according to the first HBR article in the series, “<a href="https://hbr.org/2015/05/understand-the-4-components-of-influence">Understand the Four Components of Influence</a>,” influence is not about involving, connection, or inspiring but <em>domination</em>. And this isn’t me reading between the lines — this brief article uses the word ‘dominate’ <em>four times</em>, just to make itself clear.</p>

<p>This is a relatively short Note to Self, but I just wanted to note how vehemently I disagree with this approach to leadership, and how domination and influence have nothing to do with each other. Domination is power and control. Influence is a mutual give and take, relationally sensing into what each element of a system is seeing and needing, and finding a way forward from there. It requires understanding that systems contain multipolar energy, a natural feature of dynamic wholeness. In order to successfully influence, a leader must also be influenceable. Domination precludes this possibility and shuts down effective avenues of influence. Domination is a sickness that leads to brittleness, a single node controlling all others in a myopic power play. It’s no wonder so many workplaces are in crises. No one wants to be dominated and controlled (certainly not Gen Z, nor any other generation for that matter). And yet, we get articles like this one.</p>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Notes] Notes on direct perception.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/notes/007/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/notes/007/</guid>
				<pubDate>Sat, 18 Nov 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<p>It’s been seven or eight months since I wrote anything serious towards <em>A Song of Reworlding</em>, but the energy around it seems to be picking up again. Or at least the universe is providing an impetus to push my thinking a little bit further.</p>

<p>I randomly picked up Jung’s autobiography, “<a href="https://archive.org/details/MemoriesDreamsReflectionsCarlJung_201608">Memories, Dreams, and Reflections</a>,” on a trip to North Carolina. It was on the bedside table and I couldn’t sleep and seemed like a reasonable use of extra time and wow I wasn’t wrong. More on that later, but the relevant ideas I want to capture in this note come from Chapter 4, “Psychiatric Activities.” Jung was remarkably unique in how deeply he considered the entirety of a person, seeking understanding through a consideration of how stories reveal psychic fragments and the role the lyrical imagery of the unconscious plays, holding clues to healing and wholeness.</p>

<p>Jung’s peers reduced their patients to symptoms and pathologies. They didn’t seem to care much for what people had to say or the details of their lives. Freud couldn’t even stand to listen to women he considered ugly. The whole structure of diagnoses revealed the intellectual and materialist approach driven by scientific ways of understanding. And Jung saw the damaging effects of materialist science and modernity not just in the field he worked in, but on the psyche itself. Reflecting on the frailty of the modern psyche, specifically certain types perhaps more afflicted by the needs of modern life:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“If they had lived in a period and in a milieu in which man was still linked by myth with the world of the ancestors, and thus with nature truly experienced and not merely seen from the outside.” He continues, “I am speaking of those tho cannot tolerate the loss of myth and who can neither find a way to to a merely exterior world, to the world as seen by science, nor rest satisfied with an intellectual juggling with words, which has nothing whatsoever to do with wisdom (p. 172).”</p>
</blockquote>

<p><em>(Note to self: come back to myth and link this up with Gebser.)</em></p>

<p>Andrew Feenberg’s <a href="https://www.sfu.ca/~andrewf/books/critbio.pdf">Instrumentalization Theory</a> is the most complete understanding I have come across when it comes to the technological foundations of deworlding. But I think Jung has more sensitivity to the origins of cognitive and intellectual deworlding. Feenberg is interested in the functional constitution of technical objects and subects and his work grounds the theory through examples of technological objects. Jung begins at a deeper level - the loss of the mythic and the subsequent shift to a more material world. This shift placed us <em>outside</em> of a world we had always lived among and with, and from the outside we found ourselves in a position to reinforce our separateness through the creation of technological objects.</p>

<p>Jung was frequently baffled by his peers who navigated their professional work through purely intellectual approaches. With such a limited perspective they lacked the experience of numinous archetypes that reveal deeper truths, truths essential to healing. He writes,</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“this is where those perilous aberrations begin, the first of which is the attempt to dominate everything by intellect. This serves the secret purpose of placing both doctor and patient at a safe distance from the archetypal effect and thus from real experience, and of substituting for psychic reality an apparently secure, artificial, but merely two-dimensional conceptual world in which reality of life is well covered up by so-called clear concepts. <strong>Experience is stripped of its substance, and instead mere names are substituted, which are henceforth put in the place of reality. No one has any obligations to a concept; that is what is so agreeable about conceptuality - it promises protection from experience.</strong> The spirit does not dwell in concepts, but in deeds and in facts. Words butter no parsnips; nevertheless, this futile procedure is repeated <em>ad infinitum</em> (p. 173).”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Bayo Akomolafe is poetically attuned to how concepts are used to freeze the world into a knowable and false structure. From a recent essay, “<a href="https://www.democracyandbelongingforum.org/forum-blog/black-lives-matter-but-to-whom-part-1">Black Lives Matter, But to whom? Why We Need a Politics of Exile in a Time of Troubling Stuckness, (Part I)</a>:”</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“When we begin trusting that we’ve figured it all out, that our descriptions of ‘facts’ are confident reflections of the way the world really is, we become frozen and impervious to the movement of things. The world is not a simple archive of things that happened, but is a creative, orgasmic dancing with itself, experimenting with im/possibilities.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Reflecting on the matrix of imperial capture, Akomolafe points to the slave ship as the origins of deworlding:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Despite the cold stare of history, black bodies (and their slavers) didn’t leave the slave ships for the plantation. They didn’t disembark. The last slave ship didn’t disappear into the backwaters of ignominious times. When it arrived the shore, it became the shore. It turned. It became the organelles of computational capitalism and its hidden algorithms of bodily reproduction. It became our hegemonic monocultures of mind that orbit around the fetish of the citizen-subject, the dissociated self of modern civilization.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The corollary here is that to reworld ourselves, we have to leave the slave ship for an animist-cosmovision that enables us to live our experiences fully and directly, connecting us to the mythopoetic landscapes that are our birthright.</p>

<p>Jung speaks of the way concepts substitute the mystery of pyschic reality with the solid knowingness of the intellect. I read overlaps with Akomolafe's articulation of the logic of Whiteness:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“a dissociative performance that hijacks the event and makes it subservient to the privileged body, which is itself tautological: in other words, it reduces agonistic tensions, patterns, and embodied movements to pre-figured entities with already stable identities and properties – demanding names, location, and firm histories.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The hegemonic dominance of this demanding worldview feels inescapable. But when I hear Akomolafe’s call to fugitivity something in me responds that feels alive at the invitation, excited by the permission to remain illegible to our current algorithmic arrangement. When we seek to be understood by dominant systems we reduce the dynamic contours of our <em>secret and deep knowing</em> into  flat, two-dimensional space. Legibility begets complicity. To be illegible, to fugitively reconnect with myth and animist-cosomovisions, may yet be the path to reworlding.</p>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Notes] Working with, not against.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/notes/006/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/notes/006/</guid>
				<pubDate>Thu, 09 Nov 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<p>Most business journals talk about “overcoming” resistance as if it were an obstacle on the road to an undoubtedly better destination. Just push a little harder and you’ll get past it! Which completely ignores the intelligence contained within the resistance — additional perspectives, information, sensing, and protective mechanisms that might in fact be very beneficial to consider. If you pause for a minute and listen to the resistance you'll realize you have a blurry map of other possible roads, ones that aren’t blocked by a giant obstacle. While they may not lead to the <em>exact</em> destination you had in mind, they still take you in generally the right direction.</p>

<p>In my Gestalt training we talk a lot about polarities — seemingly opposing concepts that are interrelated and together form a whole. Things like control/freedom, stability/change, individual/group, thinking/feeling, etc. While many of us have learned to think of one end as good and the other as bad, both ends are important for healthy functioning systems. <strong>The interesting thing with polarities is that if you hang out at one end of a spectrum long enough, you eventually get interested in the other end.</strong> We saw this in session with a team that was really great at sharing and listening fully. As we appreciated their skill and capacity in this area, they eventually got to a point where they wondered about taking action.</p>

<p>And then you have the idea of <em>blending</em>, or joining with the energy of tension and moving along with it rather than opposing it. I've come across this concept several areas - body work, martial arts, and in the Realization Process, though I think Aikido has contributed the most to the leadership literature through the lens of resistance. Aikido is a martial art of harmony, of bringing together elements and intensifying them, driving the whole forward at high levels. The practitioner learns how to work with the energy of attack, joining with it and moving it so that the attack transforms and the attacked is neutralized. In leadership contexts this translates to the idea of <em>joining</em> with resistance, moving further into the energy of resistance instead of trying to overcome it (which, if you think about it, is really resisting the resistance and that tends to end in deadlock).</p>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Notes] Becoming whole through the integration of the body.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/notes/005/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/notes/005/</guid>
				<pubDate>Thu, 03 Aug 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<p>For the last four years I've been in training to become a teacher of <a href="https://realizationprocess.org">The Realization Process</a>, a direct path to embodied nondual awakening. Judith Blackstone, who developed this work through her own healing journey, has mentioned on several occasions that the fascia is likely the locus of activity for the constrictions, release, and opening that happens as we attune to ourselves more deeply.</p>

<p>So when I stumbled across <a href="https://opentheory.net/2023/07/principles-of-vasocomputation-a-unification-of-buddhist-phenomenology-active-inference-and-physical-reflex-part-i/">this paper</a>, my ears perked up. The explication of <em>tanha</em> as “grasping” or “clenching” certainly matches up with my own experience (as does “fast grabby thing” for that matter). When I can access the pervasive stillness of what Judith calls Fundamental Consciousness, I open to the awareness of how this grabby, graspy, grippy clenching thing happens. A kind of minute but consistent attempt to hold on to, control, or manipulate direct experience.</p>

<p>There is still much for me to comprehend about what Michael Edward Johnson is pointing to here, but there is enough of an intersection of thought and energy of excitment to warrent a brief note to self here. Especially as I gear up to offer my own Realization Process classes in 2024.</p>

<p>A few quotes from Judith on RP and fascia:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>"In my work, I call the binding, organizing level (or function) of consciousness the “movable mind.” This refers to our ability to mold even the internal space of the body with our imagination. This aspect of consciousness seems intimately connected with the fascia that is everywhere in the body like an interconnected web. Reich believed that we create character armor in rings around the surface of our body. But we now know that this binding can occur anywhere within the internal space of the body, through the binding of the fascia and other physical tissues. Although it may produce an obvious postural change (such as stooping, or scoliosis), it is often a barely detectable density within the body. When we penetrate into the bound tissues with our focus, or through deep massage, we can experience the memory of ourselves in the moment of binding. - p. 49, The Enlightenment Process</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>"It is most likely the fascia of the body that is the shaper of the body in reaction to trauma. Fascia is the connective tissue in the body that surrounds all of our bodily structures. Our fascia is itself a dimension of wholeness. It is made of interconnected tissues that reach everywhere in our body. In the living body, it is a fluid medium that appears to react to both physical and emotional stresses, and then harden, over time, into those reactive shapes. Although this requires more research to establish scientifically, there is a great deal of anecdotal evidence to suggest that the fascia stores the emotional charge of trauma and even the memories of the trauma, or at least, provides access to those memories. In this way, working with the fascia provides a comprehensive approach to releasing trauma from all aspects of the physical body, as well as releasing emotions that are held in the body, and bringing to awareness the memories and beliefs associated with the traumatic events so we may resolve them. The nervous system naturally relaxes into its parasympathetic mode as well, as we release the constrictions within our whole body. p 6 - 7 Trauma and the Unbound Body</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>"Since the fascia is everywhere in our body as an interconnected substance, it is a dimension of our internal wholeness. This means that when we constrict the fascia in one part of our body, it pulls on other parts of the body. This is something like twisting a balloon—even a small torque on one part of the balloon will affect the overall shape. In a human being, there is not just a single twist, but a complexity of constrictions, each producing tension throughout the whole body. p. 14 Trauma and the Unbound Body</p>
</blockquote>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Notes] Leadership as action.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/notes/003/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/notes/003/</guid>
				<pubDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<p>I have recently, thanks to Mastodon's non-algorithmic feed, learned about the work of Mary Parker Follet. Follet was an early philosopher, management consultant, and pioneer in the field of organizational theory and behavior who has some very interesting and relevant ideas about organizations, leadership, and complexity.</p>

<p>I haven't read Follett directly (yet), but rather <a href="https://www.academia.edu/3247476/The_Leadership_of_Everyman">Nanette Monin and Ralph Bathurst's</a> close reading of <em>Essentials of Leadership</em>, a lecture she delivered in 1933 to the newly formed Department of Business Administration at the London School of Economics.</p>

<p>I wanted to capture some initial notes from my reading because there are seeds of thought, ideas of Follett's that I find very compelling and germane to what we are facing in the 21st century. There is complexity in what Follett writes about and she refuses to reduce what she is pointing to into anything concrete, finished, or fully known. Instead, she advocates for the role that leadership, as creative enactment, can play as a sense making process to uncover threads of possibility in each arising moment.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="quotes">Quotes</h3>

<blockquote>
  <p>In business we are always passing from one significant moment to another significant moment, and the leader’s task is pre-eminently to understand the moment of passing. The leader sees one moment melting into another and has learned the mastery of the moment. (Follett, p. 53)</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>The leader's job is to pull the thread of meaning that seems to structure the situation and discover within it the action that will result in the most satisfying outcome for all involved while at the same time holding each resolution lightly. (p. 452)</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Effective leaders enable followership of all, themselves included, to enthrone leadership and demote leaders. (p. 457)</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="notes">Notes</h3>

<ul>
  <li>Leadership is <em>enacted</em> towards a common purpose. Leadership is something that is <em>done</em>, not something that <em>is</em>.</li>
  <li>Leadership as a process of sense-making in order to discover the thread that structures understanding of the total situation. The total situation is ultimately unknowable because it is always changing, dissolving, reforming making it impossible for a leader to understand the total situation. But this should not stop a leader from trying.</li>
  <li>The thread cannot be reduced to a single narrative but must stay connected to multiple possibilities, “where multiple readings of the ever-changing situation allow for creative new solutions not yet considered (p. 450).” This of course is a paradox, the leader can never accomplish this.</li>
  <li>Leadership is not some kind of exalted, super hero role, but the birthright of every man.</li>
  <li>Leadership is a creative role and leaders must learn to work with transitoriness. Leaders must live in doubt, confusion, and limited understanding (Follet calls this <em>negative capability</em>).</li>
  <li>Follett argues that there are no leaders, only leadership. The one true leader is <em>common purpose</em>.</li>
  <li>The thread is the web of relationships that comprise and organization, not a mechanism to exploit or control outcomes.</li>
  <li>The paradox of leadership is that the central responsibility of the leader can never be fully realized because the total situation is not static.</li>
  <li>I think what I like about this is the constant becoming aware of, coming to, letting go, sensing again cycle that it invites. A freshness that is always present, always more full and alive than we can imagine.</li>
  <li>It is not enough to see the situation, the leader must also see the <em>evolving</em> situation, the <em>developing</em> situation, a situation that is constantly changing all the time.</li>
  <li>Making is what leadership is about. The making of leadership is to create the future because, as Follett points out, we usually "have the situation that we make" which relies upon the leader's understanding of the relation between all the different factors. It is not just meeting the next situation, it is <em>making</em> the next situation.</li>
  <li>Leading and following are not antithetical. It is followers who provide leadership, who enable leaders to lead</li>
  <li>Ultimately, there is no such thing as a leader, there is only leadership</li>
  <li><em>Common purpose</em> is the invisible leader of both leaders and followers. Sometimes we may be called to share our expertise (which I think can look like the role of leader) but ultimately when we are followers of the common purpose then we have the best chance at the common bond of union.</li>
  <li>Follett wanted to bust the myth that “leaders are born, not made.”</li>
  <li>Follett talks about a “diffused leadership”, but I am not yet clear on what exactly that means.</li>
  <li>The total situation is always in the process of becoming another situation, common purpose can only be supposed through attempts to figure out the always transitory total situation, and leadership (not leaders) is the way to sense make and find the threads and overall structure.</li>
  <li>I appreciate how much she plays with paradox, especially given my recent trainings in Gestalt. Follett was influenced by Gestalt as well. Chapter 5 of her book <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Creative-Experience-Mary-Parker-Follett-ebook/dp/B01IPHN9Z2/ref=sr_1_3?keywords=mary+parker+follett&amp;qid=1682197685&amp;s=books&amp;sprefix=mary+follett%2Cstripbooks%2C330&amp;sr=1-3">Creative Experience</a> is titled “Experience in the Light of Recent Psychology: The Gestalt Concept.”</li>
</ul>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Notes] Explorations and challenges.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/notes/002/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/notes/002/</guid>
				<pubDate>Fri, 14 Apr 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<p>This morning I finally caught up on Bill Plotkin's three part essay, <em>Who is Up for Building a Cathedral</em> (<a href="https://myemail.constantcontact.com/Who-s-Up-for-Building-a-Cathedral---Part-I--SM322--Bill-Plotkin-Soulcraft-Musing.html?soid=1102010840526&amp;aid=lUl0tzr9FGU">Part I</a>, <a href="https://myemail.constantcontact.com/Who-s-Up-for-Building-a-Cathedral---Part-II--SM323--Bill-Plotkin-Soulcraft-Musing.html?soid=1102010840526&amp;aid=v5hfjf_di2A">Part II</a>, <a href="https://myemail.constantcontact.com/Who-s-Up-for-Building-a-Cathedral---Part-III--SM324--Bill-Plotkin-Soulcraft-Musing.html?soid=1102010840526&amp;aid=FYyIMj3qdG4">Part III</a>), that contextualizes Joseph Campbell's myth of the Hero's Journey as a guide to the adolescent phase of life (defined not by age but by developmental life stage that spans from early adolescence to late adolescence). There are many gifts that this phase of life offers, including exuberance and fiery creativity. But we have prolonged adolescence until it has become pathological, facing a true scarcity of adults and elders. And in this capacity, the Hero's Adventure doesn't offer us any way out, any path beyond the egocentric path of the solo superstar.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>And this brings us right to the heart of what I most want to share with you in this essay: The difficulty for any given person in accessing or recognizing a mature framework (a framework for true maturity) is not only that person’s culture but, even more so, their developmental stage. Maybe it’s just obvious: If someone has not themselves matured beyond early adolescence, then their lens, too, will necessarily be adolescent; everything they experience will be seen and understood through that lens. The caterpillar cannot truly imagine the life of a butterfly.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The quote above captures the essence of what Plotkin writes about, the concession that many myths beyond the Hero's Journey exist, but we cannot see them accurately from the perspective of adolescence because from that vantage point, <em>everything</em> looks like the Hero's Journey. There isn't enough maturity or sensitivity to see things otherwise. A few hours later I was listening to <a href="https://www.coachesrising.com/podcast/an-invitation-into-wholeness-with-veronica-and-alexander-love-and-lorie-dechar/">“An Invitation Into Wholeness,”</a> an episode of the Coaches Rising podcast with Veronica Olalla Love, Alexander Love, and Lorie Dechar. While I'm only halfway through, the beginning half of the conversation covered the necessity of both transactional and transformational coaching. The former being oriented around supporting a client in getting from A to B, the latter being more of a fundamental questioning of our very being and orientation to life.</p>

<p>The starting point of that particular conversational thread was a question of whether it is useful to orient around the future at all, with some people saying that any vision of the future pulls you out of the present in a detrimental way. Their consideration was nuanced and transcended the polarity with some both/and thinking, but what I thought paralleled Plotkin's piece was the idea that in a future orientation that is perspectival, then you are stuck within a perspectival futurism, in the same way once you are in the adolesence of the Hero's Journey every other myth looks like the Hero's Journey. I'm making a note of this because it's an interesting thread to come back to, and both are very Gebserian in nature. Which is also a note to self to continue my reading of Jeremy Johnson's <a href="https://bookshop.org/p/books/seeing-through-the-world-jean-gebser-and-integral-consciousness-jeremy-d-johnson/9691712?ean=9781947544154">Seeing Through the Wold</a>, a kind of intro text for Gebser and integral consciousness.</p>

<p>Unrelated to the themes above, there were some interesting threads relating to AI and deworlding on Substack, but given that it is a <a href="https://buttondown.email/thehypothesis/archive/heres-why-substacks-scam-worked-so-well/">platform for white supremacy</a> (or a <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/2023/04/14/substack-ceo-chris-best-doesnt-realize-hes-just-become-the-nazi-bar/">Nazi Bar</a>, if you will) I'm not very interested in linking to them. Not sure how to reconcile this in the long run, but fine with just keeping research notes and hoping people leave the racist platform.</p>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Notes] Calling all mischievous robot inventors.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/notes/001/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/notes/001/</guid>
				<pubDate>Tue, 14 Mar 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<p>Continuing to collect links and insights that are helping me make sense of the most recent season of <strong>Is Artificial Intelligence Intelligent</strong>? Of course the day after I wrote the <a href="../../the-becoming/005">ChatGPT edition of the becoming</a>, Intelligencer published <a href="https://nymag.com/intelligencer/article/ai-artificial-intelligence-chatbots-emily-m-bender.html">You Are Not a Parrot</a> which says a lot of what I was trying to say but much better, and with more experts.</p>

<p>Then John Maeda sent out the <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/simons-scissors-weizenbaums-wisdom-nicholas-dr-john-maeda/">March 2023 #DesignInTech briefing</a>, in which he includes a passage from <a href="http://blogs.evergreen.edu/cpat/files/2013/05/Computer-Power-and-Human-Reason.pdf">Computer Power and Human Reason</a>, penned by one Dr. Joseph Weizenbaum who apparently invented the chatbot back in 1967, so definitely has some street cred:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I knew of course that people form all sorts of emotional bonds to machines, for example, to musical instruments, motorcycles, and cars. And I knew from long experience that the strong emotional ties many programmers have to their computers are often formed after only short exposures to their machines. What I had not realized is that extremely short exposures to a relatively simple computer program could induce powerful delusional thinking in quite normal people.
This insight led me to attach new importance to questions of the relationship between the individual and the computer, and hence to resolve to think about them.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Once more for everyone in the back, <strong><em>extremely short exposures to a relatively simple computer program could induce powerful delusional thinking in quite normal people</em></strong>. I mean, this feels like what is happening, no?</p>

<p>To keep our heads spinning, <a href="https://openai.com/research/gpt-4">GPT-4</a> was just released, along with a <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.08774">white paper</a> I haven't read (yet) but <a href="https://twitter.com/emilymbender/status/1636089802260111360">it sure doesn't sound very open</a>.</p>

<p>My working assumption right now is that to whatever extent intelligence is being attributed to these tools, we are dealing with projection. Because if you look at the larger zeitgeist and polarizations that are happening in this country (around the world, really) and the intense desire to dehumanize a large part of the planet (I mean, the same desire that's been around for at least 500 years with the rampant violence and subjugation of humans and nature), what is with the urge to humanize a Large Language Model? And if you took the other side and assume these projections are based on positive qualities, then we run the risk of transforming these models into gods.</p>

<p>But either way you look at it, the one thing that remains true for projections is that they function to absolve us of any responsibility in the matter. And that is what scares me the most.</p>

<p>I am beginning to think these projections matter more than whether or not these models are <em>actually</em> intelligent (I need a philosophy tutor just to approach the depth of knowledge and nuance required to be able to coherently contribute to a conversation around "what is intelligence?"). I do think that these models will become part of agentic systems that will be tasked with going off and doing things like scientific research, engineering, business/military/political strategy, hacking, and social persuasion/manipulation (see <a href="https://joecarlsmith.com">Joe Carlsmith</a>'s <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2206.13353.pdf">paper examining the risk factors of power-seeking AI</a> for more on this). Which to me reads like creating tools that further the extractive and violent model of human living (e.g. colonialism, white supremacy). If domination is what we reify, domination we will get. Who is building LLMs that will write poetry, compose sonnets, and delight in the beauty of a butterfly? Not as a cute parlor trick but in a capacity that supports the tending of the human parts of ourselves (and no, this does not look like a 'mental health app' coughed up from the hellscape of capitalist consumerism).</p>

<p>In The Trap of Gargantius, the First Sally of inventors Klapacius and Trurl is at the behest of a king in search of a way of augmenting his army to act as one, which presumably translates into conquest on the battle field. To this end, the two intrepid inventors go about outfitting each soldier with the hardware required to link one to the next. But as each individual connects and the collective mind grows, the unexpected begins to happen.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The fearsome metallic clatter of closing contacts reverberated over the future battlefield; in the place of a thousand bombardiers and grenadiers, commandos, lancers, gunners, snipers, sappers and marauders—there stood two giant beings, who gazed at one another through a million eyes across a mighty plain that lay beneath billowing clouds. There was absolute silence. That famous culmination of consciousness which the great Gargantius had predicted with mathematical precision was now reached on both sides. <strong>For beyond a certain point militarism, a purely local phenomenon, becomes civil, and this is because the Cosmos Itself is by nature wholly civilian, and indeed, the minds of both armies had assumed truly cosmic proportions! Thus, though on the outside armor still gleamed, as well as the death-dealing steel of artillery, within there surged an ocean of mutual good will, tolerance, an all-embracing benevolence, and bright reason.</strong> - Lem, Stanislaw. <a href="https://www.amazon.com/The-Cyberiad/dp/0241467993/ref=tmm_pap_swatch_0?_encoding=UTF8&amp;qid=1679086629&amp;sr=8-1">The Cyberiad</a> (p. 42).</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So I'm on the lookout for mischievous robot inventors instigating random acts of kindness, humor, and goodwill.</p>

<p>Oh, and one more thing. A <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1bG0yIdawiUvwh7m0AnXV5W6JHkK9xwXemuVjSU5tbhQ/preview">collection of suggested readings</a> from the #StochasticParrotsDay live stream hosted by the <a href="https://www.dair-institute.org">DAIR institute</a>.</p>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Essays] On the impact of effective coaching conversations at work</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/creating-space-for-others-to-think/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/creating-space-for-others-to-think/</guid>
				<pubDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<p>For a long time the maxim “don’t bring me problems, bring me solutions,” ruled the world of organizational leadership. While a quick search for the phrase reveals it has fallen out of favor in most management circles, within organizations the ethos <a href="https://www.inc.com/jim-schleckser/build-organizational-muscle-encourage-your-team-to-bring-solutions-not-problems.html">seems alive and well</a>. To a degree this makes sense — most executives I know have progressed up the leadership ladder by assessing big picture challenges and opportunities, coming up with solutions, and getting things done. Once you are senior enough this just becomes a part of your job. The thinking that got you there comes along too, creating a positive feedback loop that further entrenches the approach.</p>

<p><a href="https://ecorner.stanford.edu/clips/encourage-a-culture-of-inquiry">According to Adam Grant</a>, asking people to only bring solutions means 1) people will never speak up about the hardest problems, and 2) when they do have a solution they will push for their approach above all others, resulting in a culture of advocacy rather than inquiry. The detriment here is that a lot of organizational energy goes to positioning, optics, and politics as each leader vies to be the one whose solution gets implemented. What if that energy could be funneled to collaboratively understanding the most pressing and complex problems facing an organization, both internally and externally?</p>

<p>Imagine each person in an organization as a node of awareness. A single node cannot comprehend the wholeness of any complex problem or situation, in the same way <a href="https://allpoetry.com/The-Blind-Man-And-The-Elephant">six blind men cannot comprehend the wholeness of an elephant</a>. Which means it is also unlikely that any solution an individual comes up with will be appropriate to the problem at hand, in part because the problem has not been adequately sensed on a larger scale. A manager or executive might have a wider view of the problem, but it is still incomplete in various ways.</p>

<p>I suspect this is why coaching skills are becoming increasingly important for organizations and executives, as a way of increasing awareness in rapidly changing and unpredictable conditions. A coaching approach builds this awareness by creating space for others to think, where deeper questions can be voiced and explored. In this regard, coaching conversations can essentially be thought of as learning conversations, places of pause where new meaning is made. Conversations that support an increased capacity for individuals and teams to sit with uncertainty, to deeply and thoroughly consider an issue, to reflect on their own contributions to the issue, and to use curiosity as a launchpad for innovation.</p>

<p>Coaching conversations are qualitatively different than other types of conversations leaders have and are not meant to be a replacement. When utilizing a coaching-style approach, a leader must learn to let go of the reins and rely on genuine curiosity and not-knowing to guide the work. This isn’t a passive approach by any stretch of the imagination, but the activeness of coaching is focused on the person and the awareness they are bringing to the issue, not on the issue itself (this is a subtle but important shift). By staying firmly rooted in reality with an optimistic view of the future and asking open and honest questions, the leader as coach creates space for the person they are working with to reflect, make meaning, see new possibilities, and take effective action.</p>

<p>And while coaching conversations are solutions-oriented, solutions are undefined at the outset. When two people come together to explore an issue with a commitment to curiosity and learning, they first build the strength of their relational connection. This connection enables deeper ways of seeing and listening that can regulate the nervous system, <a href="https://medium.com/reboot-leadership-resiliency/leading-consciously-staying-relational-with-presence-and-attunement-a6af1d1233f6">create a sense of safety</a>, and increase creativity. The solutions that emerge in this space are of a higher caliber than solutions that come from stress and fear, which is precisely what the “bring me a solution” mindset invokes. <a href="https://hbr.org/2017/09/the-problem-with-saying-dont-bring-me-problems-bring-me-solutions">According to Sabina Nawaz</a>, this approach can “cause employees to shut down in fear, breeds a culture of intimidation, and prevents some problems from surfacing until they’re full-blown crises.”</p>

<p>So hopefully you are on board with the idea that creating space for others to think is a good thing. That something beneficial happens both personally and organizationally when one person is supported by another in building awareness, creating meaning, and finding new ways forward without someone else, like their manager, doing it for them.</p>

<p>And yet! This can feel really uncomfortable for leaders, especially leaders who believe they already know the answer and want to help. Why not alleviate the problem by sharing what we know and have learned through experience?</p>

<p>Because helping, it turns out, isn’t really all that helpful. In <a href="https://www.awakin.org/v2/read/view.php?tid=127">Helping, Fixing, and Serving</a>, Rachel Remen points to the inherent power imbalance in helping:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Helping is based on inequality, it’s not a relationship between equals. When you help, you use your own strength to help someone with less strength. It’s a one up, one down relationship, and people feel this inequality. When we help, we may inadvertently take away more than we give, diminishing the person’s sense of self-worth and self-esteem.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is an important nuance to pull out — the idea that a coaching approach is one that gives, that increases a person’s sense of self-worth and self-esteem. This is the quiet foundation of effective coaching and why it is so important to create space for people to think and find their own path forward. With this seed of change in place, all the other benefits of coaching conversations become magnified.</p>

<p>We each have our own capacity to sense into the challenges in front of us and figure out how to move through them. Sometimes we need another set of eyes and ears to see and listen for patterns that live in our blind spots, but once these patterns are made visible we can utilize our inherent creativity to find novel solutions to problems. And when we are the ones who do the meaning making, when we are the ones generating new possibilities, when we are the ones choosing what actions to take, then our self-worth, self-esteem, and personal power begins to grow. And the next time we face a challenge we have the memory of our innate resourcefulness in finding our way through. This scales to the team and organizational level as well, where collective memories play an outsized role in a system’s ability to support or block its own capacity to navigate challenges and change.</p>

<p>When these kind of conversations are happening across an entire organization, everything loops back to increase resourcefulness and creativity. As we collectively deepen our awareness, calm our nervous systems, and increase our creative capacity, our ability to work with uncertainty and overcome obstacles becomes stronger.</p>

<p>And it all starts with creating space for others to think.</p>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Essays] Guided reflections across transitional thresholds.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/end-of-a-cycle/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/end-of-a-cycle/</guid>
				<pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2022 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<p>We live our lives within the rhythms and cycles of the physical world. Our calendars commemorate this by marking each full rotation of the earth as a day, the total cycle of the moon around the earth as a month, and the complete trip of the earth around the sun as a year. Though modern life and the Time Grid<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> suggest otherwise, our animal bodies are intimately tied to these rhythms through circadian cycles that let us know when to rest and when to move.</p>

<p>The end of the year, the equinox, the solistice, the end of a quarter - these can all be an auspicious and meaningful times to pause, reflect, and celebrate. To deepen what is congruent and course correct where we feel out of alignment. “At the End of the Cycle” is an exercise in service of you and your journey, and it can be completed whenever it is you feel called to mark some kind of transition, yearly<sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> or otherwise.</p>

<p>This exercise has three parts:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Part 1: Becoming the Being That You Are.</strong> A macro level reflection about who you are and what you are becoming. Think of this as a snapshot of what holds deep meaning and resonance for you and your life, and less about the particular events of the last cycle.</li>
  <li><strong>Part 2: Reflecting on the Past Cycle.</strong> Understanding what shaped you over the course of the past cycle. This takes a more traditional reflection approach across various dimensions of life.</li>
  <li><strong>Part 3: Declaring Future Possibilities.</strong> Writing a letter to Future You, who will be starting the reflection process some time from now (whether that is in 3 months, 6 months, a year is entirely up to you). The letter acts as a synthesis of the work you did in Part 1 and Part 2, while simultaneously weaving in commitments about the future you are creating <sup id="fnref:3" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>.</li>
</ul>

<p>If you’d prefer that in business terms:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Part 1: The Balance Sheet of You.</strong> A snapshot of who you are in the present. You can even map this exercise to the <a href="https://corporatefinanceinstitute.com/resources/accounting/accounting-equation/">accounting equation</a>: your wholeness = who you are + how you resist.</li>
  <li><strong>Part 2: The Income Statement of Life.</strong> A summary of the past cycle across various dimensions of life.</li>
  <li><strong>Part 3: Letter to Shareholders.</strong> In this case the shareholder is Future You.</li>
</ul>

<p>A few tips: I recommend not doing this all in one sitting, but if that’s your jam then go for it. If any reflection or exercise does not feel good to you, skip it. Create whatever kind of space you need to engage in this work. This could be with a cup of tea and a cozy chair, outside in nature, at a your favorite cafe, with a group of friends, or at a noisy bar. Et cetera.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="an-interlude-the-letter">An Interlude: The Letter</h2>
<p>If you did this exercise from a previous cycle, now is the time to read the letter you wrote to your future self. If you have no idea what this means, don’t worry about it! Move on to the next section.</p>

<p class="caption"><img src="/images/essays/moon-cycle.jpg" alt="moon cycle photo" />
Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/photos/-GlDIYT3qSc">Mason Kimbarovsky</a></p>

<hr />

<h2 id="part-1-becoming-the-being-that-you-are">Part 1: Becoming the Being That You Are</h2>
<p>The intention of this exercise is to facilitate a macro understanding of who you understand yourself to be, in this very moment. Of sensing into what it is you long for and what holds you back. To connect with your wholeness, areas of resistance, and the possibilities that open up when you can hold both, together.</p>

<h3 id="who-you-are">Who you are</h3>
<p>Take a few breaths and connect with yourself in this moment. What are you in connection with, what felt senses are arising, and what is your capacity to be with what is here, now? Answer the following questions:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Who am I in this moment? Who do I understand myself to be?</li>
  <li>What am I up to in the world?</li>
  <li>What matters?</li>
  <li>What do I really believe?</li>
  <li>What do I really want?</li>
  <li>How do my thoughts, practices, moods, and habits contribute to my sense of who I am?</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="how-you-resist">How You Resist</h3>
<p>As you worked through the previous exercise, did you notice any resistance to what you were thinking, feeling, and writing? As you begin to observe the resistance, answer the following questions:</p>

<ul>
  <li>What am I resisting?</li>
  <li>How do I do that?</li>
  <li>What is underneath the resistance?</li>
  <li>What limiting beliefs do I hold?</li>
  <li>How does this keep me safe?</li>
  <li>How do my thoughts, practices, moods, and habits support my resistance?</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="appreciating-your-wholeness">Appreciating Your Wholeness</h3>
<p>Who you are and how you resist are all part of your wholeness, the system of you. Resistance serves a purpose, though it may not always be obvious. Take a moment to appreciate all of who you are, and all of how you resist. See if you can drop in and really appreciate every part of you. Answer the following questions:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Who am I in my wholeness?</li>
  <li>How can I deeply appreciate my wholeness?</li>
  <li>What is possible when I fully appreciate my wholeness?</li>
  <li>With this knowledge, what new thoughts, practices, moods, and habits do I want to begin?</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h2 id="part-2-reflecting-on-the-past-cycle">Part 2: Reflecting on the Past Cycle</h2>
<p>The second exercise in this series takes a more traditional reflection route, and uses the events of the last cycle to acknowledge and celebrate the accomplishments, challenges, surprises, and meaning that shaped you. Some folks like to go through their calendar, photos, journals, bank accounts, and other artifacts before jumping into the reflection questions.</p>

<ul>
  <li>What went well?</li>
  <li>What needs to be celebrated?</li>
  <li>What didn’t go well?</li>
  <li>What needs to be let go of?</li>
  <li>What did I learn?</li>
  <li>What did I avoid?</li>
  <li>What did I heal?</li>
  <li>What do I want to remember?</li>
  <li>What brought me energy?</li>
  <li>What depleted me?</li>
  <li>What surprised me?</li>
  <li>What disappointed me?</li>
  <li>What do I want more of?</li>
  <li>What do I want less of?</li>
  <li>What is enough?</li>
  <li>What am I grateful for?</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="dimensions-of-life">Dimensions of Life</h3>
<p>When answering the questions in Part 2, it can be useful to reflect on specific dimensions of your life. You can use the questions to guide reflections in a specific dimension, or include the dimensions in your answers to each question.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Relationships</li>
  <li>Love</li>
  <li>Wealth</li>
  <li>Vocation</li>
  <li>Spirituality</li>
  <li>Health &amp; Wellness</li>
  <li>Practices &amp; Habits</li>
  <li>Adventure</li>
  <li>Community &amp; Service</li>
  <li>Learning &amp; Growth</li>
  <li>Energy &amp; Vitality</li>
  <li>Nature</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h2 id="part-3-declaring-future-possibilities-aka-the-letter">Part 3: Declaring Future Possibilities (aka The Letter)</h2>

<p>Once you feel complete with the appreciation and reflection exercises, give yourself space to let the work settle. This may look like taking a break (15 minutes, 1 day, 1 week, whatever feels right for you), creating a completion ritual, changing locations, having a mini-dance party, making some tea, really anything that can give you a sense of closing out and completing the first part of the process.</p>

<p>When you are ready to begin The Letter, take a few moments to settle your mind. Sit quietly and follow your breath, feel your feet on the floor and your seat in the chair. What do you notice? What sensations are you aware of? Allow the impressions from your reflections to float into your awareness.
Imagine you are sitting across from your future self, one year from today. Your future self that has just started the yearly reflection process. The first thing your future self will do is read the letter you are about to write.</p>

<p>What do you want Future You to know? Sitting here now, in this exact moment, what seeds of the future do you hold and what hopes do you have for what these seeds will grow into? What do you want your future self to know about who you are and what you long for? Your hopes and dreams? What you are committed to? If you are a goal-oriented person, this is a great place to talk about the goals you set and achieved.</p>

<p><em>There is absolutely no wrong way to do this.</em> However you feel called to communicate with Future You a year from now, do that. A letter, a video, a song, a collage, whatever captures what you are living into. Allow your creativity and heart to lead this process.
When you are finished with the letter, put it somewhere safe. You will read it one year from now when you sit down once again to reflect on the year and the person you are becoming.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="closing-with-gratitude">Closing With Gratitude</h2>

<p>To close out the reflection process, take a moment to express your gratitude for everything and everyone that has brought you to where you are today, and for the amazing person you are (becoming). Let the gratitude fully wash over you before you get up and continue move back into the flow of life.</p>

<hr />

<h5 id="footnotes">Footnotes</h5>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Honestly, Time Grid is a more accurate term for what we refer to as a “calendar”. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>In addition to the Lunar New Year, Islamic New Year, Tamil New Year, and Jewish New Year (among others), this exercise can also be used for shorter and longer time frames. Quarterly, semi-annually, your 7 year Saturn cycle, you name it. The Personal New Year (aka your birthday) is also a good time to pause and reflect. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Writing The Letter is my favorite part. I write myself a lot of letters, both to Future Me and Past Me. <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Essays] On working with change as an expression of your full aliveness.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/building-a-relationship-with-change/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/building-a-relationship-with-change/</guid>
				<pubDate>Tue, 29 Nov 2022 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<p>The pace of change today — technological, societal, environmental, geopolitical — is increasing at such a rapid rate that it can be destabilizing to our individual identities. Those of us caught up in the expansive reach of free-market capitalism have cultivated a sense of urgency, entrepreneurialism, and problem-solving when it comes to change. We learn productivity frameworks like <a href="https://www.mindtools.com/a4wo118/smart-goals">S.M.A.R.T.</a>, <a href="https://rework.withgoogle.com/guides/set-goals-with-okrs/steps/introduction/">OKR</a>, and <a href="https://business.adobe.com/blog/basics/bhag">BHAG</a> through which we articulate compelling visions and measure success. And while these approaches have a place, both in the business world and in our personal lives, these frameworks inherently narrow the world in service of what we must achieve at the expense of who we authentically are.</p>

<p>Developing a healthy relationship to change is essential, both personally and professionally, to stay connected to ourselves while adjusting creatively to changing conditions. As each year comes to an end many of us collectively engage in the ritual of New Year’s Resolutions. We identify what we need to start or stop doing to become the type of person that is fully deserving of safety, connection, and belonging. We decide that if we just lose a little more weight, eat healthier, meditate more, work harder, are less stressed, then everything will be ok. And yet, despite our best intentions, <a href="https://www.inc.com/marcel-schwantes/studies-show-91-percent-of-us-wont-achieve-our-new-years-resolutions-how-to-be-9-percent-that-do.html">91% of us won’t achieve our New Year’s Resolutions</a>.</p>

<p>When it comes to the stirrings of the soul, productivity frameworks aren’t the right fit. We can become so focused on specific outcomes in the future that we close ourselves off to who we are in the present. It’s a wonder that even 9% can achieve New Year’s Resolutions!
So what are we to do? The world of Gestalt psychology offers us another option, a theory of change that is more sustainable, less effortful, and embraces the complexity of the world. The theory so simple it doesn’t even require an acronym.</p>

<p>I’m going to share it with you right now. Ready? Here it is:</p>

<p><strong>Change occurs when you become what you are, not by becoming what you are not <sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>.</strong></p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-island-where-it-all-works-out">The Island Where it All Works Out</h2>

<p class="caption"><img src="/images/essays/the-island.jpg" alt="photo of an island from above in the middle of a big blue sea" />
Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@matheo_jbt">Matheo JBT</a></p>

<p>I’d like to tell you about an island you may have heard of: The Island Where It All Works Out. On this island are all the things that we lack today that, when achieved, will bring a sense of success, accomplishment, and peace. We come to a sense of these things through our environment — messages from the systems we inhabit that define what it means to be a successful and valued member of society. Things like owning a house, having an amazing job, finding a partner, being a fully competent human that never makes mistakes; these all live on the island. And if we can just get to the island, everything will work out.</p>

<p>When we catch sight of The Island it lights a fire in us. We set out to get there as quickly as possible, whatever it takes. It’s uncomfortable and unsatisfying being where we are, but on the island we know we can relax because we will have made it. Whatever winds, currents, weather patterns, and mighty whales get in our way, we push forward with force — nothing can take us off course.</p>

<p>When we finally get to the island, somewhat worse for the wear because of the grind and sacrifices we had to make, we realize that the island we have reached isn’t the exact island we set out for. It’s a little run down and lackluster, missing a few things we now realize are also important to achieve satisfaction and contentment. The Island Where It All Works out is still off in the distance. And so we set out again.</p>

<p>You are probably starting to catch on to what is happening. This island certainly is problematic, isn’t it?</p>

<p>There is something I’d like you to know, a little secret if you will. There are two choices that you have when it comes to The Island: the
first is to realize that The Island doesn’t actually exist. You will never reach it because it is not there. The other choice you have is to realize <em>you are already on The Island</em> 🤯.</p>

<p>Which one brings you the biggest sense of relief? Go with that one.</p>

<p>What does The Island have to do with change? When we realize that The Island doesn’t exist (or that we are already on the island) we stop pushing so hard into the future and turn towards the present and the reality of what we are right now. We let go of the there and allow ourselves to be here. And when we can be fully present with what is, that is when real change begins.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-paradox-of-change">The Paradox of Change</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/quotes/50836-the-curious-paradox-is-that-when-i-accept-myself-just">“The curious paradox is that when I accept myself as I am, then I can change.”</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Take a minute and imagine a change in your life you are trying to make. For example maybe you want to be more productive, lose weight, start a side hustle, connect more with people. Sense into how, in that desire for change, you deny anything about you that is getting in your way of achieving that goal. Notice how you do this, how you deny these parts of you. The part of you that procrastinates, indulges, resists, is withdrawn. How do you feel about these parts? You might notice an inner critic or judge saying very negative and mean things about them! But there is certain kind of logic to it — if these parts are getting in the way, then it makes sense to ignore them and get going on achieving the change you want to make. And yet, these disowned parts are the missing piece to making real and lasting change.</p>

<p>What is happening as you explore your hope for change is that you are already stepping into what you think you need to become. In this process a lot of energy is tied up in denying the parts of you that appear to get in the way. You might hear yourself saying things like, “If I was just a little more like this…,” or “If I wasn’t so much like that…,” as you work through this exercise. It can feel confusing and exhausting to exist in this state. To maintain the denial of certain parts of you in order to become something you are not.</p>

<p>A metaphor might help here. Imagine you are setting out on a road trip across the country. You pick a destination on the opposite coast and begin to plan your route. But you are so unhappy with where you currently live that you deny you are actually there. You spend a lot of time and energy maintaining the idea that you live somewhere else entirely! How on earth can you plan the trip if you don’t know where you are starting from?</p>

<p>This is what happens when we try to become something we are not before accepting what we are. We need a solid foundation in order to begin. And this is the core idea behind the paradoxical theory of change: <em>change happens by becoming fully who we are</em>.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="okay-but-ive-got-goals">Okay, but I've got GOALS!</h2>
<p>You might be wondering how this impacts all the things you want to achieve and have and do <sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. When it comes to goals, I have a proposition: what if we thought of them more as a direction, and less as a destination? If we used them as symbolic pointers to help uncover what holds deep meaning and purpose in our lives? If you are willing to do this, two possibilities emerge:</p>

<p>1) What you achieve isn’t exactly what you set out to do, but in the process of uncovering the deeper meaning of your goal you connect with the fullest expression of your own aliveness. By using the goal as a direction rather than a destination, you are able to cultivate a relationship to what is most aligned and coherent for you.</p>

<p>2) You reach your goal unexpectedly, through an indirect and winding path. In each moment you connect with who and where you are, and each next step is taken with integrity and alignment. When you eventually reach your goal, you are a different person than the one that started out, transformed by your relationship with change and in connection with the expression of your full aliveness.</p>

<p>In each of these scenarios we are cultivating a <em>relationship</em> with change. We are allowing ourselves to be responsive to change, to be open and in conversation with it as we move through life. We don’t have this relationship when we are trying to reach The Island. We construct a reality in which the shortest distance between two points is a straight line, and we brute force our way through with maximum energy and effort. This geometric arrangement between here and there may be true in Euclidean space but it does not hold up in the face of the complexity of human living. Being in relationship with change means that we are flexible to the ever changing circumstances of our environment and of ourselves, and through awareness, acceptance, and appreciation of <em>what is</em>, find creative ways of responding. This is decidedly <em>not</em> a straight line.</p>

<p>“Tropism” is a word that denotes an animal or plant’s ability to turn or move in response to a stimulus. The way some animals can orient to true north or magnetic fields, and the way plants reach towards the sun. When we invoke our ability to orient to what feels most coherent with who we are, the ways in which we navigate change become more nourishing, effortless, and energizing.</p>

<p>Take your big goal: to go to a certain university, get a promotion, work at a specific company, buy a house, etc. Really imagine it. Now, connect to not the <em>thing</em> but the <em>qualities</em> that thing represents, the ones that light you up whenever you think about them. By way of example I’ll share one of mine: ever since I was in middle school I have wanted to work at NASA.</p>

<p>To me NASA represents collaboration, dreaming big, pushing boundaries, creativity, possibility, and a coming togetherness. There is something that I can <em>feel</em> in this image of a space colony that I first saw when I was in 7th grade <sup id="fnref:3" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>.</p>

<p class="caption"><img src="/images/essays/space-colony.jpg" alt="illustration of a space colony in a cylindar in space" />
<a href="https://www.nasa.gov/image-feature/retrofuturistic-nasa-space-art">Rick Guidice’s</a> illustration of a torodial space colony, 1970.</p>

<p>As a destination I have not reached the Work At Nasa Island. But this image has consistently held a resonant directionality that has illuminated my path over the years. Who knows, maybe someday I will find myself at the doorstep of the Ames Research Center! But whether I do or not is secondary to honoring the seed of aliveness in this image and navigating life by accepting, appreciating, and being what I am.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="befriending-reality">Befriending Reality</h2>

<p>If this resonates with you, you might be wondering how you can you make reality your BFF. I’ve outlined some steps you can take to engage with this work below. Unlike productivity frameworks, this is not something you can approach intellectually. You must work with change through direct experience and then integrating what you learn into your body and attitude.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Wherever you happen to be right now take a moment pause, settle in, and take a few breaths.</li>
  <li>Now bring to mind a dilemma, a challenge, or some point of tension in your life. Describe the dilemma (either to yourself or to a trusted partner). Don’t worry about how you might resolve it, just explore the dilemma itself.</li>
  <li>As you share, notice what comes into your awareness. Notice what happens in your body as well as any feelings and thoughts that are present. Where do you notice tension, constriction, holding, frustration?</li>
  <li>Notice how you organize yourself in relationship to the challenge you face in your life. What is it like for you to be in that? In the the tension of the dilemma?</li>
  <li>Begin to explore what is good about how you are holding that tension. What is working in that tension? What can be appreciated about how that is serving you right now?</li>
  <li>For example, if you begin to notice that procrastination is playing a role in your dilemma, see if you can let go of any judgements and appreciate how procrastination is working for you . Maybe procrastination creates space for you to focus on multiple things at once. Maybe it keeps you safe by holding you back from completing a project and putting yourself in the position of potentially hearing negative feedback. That’s a pretty important role that procrastination is playing! See if you can really appreciate that.</li>
  <li>Continue to cultivate a sense of appreciation for what you are in this moment. Every single part of you has an intelligence that is working for you in some way, shape, or form. You wouldn’t be doing what you are doing if it wasn’t intended to support you in some way.</li>
  <li>Watch what happens when you do this, when you really sit with and accept and appreciate all of you. Allow the appreciation to melt the structures of judgement that have held you in place for so long. You might also notice that more energy begins to become available. This energy might want to be mobilized in a certain way. If it does, roll with it!</li>
  <li>Keep noticing what is. Herb Stevenson writes that if you can fully stay with your experience, change is inevitable. As much as possible allow your resistance to soften and be with reality as it is in the moment.</li>
</ol>

<p>Ultimately what you are doing in this process is increasing your capacity for awareness, acceptance, and appreciation which allows you to settle into to exactly what you are, without leaving anything out. Your starting place is always in accepting what is. In what is present in doing, thinking, feeling, wanting. And as you build this capacity you will begin to understand how you do what you do, both the benefits and the cost. And what you will find, as you engage in this process, is that you have access to a wider range of possibilities in how you respond and react to life.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="give-it-a-whirl">Give it a Whirl</h2>

<p>When we fight with reality and try to become what we are not, energy becomes trapped in the structures that hold us in patterns of denial. By fully accepting and appreciating who we are right now, even the parts of us that we have opinions about, we can release the trapped energy of stuckness and use it to be more choiceful in how we move in the world. The more we do this, the more be build the flexibility to respond to changing conditions with creativity while also staying connected to ourselves. We find our ground in the foundation of what is, and from this place we can take the next best move in response to change.</p>

<hr />

<h5 id="footnotes">Footnotes</h5>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>This is a slight modification to Arnold Beisser’s original quote, “…change occurs when one becomes what he is, not when he tries to become what he is not.” <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>If you have a Thing You Have to Do, like say, you signed a book contract and have a deadline, then by all means pick up a productivity framework. At this point you are absolutely dealing with a destination, not a direction. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Be careful not to get too analytical with this. My adult brain looks at these images and wants to analyze and critique representations of things like living and dwelling. Which would be useful for a dissertation on the politics of retrofuturism, but as a practice of finding aliveness and meaning, it is the surest way to kill deep imagination. <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

  </channel>
</rss>
