<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"

	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	>

  <channel>
    <title>method &#038; matter</title>
    <atom:link href="https://methodandmatter.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <link>https://methodandmatter.com</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <generator>Middleman (Ruby)</generator>
    <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>
		<description>From the desk of Andrea Mignolo</description>
		<meta property="og:image" content="https://methodandmatter.com/images/mm-round.png" />
    <image>
      <url>https://methodandmatter.com/images/mm-round.png</url>
      <title>method &#038; matter</title>
      <link>https://methodandmatter.com</link>
    </image>


			<item>
        <title>[Note] </title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/notes/individuals-are-identified-through-their-relations/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/notes/individuals-are-identified-through-their-relations/</guid>
				<pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<blockquote>
  <p>Individuals, whether events, particles, or subsystems, don’t have intrinsic names or labels or coordinates. They are distinguished and named only by what they know about the rest of the system through their interactions or shared relationships, ie by what they see when they look around. This is expressed as the view of that individual… so we never think of an individual particle as placed or moving in a background space. We think of an individual only in terms of its view of the rest. — Lee Smolin</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>In modern physics the essential stuff of the universe cannot be reduced to billiard-ball atoms, but exists as relationships and fluctuations at the boundary of what we call matter and energy. Indigenous science teaches that all that exists is an expression of relationships, alliances, and balances between what, for lack of better words, we could call energies, powers, or spirits. — David Peat</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>The world is not a collection of things, it is a collection of events. The difference between things and events is that things persist in time; events have a limited duration. A stone is a prototypical “thing”: we can ask ourselves where it will be tomorrow. Conversely, a kiss is an “event.” It makes no sense to ask where the kiss will be tomorrow. The world is made up of networks of kisses, not of stones. On closer inspection, in fact, even the things that are most “thinglike” are nothing more than long events. — Carlo Rovelli</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Relationality doesn’t mean that there is one way to do and conceive decoloniality, and that it happens to be the way we—the authors of this text—do and conceive it. For us to think that we are in possession of a decolonial universal truth would not be decolonial at all but modern/colonial, and for you, the reader, to assume that this is the way we think would create misunderstandings from the very beginning. Relationality also doesn’t mean simply to include other practices and concepts into our own. Its meaning references what some Andean Indigenous thinkers, including Nina Pacari, Fernando Huanacuni Mamani, and Félix Patzi Paco, refer to as vincularidad. Vincularidad is the awareness of the integral relation and interdependence amongst all living organisms (in which humans are only a part) with territory or land and the cosmos. It is a relation and interdependence in search of balance and harmony of life in the planet. — Catherine E. Walsh and Walter Mignolo</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The universe is a collection of events, connected through interactions and relationships. Humans are no exception. Despite the insistence of  Western individualism, humans do not exist in isolation as things but rather in networks of relationships that give rise to their becoming. Each of us has a
<a href="/writing/notes/we-are-all-unique-observers">distinct and unique view of the universe</a> that is revealed by what we see when we look around.</p>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Note] </title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/notes/we-are-all-unique-observers/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/notes/we-are-all-unique-observers/</guid>
				<pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<blockquote>
  <p>“It is the field in which each and every thing—as an absolute center, possessed of an absolutely unique individuality—becomes manifest as it is in itself.” — Nishanti</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Each of us is a unique observer. This statement is true in many domains—relational physics (the question of consciousness), the biology of cognition (the question of reality), spirituality (the question of originality), and Gestalt psychology (the question of perception).</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-question-of-consciousness">The Question of Consciousness</h2>
<blockquote>
  <p>“A causal universe that is composed of a set of partial views of itself.” — Lee Smolin</p>
</blockquote>

<p>From the standpoint of relational physics, views, or more specifically the differences between views, are a fundamental property of the universe. Some views are common with many near copies; not identical but similar. And some are unique or unprecedented, with no near copies. Some of these novel views experience conscious perceptions which involve “bundled grouping of qualia that define a momentary self.” (p.1)</p>

<p>So consciousness in some capacity is a characteristic of novel views of the universe in that consciousness requires novelty in order to be experienced.</p>

<p><a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/19Ndg6TvMSZgdUABHEoEIKG2ookuHzPE6/view?usp=share_link">On the place of qualia in a relational universe, Lee Smolin</a></p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-question-of-reality">The Question of Reality</h2>
<blockquote>
  <p>“…the reality we live depends on the explanatory path we adopt, and that this in turn depends on the emotional domain in which we enter at the moment of explaining.” — Humberto R. Maturana</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The biology of cognition gives us the idea of a living biological observer whose cognitive abilities are altered if its biology is altered. The malleable nature of biological perception leads us to the question of reality. How each observers views reality is a combination of our biology, emotions, and language. Given the infinite variations that can exist among observers, what constitutes reality is different for each observer! While there are things that we can agree upon exist “as facts”, most of what we take to be reality is generated, created, and maintained inside the observer. To have a meeting at 3pm in the afternoon in a room called “Banana” in a certain building in New York City points to these factual parts of reality. But most everything else that occurs in that meeting will happen in the internal worlds of each observer, who then take those happenings as fact. The meaning making and interpretation of what was said and done will be different for each observer according to whatever was happening somatically, emotionally, and linguistically at the time. In this way, each unique observer observes a unique reality.</p>

<p><a href="https://constructivist.info/radical/papers/maturana/88-reality.html">Reality: The Search for Objectivity or the Quest for a Compelling Argument, Humberto R. Maturana</a></p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-question-of-originality">The Question of Originality</h2>
<blockquote>
  <p>We are original by simply being ourselves, and our creativity tends to be naturally and spontaneously original, without us having to seek out originality. We are complete, and our expressions are true and authentic. — A.H. Almaas</p>
</blockquote>

<p>From a spiritual standpoint we get the question of originality. Spiritual traditions point us to the ways we mistake ourselves for what we are not, often described as some combination of ego and essence. Ego being the schemas that we develop as we individuate and become a human in the world, and essence being the deeper nature of who we truly are. And when we begin to access this deeper nature, we make contact with our originality.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.diamondapproach.org/public-page/keys-enneagram">Keys to the Enneagram, A.H. Almaas</a></p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-question-of-perception">The Question of Perception</h2>
<blockquote>
  <p>We organize the world within us and tend to synthesize experience in terms of wholes. When we manage to do this, we experience closure - satisfaction, completion, or insight. When an experience is difficult to organize and complete, we feel disease or discomfort.” — Joseph C. Zinker</p>
</blockquote>

<p>As unique observers, how do we see? Gestalt points us to some ways to orient ourselves to this question. Taking from the work of systems and fields in the physical sciences, Gestalt extended the idea of ‘the field’ into the social sciences. In this way, objects are do not exist independently of the world around them, but are perceived according to the total configuration in which they are embedded. As Franz Zinker writes, “perception is not determined by fixed characteristics of individual components, but rather by the relationships among these components (p. 47).” Additionally, as pattern-making beings, humans attend to the world and perceive it through relational wholes. The ability to bring awareness to the flow of life, to what requires tending and completion, so that individuals and groups stay in contact with life’s unfolding. And each of us, as a unique perceiver, brings awareness to happens at different points in time, noticing different qualities, and moving into action that keeps us in our own integrity.</p>

<p>Combined with the question of consciousness, the question of perception reveals how each of us, as unique observers with different forms of perception, can begin to form a more coherent sense of what is emerging because each of us is both part of the system and sensing the system.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.gestaltpress.com/in-search-of-good-form/">In Search of Good Form, Joseph C. Zinker</a></p>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Essay] A high level overview of the Coaching Leadership Style.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/the-coaching-leadership-style/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/the-coaching-leadership-style/</guid>
				<pubDate>Tue, 11 Jul 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<p>The Coaching Leadership Style (CLS) is an approach to leadership that focuses on two tracks: development of self and development of others. By utilizing essential coaching skills and methodologies, work becomes a place for deep transformation, learning, and realizing potential.</p>

<h2 id="what-are-leadership-styles">What are Leadership Styles?</h2>

<p>Leadership Styles are a set of core characteristics that describe how a leader leads. When people step into their first leadership role their style emerges organically from past experiences, current beliefs, personality patterns, and what they value most—accomplishment, collaboration, challenge, being recognized, feeling competent, etc. Sometimes the emergent leadership style is congruent with the organization and environment a leader is working in, but at some point leaders find themselves in a situation where their leadership style suddenly seems to stop working.</p>

<p>When this happens the default style, which had been functioning happily and invisibly in the background, is made visible. Leaders realize they have a choice in how they lead and that it is possible to be more effective in their roles by learning new styles. Over time leadership moves from an unconscious expression of beliefs about what leadership should be, to a conscious commitment to lead uniquely from an aware, responsive, and integrated place. When a leader reaches this point they are able to tailor their leadership style specifically for the needs of any given situation.</p>

<h2 id="types-of-leadership-styles">Types of Leadership Styles</h2>

<p>Kurt Lewin developed one of the earliest leadership styles framework in the 1930s in which he defined <a href="https://www.leadershipahoy.com/kurt-lewin-leadership-styles/">three primary leadership styles</a>: autocratic, democratic, and laissez-faire. Half a century later, Daniel Goleman described <a href="https://hbr.org/2000/03/leadership-that-gets-results">six leadership styles</a> based on his Emotional Intelligence framework: coercive, authoritative, affiliative, democratic, pacesetting, and coaching. Then there is the <a href="https://thinkinsights.net/leadership/hersey-blanchard-situational-leadership/">Hersey-Blanchard Model</a> (also known as Situational Leadership), developed in the 1960s, that says no leadership style is better than any other and that a leader must adapt their style to those they lead. The model relies on four styles to support people based on their abilities and attitudes (called ‘willingness’ in the model): directing, coaching, supporting, and delegating (I believe this is the first instance of coaching being linked to a leadership style).</p>

<p class="essay-image-extend"><img src="/images/essays/leadership-styles.png" alt="smiley" /></p>
<p class="caption">Goleman's six leadership styles based on Emotional Intelligence, via <a href="https://hbr.org/2000/03/leadership-that-gets-results">HBR</a></p>

<p>I use these frameworks as more of a heuristic than an exact science—useful tools for understanding and reflecting on the set of skills experienced leaders should have access to. In practice, leadership styles don’t fit into neat categories—most leaders embody a mix of several—so it is important to be conscious of which is being used and why. The work of a leader, at least some of it, is to notice their style in action and learn what it says about how they view both themselves and others. When this becomes clear leaders respond with increased awareness, utilizing different styles with intention, in order to be truly effective.</p>

<h2 id="what-is-the-coaching-leadership-style">What is the Coaching Leadership Style?</h2>

<p>The Coaching Leadership Style (CLS) is an orientation to leadership that is built on a solid foundation of coaching skills including optimism, reflection, self-efficacy, positive emotions, and learning. Leaders who adopt the CLS exponentially increase their ability to support others to develop their potential and take action that creates results. This style combines leadership, management, coaching, positive psychology, organizational behavior, teaming, and learning.</p>

<p>While Situational Leadership integrates aspects of coaching into its theory of leadership, CLS is more comprehensive in its coaching approach and utilizes coaching not just for skills development, but to support people with attitude misalignments (lack of confidence, limiting beliefs, fear, uncertainty), increased ownership of their own development, and long term excellence and professional goals.</p>

<p>The Coaching Leadership Style is also different in the way it utilizes curiosity and learning as the lens through which development, growth, and action happen. It is solutions-oriented and action-based, embodying a true co-creative partnership with others to improve performance and develop long-term strengths. Of all the leadership styles I’ve come across, the coaching leadership style is the most comprehensive when it comes to integrating care, positive regard, high standards, accountability, and direct conversations that empower both the leader and their team to achieve outcomes, overcome challenges, and embrace possibilities in creative ways. It is also a powerful way to close the <a href="https://www.gsb.stanford.edu/insights/knowing-doing-gap">knowing-doing gap</a> and implement long-lasting, transformational change.</p>

<p>Elements of the Coaching Leadership Style include:</p>

<ul>
  <li>A strengths-based approach to change</li>
  <li>Embodying a growth mindset</li>
  <li>Giving clear and effective feedback</li>
  <li>Presence and self-awareness</li>
  <li>Embracing optimism, self-efficacy, positive emotions, and learning</li>
  <li>Working in mutual and creative partnership with others</li>
</ul>

<p>A Few Benefits of the Coaching Leadership Style:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Increased self-confidence and self-efficacy</li>
  <li>The ability to take actions that create results</li>
  <li>Achievement of desired goals</li>
  <li>Increased trust</li>
  <li>Less stress</li>
  <li>Deeper capacity to be with uncertainty and ambiguity</li>
</ul>

<p>The CLS consists of two tracks—self development and the development of others. For a leader to be effective as a coach they must also engage in their own developmental work bringing self-awareness, reflection, and new actions to their own way of being in the world and relating with others. Because of this, it is also the most self-reflective of the leadership styles.</p>

<h2 id="why-it-matters">Why it matters</h2>

<p>Businesses operate in constantly changing and complex environments that require openness, flexibility, and curiosity to be effectively navigated. Organizations that can access the maximum range of sensing, awareness, and creativity available will be more responsive than the competition, able to take first advantage of new developments. For this to be possible, leaders must let go of the idea they should have all the answers and instead step into an approach to leadership that maximizes ongoing and collective learning. The CLS is well-suited to this task.</p>

<hr />

<p>If you are interested in learning more about the CLS and how to practice it, sign-up for <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds/">Words Make Worlds</a>, a bi-weekly newsletter about the art, science, and craft of the Coaching Leadership Style.</p>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Essay] On the impact of effective coaching conversations at work.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/creating-space-for-others-to-think/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/creating-space-for-others-to-think/</guid>
				<pubDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<p>For a long time the maxim “don’t bring me problems, bring me solutions,” ruled the world of organizational leadership. While a quick search for the phrase reveals it has fallen out of favor in most management circles, within organizations the ethos <a href="https://www.inc.com/jim-schleckser/build-organizational-muscle-encourage-your-team-to-bring-solutions-not-problems.html">seems alive and well</a>. To a degree this makes sense — most executives I know have progressed up the leadership ladder by assessing big picture challenges and opportunities, coming up with solutions, and getting things done. Once you are senior enough this just becomes a part of your job. The thinking that got you there comes along too, creating a positive feedback loop that further entrenches the approach.</p>

<p><a href="https://ecorner.stanford.edu/clips/encourage-a-culture-of-inquiry">According to Adam Grant</a>, asking people to only bring solutions means 1) people will never speak up about the hardest problems, and 2) when they do have a solution they will push for their approach above all others, resulting in a culture of advocacy rather than inquiry. The detriment here is that a lot of organizational energy goes to positioning, optics, and politics as each leader vies to be the one whose solution gets implemented. What if that energy could be funneled to collaboratively understanding the most pressing and complex problems facing an organization, both internally and externally?</p>

<p>Imagine each person in an organization as a node of awareness. A single node cannot comprehend the wholeness of any complex problem or situation, in the same way <a href="https://allpoetry.com/The-Blind-Man-And-The-Elephant">six blind men cannot comprehend the wholeness of an elephant</a>. Which means it is also unlikely that any solution an individual comes up with will be appropriate to the problem at hand, in part because the problem has not been adequately sensed on a larger scale. A manager or executive might have a wider view of the problem, but it is still incomplete in various ways.</p>

<p>I suspect this is why coaching skills are becoming increasingly important for organizations and executives, as a way of increasing awareness in rapidly changing and unpredictable conditions. A coaching approach builds this awareness by creating space for others to think, where deeper questions can be voiced and explored. In this regard, coaching conversations can essentially be thought of as learning conversations, places of pause where new meaning is made. Conversations that support an increased capacity for individuals and teams to sit with uncertainty, to deeply and thoroughly consider an issue, to reflect on their own contributions to the issue, and to use curiosity as a launchpad for innovation.</p>

<p>Coaching conversations are qualitatively different than other types of conversations leaders have and are not meant to be a replacement. When utilizing a coaching-style approach, a leader must learn to let go of the reins and rely on genuine curiosity and not-knowing to guide the work. This isn’t a passive approach by any stretch of the imagination, but the activeness of coaching is focused on the person and the awareness they are bringing to the issue, not on the issue itself (this is a subtle but important shift). By staying firmly rooted in reality with an optimistic view of the future and asking open and honest questions, the leader as coach creates space for the person they are working with to reflect, make meaning, see new possibilities, and take effective action.</p>

<p>And while coaching conversations are solutions-oriented, solutions are undefined at the outset. When two people come together to explore an issue with a commitment to curiosity and learning, they first build the strength of their relational connection. This connection enables deeper ways of seeing and listening that can regulate the nervous system, <a href="https://medium.com/reboot-leadership-resiliency/leading-consciously-staying-relational-with-presence-and-attunement-a6af1d1233f6">create a sense of safety</a>, and increase creativity. The solutions that emerge in this space are of a higher caliber than solutions that come from stress and fear, which is precisely what the “bring me a solution” mindset invokes. <a href="https://hbr.org/2017/09/the-problem-with-saying-dont-bring-me-problems-bring-me-solutions">According to Sabina Nawaz</a>, this approach can “cause employees to shut down in fear, breeds a culture of intimidation, and prevents some problems from surfacing until they’re full-blown crises.”</p>

<p>So hopefully you are on board with the idea that creating space for others to think is a good thing. That something beneficial happens both personally and organizationally when one person is supported by another in building awareness, creating meaning, and finding new ways forward without someone else, like their manager, doing it for them.</p>

<p>And yet! This can feel really uncomfortable for leaders, especially leaders who believe they already know the answer and want to help. Why not alleviate the problem by sharing what we know and have learned through experience?</p>

<p>Because helping, it turns out, isn’t really all that helpful. In <a href="https://www.awakin.org/v2/read/view.php?tid=127">Helping, Fixing, and Serving</a>, Rachel Remen points to the inherent power imbalance in helping:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Helping is based on inequality, it’s not a relationship between equals. When you help, you use your own strength to help someone with less strength. It’s a one up, one down relationship, and people feel this inequality. When we help, we may inadvertently take away more than we give, diminishing the person’s sense of self-worth and self-esteem.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is an important nuance to pull out — the idea that a coaching approach is one that gives, that increases a person’s sense of self-worth and self-esteem. This is the quiet foundation of effective coaching and why it is so important to create space for people to think and find their own path forward. With this seed of change in place, all the other benefits of coaching conversations become magnified.</p>

<p>We each have our own capacity to sense into the challenges in front of us and figure out how to move through them. Sometimes we need another set of eyes and ears to see and listen for patterns that live in our blind spots, but once these patterns are made visible we can utilize our inherent creativity to find novel solutions to problems. And when we are the ones who do the meaning making, when we are the ones generating new possibilities, when we are the ones choosing what actions to take, then our self-worth, self-esteem, and personal power begins to grow. And the next time we face a challenge we have the memory of our innate resourcefulness in finding our way through. This scales to the team and organizational level as well, where collective memories play an outsized role in a system’s ability to support or block its own capacity to navigate challenges and change.</p>

<p>When these kind of conversations are happening across an entire organization, everything loops back to increase resourcefulness and creativity. As we collectively deepen our awareness, calm our nervous systems, and increase our creative capacity, our ability to work with uncertainty and overcome obstacles becomes stronger.</p>

<p>And it all starts with creating space for others to think.</p>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Essay] A story of coming home.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/on-belonging/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/on-belonging/</guid>
				<pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<p class="caption"><img src="/images/essays/belonging.png" alt="smiley" />
Trillium illustration courtesy of Midjourney.</p>

<p>When I was in elementary school we lived on a dirt road in a small, wooded neighborhood. The houses were somewhat far apart, walkable but not dense enough to fill a pillowcase full of candy on Halloween. There weren’t any kids close by so I spent a lot of time in the forest and with our older, friendly neighbors.</p>

<p>The Gregorys, who lived across the street, had vineyards and strawberry patches, the first spiral staircase I had ever seen, and put flowers in their salads. My 10 year old brain marveled at this act of wild creativity. It was on their property that I learned an early and important lesson about electric fences. The Lanes lived down the road past a large patch of trilliums in a shaded midcentury modern and were involved in the world of midwestern architecture (Mr. Lane was the architect of a local high school). And there was Mr. Bateroff in his pick-up truck, speeding too fast along the little dirt road. I mimicked the head shaking and tutting of the adults every time he zipped by, kicking up a cloud of dust. Other than speeding he was a friendly man, hosting neighborhood potlucks and letting us catch tadpoles from the pond in his back yard.</p>

<p>And then one summer two girls, sisters, moved into their grandparents house down the street. The move was temporary while their parents, who had also moved in, navigated a brief hiatus in employment.</p>

<p class="essay-image-extend"><img src="/images/essays/woodland.jpg" alt="smiley" /></p>
<p class="caption">The house looked something like this.</p>

<p>Laura was my age and had a flair for drama (think Sound of Music not Gossip Girl) and mischievousness, of which her older sister was usually the target. She had a way of smiling, followed by a quick wink, that let you know she was up to something. I don’t remember us <em>becoming</em> friends, we just immediately <em>were</em>.</p>

<p>Our imaginations functioned on the same frequency and the connection felt intuitive. There was nothing to negotiate, just endless worlds to explore. The way we played was wildly expressive and lacked any sense of self-consciousness that would have been destabilizing. One day after school we became cats and crawled through her grandparent’s house on all fours meowing at everyone, which drove her sister wild (this put “being cats” in regular play rotation). We filled bowls with Cheerios, set them on the kitchen floor, and ate without using our hands before meowing some more, purring, and taking naps.</p>

<p>I also was building friendships with other girls at school, girls who lived in neighborhoods with paved streets, lots of kids, and a housing density that could fill a pillowcase full of candy faster than you could say, “Ghostbusters!”</p>

<p class="caption"><img src="/images/essays/stickers.jpg" alt="smiley" />
Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@stationery_hoe?utm_source=unsplash&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_content=creditCopyText">Kasturi Roy</a> on Unsplash</p>

<p>I learned a lot from them too—how to be a part of a group, the rituals of girlhood interactions, and how to belong socially. Collecting stickers was popular activity and we’d spend hours flipping through each other’s books commenting on recent additions and occasionally making strategic trades. The glorious puffy, glittery, smelly stickers were all safely behind plastic coversheets of photo album pages. To my recollection we never actually stuck them on anything. Maybe they were a proxy for our budding style and curatorial sensibilities, maybe they were a way of understanding how to negotiate social situations while quietly broadcasting our identity. But deep imagination wasn’t a part of how I interacted with this group of friends. It was more of a tentative foray into the question of “how do we belong together?”</p>

<hr class="section-break" />

<p>As my career took off I found myself spending more and more time in the world of stickers. Learning the rituals of belonging in corporate and start-up environments and learning them pretty dang well. But the cost was high—I lost my connection with intuition and imagination, along with the courage to step into relationships where such things could flourish. Whenever I met someone who lived on that frequency, connected to the flow of life in ways I longed for, I felt shame. Shame for having lost touch with this part of myself and shame that I didn’t know if I could connect with it again.</p>

<p>The world of stickers asks us to sacrifice a part of ourselves for the safety of belonging. Encoded are rituals for how we behave, what we do, and what we acquire so that we can be accepted, successful, and liked. As I examined this aspect of my own life it became clear that in my bid for belonging I routinely abandoned myself.</p>

<p>To rectify this dire situation I figured I needed to get back to connecting with the Lauras of the world. I wondered if I could become a tuning fork, vibrating at a frequency that would invite connections that do not require negotiation but simply the willingness to be, and the courage to follow with openness and curiosity, the currents of creativity.</p>

<p>Recently I was talking to a dear friend, <a href="https://whitneyhess.com/">Whitney Hess</a>, and shared that I was hearing echoes from the world of stickers that softly called to my fear of not belonging. In response she shared that for her, no belonging mattered more than belonging to herself. Well beyond what my ears and brain were processing, her words acted like a soothing balm to existential aches I didn’t know I had.</p>

<p><em>What matters most is belonging to myself.</em></p>

<p>In life, when do we ever truly belong to ourselves? In childhood we belong to our family, in adolescence to our peer group and culture, and in adulthood to society. What gives us the courage to listen and heed the call, after learning to belong in so many ways, that it is time to come home to ourselves? I thought I needed to reclaim my connection to the Lauras of the world, but I am learning that first I must reclaim my connection to myself. As <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6qfbpBzqitA&amp;list=PLSR2TqZCSzFPTE6k34dP-CC8A7NnAPQ1a&amp;index=25&amp;t=318s">Brené Brown</a> says, “our worth and belonging are not negotiated with other people. We carry those inside our hearts.”</p>

<p>What does it mean to belong to ourselves? Here is what I’ve discovered so far: belonging to ourselves requires a radical act of trust. The willingness to connect deeply with the currents of knowing that swirl inside of us and the faith that what we find there is enough to guide who and how we are in the world. A way of settling into our bodies so deeply that a vast stillness opens and we can listen for what wants to come through. And when we hear it we tend to it, stay true to it, and allow it to become a part of our being.</p>

<p>Belonging to ourselves isn’t some kind of “my way or the highway” approach to life, in fact it is quite the opposite. As I’ve cultivated my own belonging I’ve found that I am more open to contact, more connected to the world, more in the flow of life. I am grateful for what I have learned from the world of stickers and from the Lauras, and I can see how they are all part of navigating the world together. But until we can fully belong to ourselves it is just about impossible to find our way without squeezing into uncomfortable contours that were never ours to fill. Belonging to ourselves invites the world to fold itself around our rightful shape and shows us all the ways in which we so beautifully and perfectly belong — to ourselves, to the world, and to life.</p>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Essay] A short treatise on centering.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/working-with-discomfort/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/working-with-discomfort/</guid>
				<pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<p>In life we all face bumpy moments, periods of turbulence and uncertainty, times of just not wanting things to be the way they are. The scenarios are vast: <a href="/writing/essays/receiving-feedback/">receiving feedback</a> that is hard to hear, dealing with a difficult colleague, not getting funding, getting laid off, having our hearts broken — there are so many ways that life can be uncomfortable and intense. The natural inclination is to fix whatever ails us and bring life more in line with our vision of what it should be. And sometimes this is the right approach, when there is a clear solution that is within our control to implement. But more often than not we deceive ourselves about what we can control and spend a lot of time exhausting ourselves pretending otherwise.</p>

<p class="essay-image-extend"><img src="/images/essays/discomfort.jpg" alt="smiley" /></p>
<p class="caption">Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@jbowersphotography?utm_source=medium&amp;utm_medium=referral">Jonathan Bowers</a> on Unsplash</p>

<p>Fittingly, I’m writing this article in the darkness of my home office, a single candle brightening the space but certainly not warming it. The power has gone out on a winter night. We’re in the midst of a bomb cyclone here in California and the wind just blasted off a part of my neighbor’s roof which is now sitting on the power lines as the storm rages. It is cold. I just broke out my subzero sleeping bag.</p>

<p>I do not like this. I have things to do. I hate being cold and have bad circulation. My nose is an icicle.</p>

<p>And so I center.</p>

<p>This is now my current reality. I can try to control (avoid) the reactions the situation brings up in me by tensing and pushing away my frustration, distracting myself online, or pouring a glass of wine. Or I can accept what is, let the frustration move through me, and move into action. I gather lanterns, chargers, blankets, headlamps, and anything else that would be helpful to navigate this night. I call my boyfriend and ask him to pick up something for dinner. I light a candle and sit down to write this article in the dark, at least while the battery is charged.</p>

<p>“But Andi,” you say, “that’s a pretty tame scenario. Of course you were going to get candles and blankets and figure out food.”</p>

<p>Which is true, but if I had moved into action from a place of frustration and reactivity I may not have considered all the things I did. I may not have been open to the way a suddenly new and novel situation was asking me to move in different ways. I probably would have overloaded my nervous system and been grumpy the rest of the evening.</p>

<p>Here’s another one by way of example: recently a part of my brain has decided to raise the possibility that every decision I’ve made in my life was the wrong one. What it lacks in logic it makes up for in emotion. Whenever this idea pops up it grabs me and my body starts to freak out. Tense muscles, shortness of breath, spiraling thoughts. It feels real. I can try and control this by pushing it away and focusing on something else or I can center.</p>

<p>Centering calms my nervous system and gives me the capacity to be with the fear (née terror) that I have followed the wrong path. That I have really messed up somewhere along the way. I allow it all in, and bring compassion to myself and what I am feeling. I can ask myself the question, “what if this is true?” and have the presence, fortitude, and curiosity to explore the fear. It’s not comfortable, but I can hold it all. And when I do this, when I work with the fear rather than try and control it or avoid it, a few things happen. The first is that it doesn’t seem so bad. Even if it were 100% true that doesn’t mean that the next decision I make will be the wrong one. The second is that I now have awareness and choice available to me, there is energy that can be moved into action.</p>

<p>Richard Strozzi-Heckler <a href="https://strozziinstitute.com/centering-the-unity-of-action-and-being/">describes centering</a> as “…the broad and abundant platform from which we launch into a full relationship with the world, and ourselves.” Centering is the practice of bringing the head, heart, and body into alignment and becoming fully present. It’s ridiculously simple to do, and deceptively hard to master. But what centering creates in us is the ability to relax into ourselves so that we can hold more discomfort, be with the intensity, and face reality as it is. Centering is not about being Zenned out, shut down, detached, or peaceful. We center to deepen our ability to feel more, not to feel less. As <a href="https://strozziinstitute.com/staff/alta-starr/">Alta Starr</a> says, “We center so that our aliveness is as full and available to ourselves as possible. We center to be alive.”</p>

<p>The basics of centering go something like this:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Focus on your breathing:</strong> when we are moving from a place of reactivity our breathing tends to be shallow and rapid. Bring attention to your breath and take a few slow, deep inhales. Let the exhale go wherever it goes. Breathing works, just ask the science.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Shift your posture:</strong> notice how your body is shaping itself and shift into a more centered and aligned place. Wiggle your toes and fingers. Feel the length of your spine and reach the top of your head towards the sky.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Bring your attention to the present:</strong> stop time traveling into the past or the future! Focus your attention on what is going on right here, right now in your immediate environment. On what is going on right here, right now, in you. Allow yourself to feel the discomfort of disappointment, anger, hurt, sadness, powerlessness, uncertainty, and fear with deep compassion for yourself. It’s okay to be here. This is where you are. Allow your body to hold everything that is in your awareness.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>As you do this, notice what starts to shift. Discomfort often “grabs” us and pushes our nervous system into overdrive as it executes the motions of avoidance (whether that’s fight, flight, freeze, appease, or some combination therein). What usually happens for me as I sit with discomfort is that my body softens and the weight of the discomfort begins to ease up. As this happens, my field of vision widens and I can start to see possibilities for taking conscious, intentional action.</p>

<p>You can do all of this in about 30 seconds. For an even shorter technique try Wendy Palmer’s instructions:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Inhale up and lengthen your spine, exhale down softening your chest. Think of something that makes you smile.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Interestingly, centering is also a great practice when life is filled with joy, ease, and flow. Centering allows us to deepen our capacity to receive gratitude, success, and positive regard. I have worked with so many people who really struggle to fully let in and feel the fullness of their own competence and the impact they’ve had on others.</p>

<p>So give it a try. Build a simple centering practices into your day. In the morning with a cup of coffee. Before a meeting. In the evening as you wind down your day. Center to unify action and being. Center to feel your aliveness.</p>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Essay] The only constant in life is change. - Heraclitus</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/transitions/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/transitions/</guid>
				<pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<p class="caption"><img src="/images/essays/transitions-texture.jpg" alt="smiley" />
<a href="http://twitter.com/yogidan2012">@yogidan2012</a> on Unsplash</p>

<p>Life is a ceaseless process of transition. The small transitions of daily life slip by unnoticed while the big changes—career, relationship status, geographic location, etc.—are worthy of celebratory social media posts. From the outside these changes seem to happen quickly, a snapshot in time that marks the spot where one thing ceases to be and the next begins. What doesn’t make it into a LinkedIn update is that the snapshot—what we see outwardly as a marker of change—is only a small part of a much longer, invisible, non-linear process.</p>

<p>At the beginning of the pandemic I left my career in tech to become an executive coach. With a coaching certification already in hand and a small roster of clients on the side, I thought the transition would be straightforward. I <em>love</em> coaching and was ecstatic to be able to do this work full time, but wow did I underestimate what the transition would ask of me. Two years in and I’m <em>still</em> in the process of transition.</p>

<h2 id="on-transitions">On transitions</h2>

<p>The simple awareness of a transition is enough to begin the process, whether the transition itself is intentional or not. Faced with a new reality, people look for ways to orient around the change and understand what it means. It’s common to spend time reflecting on personal values to remind us of who we want to be in the world. Transitions can be an opportunity to shake off what felt compromising or intolerable in the past in order to live more congruently in the present.</p>

<p>William and Susan Bridges, some of the best writers on the subject, define transitions as: “the process of letting go of the way things used to be and then taking hold of the way they subsequently become.” In theory this sounds straightforward but in practice we can easily fall into “<a href="https://hbr.org/2022/01/when-a-major-life-change-upends-your-sense-of-self">identity paralysis</a>” — the inability to move on from previous identities and embrace new ones, <em>whether the change itself was positive or negative</em>. Transitions inevitably unravel our understanding of who we are in order to make space for <em>who we are becoming</em>.</p>

<p>Letting go is hard work. What happens to our identity in the midst of transition isn’t an additive process in which a new identity gets layered onto the our current one. It is an undoing, a cleaning out, a shedding. My career as a tech executive was intricately tied to my identity and way of being in the world. It was how I signaled my value to society and how society saw value in me. It defined what occupied my attention and how I structured my days and weeks. Who was I without the complex flow of organizational life to define me? When the daily rhythms of company work disappeared, so did my sense of self.</p>

<h2 id="the-transition-model">The Transition Model</h2>

<p>If you asked me a few years ago how transitions work, I would have said something like this:</p>

<p class="essay-image-extend"><img src="/images/essays/transitions-mine.png" alt="smiley" /></p>
<p class="caption">My faulty model of transitions.</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The Ending:</strong> something happens that precipitates a change. In my case, I realized that something vital came alive as a coach and I wanted this work to be the focus of my days, weeks, and years. I put in notice at work, said tearful goodbyes to my team, and dropped my work computer in the mail.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The New Beginning:</strong> the new beginning begins! I put up a website, opened my doors, and began coaching.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>But it turns out they look more like this:</p>

<p class="essay-image-extend"><img src="/images/essays/transitions-bridges.png" alt="smiley" /></p>
<p class="caption">William &amp; Susan Bridges model of transitions.</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The Ending:</strong> something shifts and alerts us to the closing of a cycle or period in life. At the same time, seeds of the new beginning are present along with a third space—the neutral zone—a liminal place of unbecoming.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The Neutral Zone:</strong> as we move through the stages of letting go, of grief, of understanding ourselves in new light and new context, the liminal space of the neutral zone grows and encompasses most of our awareness. We feel disoriented and uncertain.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The New Beginning:</strong> the new beginning takes shape and builds momentum. We are in conversation with the new situation while simultaneously in contact with the neutral zone and the process of metabolizing the ending.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>Bridges’ model completely shifted my understanding of transitions in two fundamental ways. First, the existence of the neutral zone as a place of necessary disorientation was the key to bringing acceptance and compassion to my experience. And second, the insight that all three stages occur simultaneously over time helped me let go of the need to have it all figured out, let go of trying to control the experience and instead give myself over to the process of transition itself.</p>

<h2 id="the-three-stages-of-transition">The Three Stages of Transition</h2>

<p>Let’s look at the three stages of transition a little more closely.</p>

<h3 id="an-ending">An Ending</h3>

<p>Endings are a kind of symbolic death in which we must let go of the person we’ve been in order to create space for something new to emerge. This is sometimes scary, always uncomfortable, and absolutely necessary to truly take advantage of what transitions can offer in terms of personal and professional transformation.</p>

<p>Endings themselves have different aspects, making them more of a process than a singular event. According to the Bridges’ research, there are 5 key phases to endings:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Disengagement:</strong> the systems that helped support our identity cease to be a part of our environment. Things like calendars, communication channels, coworkers, and responsibilities are no longer a part of our world. It’s okay to let them go.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Dismantling:</strong> once we disengage from these systems, space opens up to unpack our relationship to our previous role and the identity we created in relationship to the organization, system, and team. The separation of dismantling is what needs to happen to move from ‘we’ to ‘I’.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Disidentification:</strong> as we dismantle and disengage, old ways of defining ourselves through roles, responsibilities, and titles begin to fall away. If we are doing this right, we will start to lose a sense of who we are.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Disenchantment:</strong> this is the time to let go of assumptions about reality and accept our own role in creating the specific version we have been inhabiting. We begin to sense that reality has layers and it is time to look below the surface.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Disorientation:</strong> a time of emptiness and disorientation, we no longer know which way is forward, and which way is back. This is the doorway to the neutral zone.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>Endings can open up old wounds, particularly if we have done a good job of compartmentalizing and suppressing the pain of prior experiences. If this happens to you, know that this is very common and you are not alone. Friends, family, therapists, healers, and coaches can be supportive during this time provided the relationship is built on trust and safety. For a quick rundown of what this work entails, “<a href="https://www.thehappinessdoctor.com/blog/7-ways-to-heal-your-old-emotional-wounds">7 Ways to Heal Your Old Emotional Wounds</a>,” is a good place to start.</p>

<h3 id="the-neutral-zone">The Neutral zone</h3>

<p>The neutral zone is a liminal space, an emptiness between ending and beginning. It provides a pause between the old identity and a new one, a pause where the deep work of transitions can unfold. Being in the neutral zone invites us to sit with the discomfort of feeling aimless and undone.</p>

<p>Opening up to this space, to this in-between, gives us access to new ways of perceiving the world. The more we can let go into the aimlessness of the neutral zone, the more we have access to new levels of consciousness. We can tap into other ways of knowing such as deep imagination, intuition, and the dreamtime. When we allow ourselves to see the world differently we expand our sense of reality and connect to a deeper sense of purpose. The neutral zone is necessary in order to metabolize old identities and create the substrate for something new to emerge. Without the neutral zone we wouldn’t have access to this transformational magic.</p>

<p>The neutral zone works in a time outside of time. Personally, I’ve been sitting in the neutral zone for about a year and a half. By this point I’ve become familiar with the visceral process of excavation, sensing where the old identity is filling space that will be needed to support the emergence of a new beginning. It’s not easy though, the letting go.</p>

<p>“Really? This too?” I ask the Neutral Zone.</p>

<p>“Yes, even this too,” is always the reply.</p>

<p>And so I comply, gently, letting another part of my identity dissipate. Resting in the space of not knowing and trusting that this will, at some point, lead somewhere. Bridges calls this experience a kind of emotional wilderness, a place where we can tap into the alternate flow of time needed for internal changes to occur, for internal changes require much more time than external ones.</p>

<h3 id="the-new-beginning">The New beginning</h3>

<blockquote>
  <p>“When we are ready to make a new beginning, we will shortly find an opportunity,” — William and Susan Bridges (p. 158)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The stirrings of a beginning, of a true beginning, happen inwardly. We are changed and transformed by the neutral zone, reconstructed in ways that support the adult we are becoming. And when that becoming has reached a certain point, when we are ready, a beginning beckons. Beginnings are organic, ordinary, and small—heralded without fanfare by hints from inner signals. According to Bridges, these hints can come in many forms: ideas, images, comments, impressions, and dreams to name a few. If we pay close attention to the words and visions that make us feel alive, that have a special kind of resonance, we will find poetic guides to a new beginning.</p>

<p>I thought my new beginning was becoming a coach, but in hindsight I can see it for what it is: an ending. I am still floating in liminal space of the neutral zone letting more of my identity wash away and releasing old ways of orienting myself in the world. The person I am becoming requires yet more space, more letting go, more unraveling. The deeper beginning is still unknown to me, but I can sense it rustling on the periphery, the faintest whispers of something new. I must be still to hear it. Only then will I be able to know what beckons.</p>

<h2 id="the-transition-checklist">The Transition Checklist</h2>

<p>Transitions aren’t just about getting to the other side, they are an invitation to fully surrender to something that cannot be fully known by the cognitive mind. Understanding and accepting this doesn’t make the process any easier, but can be reassuring to know how it works. I encourage you to read <a href="https://bookshop.org/books/transitions-40th-anniversary-edition-making-sense-of-life-s-changes/9780738285405">Transitions: Making Sense of Life’s Changes</a> because it is a stellar companion to have along life’s journey. But if I were to encapsulate what I’ve learned about transitions into a quick list, I’d offer the following:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Take time to reflect and welcome whatever is occurring for you.</li>
  <li>Recognize your thoughts</li>
  <li>Honor your emotions</li>
  <li>Tune into physical sensations</li>
  <li>Create a ritual or event that symbolizes the closing of a chapter in your life. Let yourself experience the ending.</li>
  <li>Create space for emptiness. Find a regular time to be alone.</li>
  <li>Accept resistance, and welcome it in.</li>
  <li>Listen for the new beginning.</li>
  <li><a href="https://hbr.org/2005/01/whats-your-story">Craft a story to tie the past and the present together</a>.</li>
</ol>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Essay] Receiving feedback can be scary, but it doesn’t have to be.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/receiving-feedback/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/receiving-feedback/</guid>
				<pubDate>Sat, 20 Feb 2021 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<p>Good feedback, whether you are on the receiving or giving end, requires an attitude of curiosity and openness. <a href="https://medium.com/method-matter/creating-the-right-space-for-feedback-d54a872019ab">Intentionally creating space for feedback</a> can help, but even with the right space, receiving feedback can be really scary. Many organizations have formal systems of feedback in the style of mid-year and annual reviews. And it’s not uncommon for informal continuous feedback to supplement formal reviews. Formal or informal, the moment feedback is on the table, there’s a good chance <a href="https://www.verywellmind.com/what-happens-during-an-amygdala-hijack-4165944">our amygdala is going to freak out</a>. And when it does, it’s fight, flight, or freeze time. With practice, we can move away from defensiveness and reactivity, and find ways to receive feedback while remaining grounded, open, and curious.</p>

<h2 id="what-happens-when-we-receive-feedback">What happens when we receive feedback?</h2>

<p>The most common thing people do when receiving feedback is internalize it. Immediately. It just comes into our inner landscape and takes up permanent residence. The challenge when feedback is internalized so quickly is that we lose the space and perspective to examine it, understand, and process it. And when we bypass these critical steps, feedback becomes Truth. This is why reactivity and defensiveness are common responses when we experience feedback — it feels like a Truth has just been shared that we weren’t invited to participate in creating.</p>

<h2 id="the-receiving-feedback-checklist">The receiving feedback Checklist</h2>

<h3 id="step-1-check-in-with-yourself-get-grounded-get-curious">Step 1: Check-in with yourself. Get grounded. Get curious.</h3>

<p>I begin everything with a self-checkin, and receiving feedback is no different. As soon as you realize you are in a feedback conversation, take a few deep breaths. Connect to your center. Feel your feet. How are you feeling? What is your energy like? Where is your attention being drawn? What emotions are coming up? Take a few deep breaths, and see if you can find a little more ease in your body.</p>

<h3 id="step-2-listen-from-center">Step 2: Listen from center.</h3>

<p>Listen to what the other person has to say. But not just any kind of listening, centered listening. In her book <a href="https://bookshop.org/a/21645/9781492946694">Leadership Embodiment</a>, Wendy Palmer distinguishes between “listening from personality” and “listening from center”.</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Listening from personality:</strong> a good clue you’re in this mode is a need for control, approval, and safety. If what is being said isn’t what you want to hear, feelings of stress, anxiety, and irritation will come to the fore when listening from personality making it harder to receive, assess, and process information. In this mode, our bodies might physically contract, causing the mind to contract, stress hormones to kick in, and suddenly fight, flight, or freeze responses kick in.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Listening from center:</strong> characteristics of this mode include an awareness of the big picture, feelings of interconnection, and a widening of possibilities. There is a curiosity about the situation, about what is being heard, and what is being understood. Our bodies are open and relaxed. The ability to listen to what is being said and what is not being said is another characteristic of this mode.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>I’d wager that most of us, when we find ourselves in feedback conversations, are listening from personality. And this is when amygdala hijacking kicks in and we internalize feedback instantanesouly. Practicing active listening from a centered place creates space for the conversation and for our own reactions.</p>

<h3 id="step-3-put-the-feedback-on-a-plate">Step 3: Put the feedback on a plate.</h3>

<p>Imagine there is a plate between you and person sharing feedback. As they speak, imagine their words going onto the plate, where you can examine them. This visualization keeps the words external, allows you to see what is being shared, and to look at it more objectively. From this vantage point you can ask clarifying questions, seek to understand what is being shared, and remain grounded and listen from center. Keep the feedback on the plate as the feedback conversation progresses.</p>

<h3 id="step-4-distinguish-between-fact-and-opinion">Step 4: Distinguish between fact and opinion.</h3>

<p>One of the things look for when receiving feedback is opinions masquerading as facts. There is a whole <a href="https://instituteofcoaching.org/blogs/grounding-our-coaching-how-linguistic-coaching-came-be">theory of language</a> around this, but essentially it goes like this: facts are observable and grounded. “It’s 65F degrees outside.” This is a fact. Opinions are interpretations of facts. “It’s warm outside,” and “it’s cold outside,” could both be accurate opinions for the same 65F degree day, depending on a number factors such as where the speaker grew up, body type, quality of circulation, and amount of clothes currently being worn.</p>

<p>In a feedback conversation, this might show up in a comment along the lines of, “you need to speak up more.” Sounds like a fact, doesn’t it? But it’s actually an opinion based on how the speaker interprets the world. With the feedback sitting on the plate in front of you, and having flagged this as an opinion masquerading as a fact, you can now start to ask clarifying questions to understand what the speaker is really trying to say. They probably aren’t asking you to speak just for the sake of hearing yourself talk (although I do know company cultures where this is A Thing), but there is something they think can be solved by sharing their opinion-as-fact. Maybe they spoke to 10 people in other departments and none of them knew what your team was working on. Or maybe they are multi-tasking in meetings and aren’t listening when you speak. Whatever it is, “you need to speak up more,” is not a fact, nor is it very actionable feedback. Once you can see these language constructions in action, it becomes easier to use them as anchors for clarifying conversations.</p>

<h3 id="step-5-step-5-add-a-few-responses-and-gestures-to-your-toolkit">Step 5: Step 5: Add a few responses and gestures to your toolkit.</h3>

<p>It can be useful to have a few go-to phrases and responses at the ready to help create space for processing in the midst of a feedback conversation in order to slow the conversation down, modulate reactivity, and create new possibilities for responding. You might do something like take some really deep breaths while nodding slowly, saying something along the lines of, “This is new information for me and I’m going to need a few moments to process it,” or “I’m really surprised to hear this, can you provide more context?”</p>

<h2 id="sanity-check">Sanity check</h2>

<p>Sometimes we find ourselves receiving feedback from someone who feels very ‘correct’ in their interpretation of the world and gets agitated when you start to ask open and honest questions. This is a tricky situation to be in, and it means that you aren’t going to be in a learning conversation because the other side simply wants to corroborate their opinion of the situation. <em>Do not internalize the feedback they have given you.</em> Leave the feedback on the plate in front of you, thank the person for the feedback, and tell them you will reflect on what they had to share. Find a trusted colleague, a coach, or a peer group to debrief with, and look at the breakdown of facts and opinions. There will likely be a few insights for you, but it might take some work to get at them.</p>

<h2 id="thats-all">That's all!</h2>

<p>It can feel like a lot is at stake when we’re on the receiving end of a feedback conversation. As human beings, we construct interpretations of our world based on our own patterns of observing, acting, reflecting, and understanding. Because we only have access to a small set of facts, we create structures of interpretations that reinforce our personal world view. In a feedback conversation, multiple structures of interpretations are interacting with each other. Great feedback conversations acknowledge this and look for shared outcomes and understanding. Listening from center, keeping feedback on a plate, and paying attention to facts-as-opinions can make the art of receiving feedback much easier, more insightful, and eventually more easeful. So give it a try the next time someone shares feedback with you, and see what happens. Good luck!</p>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Essay] What happens outside the conversation is as important as what happens in it.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/space-for-feedback/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/space-for-feedback/</guid>
				<pubDate>Tue, 12 Jan 2021 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<p>Remember that time someone gave you a gift and you opened it and were like, “oh wow, this person doesn’t know me at all”? Maybe it wasn’t your style (or size), or too flashy, or just totally not anything you’d be into? The type of gift that is more about the person giving it, than about you?</p>

<p class="essay-image-extend"><img src="/images/essays/feedback-gift.jpg" alt="smiley" /></p>
<p class="caption">Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@kadh?utm_source=unsplash&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_content=creditCopyText">Kira auf der Heide</a> on Unsplash</p>

<p>Great feedback, on the other hand, is a gift for both parties. When approached with curiosity, care, and understanding, giving feedback becomes a learning conversation. The first step in doing this skillfully is to drop the idea that feedback is a one way street — that the person giving feedback is “right” and the person receiving feedback is somehow “wrong”. This kind of thinking makes the shittiest of gifts.</p>

<hr class="section-break" />

<h2 id="creating-the-space">Creating the Space</h2>

<p>Okay, so you want to give someone feedback. Maybe someone did something great and you are giving them feedback to celebrate (yay!), but more often than not feedback comes up when something seems to be going off the rails. Before you open your mouth and share whatever happens to be in your head in the moment, pause. Most of the important work giving feedback actually happens before the conversation itself. The following is a check-list I like to run through to make sure I’m creating the right space:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Ground yourself.</strong> Take a few deep breaths and allow yourself to settle into the present moment. What’s happening? Are you feeling reactive or judgmental? Maybe you are feeling anxious? Or perhaps thoughtful and focused? Giving good, clear feedback requires us first to be aware and in control of what’s happening in our inner world. Taking a few moments to ground and connect with ourselves is mandatory for a good feedback conversation.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Get clear on your why.</strong> What’s really driving the desire to provide feedback? Do you want to prove that your own ideas are right, validate your abilities, take someone down a notch? It’s hard to admit, and even harder to do the reflective work to know what we’re really up to, but when we’re feeling reactive or anxious to provide feedback, the underlying motives might be self-serving. If your why is coming from a place of insecurity, go back to step one and ground yourself until you move away from reactivity and can connect to a why that serves a larger purpose.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Embrace curiosity.</strong> You don’t have the full picture. No one has the full picture. It’s just the nature of human perception—we cannot possibly take in all the information and process it, so we select a subset of data to pay attention to that in turn informs our beliefs. Approaching feedback conversations from a posture of learning will help everyone involved understand context, perspectives, and assumptions. Here’s a tip: if you are feeling judgmental, negative, or ready to assign blame, you’re probably not in learning mode.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Understand power dynamics.</strong> In a position of power (especially positional power) being grounded, curious, and open is critical when entering into a feedback conversation. If you are reactive and ready to reinforce your own truth, the person on the receiving end will shut down. At this point, the conversation is no longer about learning and as a leader you’ve just poked yourself in the eye. What could have been a conversation filled with new perspectives and information is now a one-way street and you’re not going to learn anything new. Power dynamics are important to understand even if you aren’t someone’s direct manager. Maybe you’ve been there longer, have a more senior title, are a co-founder, have a lot of influence — whatever it is, be sensitive to power dynamics and if you find yourself reactive or defensive, pause, breathe, and get curious. And if you can’t do that, save the feedback session for another time.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Ask for consent.</strong> Given that we’ve all probably had less-than-wonderful feedback conversations, asking for consent is a kindness that gives the person on the receiving end of the feedback a heads up for what kind of conversation is about to happen. This can be a simple, “Hey, I have some feedback I’d like to share with you. Is that something you can hear right now?” If they are rushing towards a deadline or having a bad day, they may want to reschedule the conversation. Most times people will be open to receiving feedback and can switch into feedback mode, but make sure you ask for consent. The other benefit of asking for consent is that we can clearly signal we are giving feedback. I don’t know how many times I’ve seen people try and give feedback and the other person has no idea they are in a feedback conversation. Be kind, ask for consent. It’s a nice ritual that creates space to shift into a feedback conversation.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Share your feedback.</strong> You are grounded, curious, open. Clear on the purpose of the conversation. Aware of power dynamics. And you’ve asked consent. Now what? There are a number of frameworks that can be used to guide the actual conversation itself. A few I have used over the years: <a href="https://medium.com/@mmeima/life-saving-job-saving-communication-framework-asap-agree-5a458a59cc8">ASAP + Agree</a>, <a href="https://www.ccl.org/articles/leading-effectively-articles/hr-pipeline-a-quick-win-to-improve-your-talent-development-process/">Situation, Behavior, Impact Feedback Model</a>, <a href="https://www.nonviolentcommunication.com/learn-nonviolent-communication/4-part-nvc/">Non-violent Communication</a>, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7qtJ87WTPNY">Issue Clearing</a>. Using a framework might feel awkward at first, but they can be helpful when it comes to keeping the blame game out of the conversation. Until you’ve had a lot of practice with these types of conversations and know how to consistently stay grounded and open, frameworks can be a useful resource to re-orient towards curiosity and learning, even if the conversation gets challenging.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Get clear on what needs to happen moving forward.</strong> You’ve had a great feedback conversation—multiple perspectives and interpretations have been explored, misunderstandings and miscommunications have been clarified, there is a sense of clarity, trust, and understanding that is present—but before you wrap up, be sure you both decide what needs to happen moving forward. This isn’t about detailed action plans and bulleted lists, it’s about knowing you are leaving the conversation with a shared understanding of what’s different and what’s changed. Ideally you’ve both learned something, so what are you going to do with those insights?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Give your sincere thanks.</strong> Share your gratitude for the recipient’s willingness to be open to feedback, and to be willing to explore a learning conversation with you. This sets the tone for future conversations and builds trust. Feedback conversations are so often equated with the feeling of “being in trouble”, so the more we can create a different experience of feedback, the more these types of conversations can happen.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<hr class="section-break" />

<p><em>Good feedback is about curiosity and clear intentions.</em> It doesn’t matter what framework you use (eventually you won’t need to use one!), what matters is that every feedback conversation becomes a learning conversation. If you are willing to engage in a mutual exploration of what is happening, and if you are willing to honor the experiences of others, you’ll find these conversations can become a foundation for trust, growth, and possibility. Best of luck on your feedback journey!</p>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Essay] A closer look at management, leadership, and why it’s important to understand the differences between the two.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/management-and-leadership/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/management-and-leadership/</guid>
				<pubDate>Thu, 03 Sep 2020 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<p>If you’re stepping into a leadership role, chances are you’re also going to be doing a lot of managing. And while it’s true the two overlap quite a bit, understanding the differences can help you be more effective manager, a more inspirational leader, and more successful overall.</p>

<h2 id="on-management">On Management</h2>

<p>Managers are a specific breed of leader, created by the business world to <a href="https://hbr.org/2004/01/managers-and-leaders-are-they-different">guide the destinies</a> of corporate enterprises. They are responsible and accountable for running and <em>managing</em> a part of the business. This might be a division, a department, or a team with a specific mandate. Their power in the organization is bestowed upon them by their position, which is why it’s called positional power. If they weren’t in the position, they wouldn’t have power. When combined with great leadership skills, managers rarely need to rely on <strong>positional power</strong>. Bereft of leadership skills, however, managers with positional power become the thing of nightmares (or New Yorker cartoons).</p>

<p>A few things managers do:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Literally manages a part of the business</li>
  <li>Aligns work with strategy</li>
  <li>Green-lights projects</li>
  <li>In charge of hiring, firing, and promotions</li>
  <li>Responsible for career development</li>
  <li>Writes annual and mid-year reviews</li>
  <li>Manages P&amp;L</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="on-leadership">On Leadership</h2>

<p>Leaders, in organizations or otherwise, have the ability to bring people together; to align, inspire, and empower them towards a common vision. Leaders honor both the work to be done, and the people doing it. Their power doesn’t come from a title, but instead from the relationships they’ve built. <strong>Personal power</strong> is given to leaders by individuals who believe they are worth following and looking to for direction.</p>

<p>Historically, managers weren’t necessarily expected to have great leadership skills or experience. Positional power was enough to get the job done. These days, teams expect their managers to also be great leaders. After all, people don’t leave jobs, they leave managers.</p>

<p>A few things leaders do:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Articulates and embodies vision, values, and purpose</li>
  <li>Creates a sense of inclusion and belonging</li>
  <li>Shows up fully present</li>
  <li>Exhibits emotional and social intelligence</li>
  <li>Actively listens and invites others to the conversation</li>
  <li>Builds meaningful relationships and fosters trust</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="management--leadership-a-continuum">Management &amp; Leadership: A Continuum</h2>

<p>Management and leadership are two sides of the same coin, and it can be helpful to look at them as a continuum.</p>

<p class="essay-image-extend"><img src="/images/essays/management-leadership.png" alt="smiley" /></p>
<p class="caption">American Journal of Pharmaceutical Education 2017; 81(6) Article 102.</p>

<p>The trick is in knowing when to show up as a leader, as a manager, or as both (spoiler alert: it’s usually both). I think this is one of the most challenging things for new managers to learn, especially if they haven’t developed (or aren’t sure of) their leadership style. If you rely too much on positional power, you’ll alienate your team and come across as an autocratic leader. If you rely too much on personal power, you won’t learn how to make authoritative decisions (or build trust in your ability to make those decisions), which will significantly dampen your ability to have an impact on the business.</p>

<p>If you’ve been at this game for a while, you’ve probably developed a pretty nuanced sense for when to lead and when to manage. Even then, it can still be hard to get right!</p>

<h2 id="putting-it-into-practice">Putting It Into Practice</h2>

<p>There are three lenses that can be helpful in trying to triangulate when to lead, and when to manage: <strong>context, possibility, and action</strong>. I’m sure there are hundreds of ways to approach this and would love to learn how other folks think about it. If you are someone who spends cycles on this and are willing to share, PLEASE do (like, right here in the comments, or on Twitter, or in an email, or whatever).</p>

<p><strong>Context:</strong> Context is critical; nothing happens in a vacuum! How much do you know about the context surrounding the situation? Is there a problem?A lack of clarity? Is this within your team or across teams? What will it take to resolve it, who is involved, who is impacted, and what is the urgency? Conversely, is there excitement or a desire to do something new or different? Who do you need to convince? What is at stake?</p>

<p><strong>Possibility:</strong> What solutions or paths are available? What do you already know, what do you need to learn? Who has that information, and who might also have ideas about new possibilities? Is there appetite at the organization for multiple possibilities, or is there pressure to collapse everything into a singular possibility?</p>

<p><strong>Action:</strong> What actions can be taken to bring clarity to the situation or to a resolution/decision? What is within your mandate to do? What needs to be done by others? Do you have the time to remain open to possibilities, or is urgency requiring you to narrow things down? Who is needed to make a decision?</p>

<h2 id="an-example-scenario">An Example Scenario</h2>

<p>A new project has been green-lit for research and development. A cross-functional team has been assigned, including two members from your team who are expected to commit about 60% of their time to early exploration, alongside their day to day responsibilities. The project lead is excited (maybe a little too excited) about the potential of this new project and considers themselves a mini-CEO of the initiative. They (the project lead) begin to assign your team tasks well outside what is in scope for the project, they create silos which leads to a lack of transparency and communication, and they make promises to early clients with time frames and schedules that haven’t been backed up by other members of the team. Your team is frustrated, losing morale, and unsure of what to do.</p>

<p><em><strong>Context, possibility, action:</strong></em></p>

<p><strong>Context:</strong> A project is starting to go off the rails, your team is being impacted, and while you aren’t part of the day to day operations of this project, a big part of its early success relies on your team, and therefor you. Your team is obviously feeling the pain of this, but so is the larger project team, and the organization who is relying on this project to grow the business.</p>

<p><strong>Possibility:</strong> There are a number of possibilities in front of you: finding a way to get the cross-functional team to work together, doing some issue clearing, continuing with the status quo, creating more boundaries and silos and just stitching together the output of each person on the team (in order to avoid confrontation), or just letting the project go off the tracks entirely.</p>

<p><strong>Action:</strong> The situation demands urgency because of the importance of the project, and how people are being impacted. You have the mandate to determine what your team works on, but you don’t have mandate over the entire project. You don’t want to lose anyone, the project is important to the company, and there are a lot of complicating factors to consider.</p>

<p><em><strong>Where do you lead, and where do you manage?</strong></em></p>

<p><strong>Lead:</strong> Work with your team, teaching them frameworks and tactics for having difficult conversations. Help them process their experiences, understand their own contribution to the situation, and generate new approaches and behaviors that will open up new possibilities and ways of working. Also use leadership to foster your relationship with the project lead — spend some time with them to understand their perspective, the purpose behind their actions, and what’s blocking the team.</p>

<p><strong>Manage:</strong> This is where you exercise positional power with the project lead (though they don’t report to you, their behavior is directly impacting your team) — you need to approve what your team works on and all requests for work must run though you (make sure your team understands this as well). This removes the burden of unnecessary work being assigned and gives your team breathing room to focus on the work that needs to be done. But remember! Positional power without a side of leadership often comes off as autocratic, and you could risk impacting your relationship with the project lead. Tread carefully.</p>

<h2 id="okay-got-it-now-what">Okay, Got It. Now What?</h2>

<h3 id="keep-a-journal">Keep a Journal</h3>

<p>The best way to start to understand your own ways of leading and managing, uncover blind spots, and get a sense of your leadership style, is to keep a journal. For example, at the end of each day quickly reflect on where you lead, where you managed, and what you learned. Did you face a particularly complex and challenging situation? Jot down the context, possibilities, and actions. Which ones call for leadership, and which ones for management? After a few weeks, you’ll start to see patterns that can be great learning material for further personal and professional development.</p>

<h3 id="and-remember-its-a-balance">And Remember, It’s a Balance</h3>

<p>Day to day, the role of leadership and management blur together. As we move between tasks, meetings, and conversations we sit somewhere in the middle of the leadership &lt;-&gt; management continuum, instinctually moving across it based on our own combination of experience, training, and self-awareness. But every so often it can be beneficial to pause and reflect on the differences between the two, examining our own ways of showing up as managers and leaders. Maintaining the right balance of personal and positional power can make all the difference.</p>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Essay] On the overlap between experiential learning and designing.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/learning-through-worldmaking/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/learning-through-worldmaking/</guid>
				<pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2019 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<blockquote>
  <p>“There is no better way to gain an understanding of something than by designing it.” — Russell Ackoff</p>
</blockquote>

<p>A while back, I casually dropped an <a href="https://medium.com/@pnts/reflections-on-business-design-and-value-bb398cada721">alternative framing of design</a> as a way of learning. My intent was to articulate the activities of design, decoupled from the technics of craft, to explore how we can bring our understanding of design to business. In the intervening months, I’ve gone deeper with this framing, pulling from several theories and connecting a few more dots to help articulate the why of design as a way of learning, and to examine what makes it different.</p>

<p>As design evolves beyond a consideration of objects to answer the challenges of the 21st century, it is essential to understand what design brings to the table well beyond the current framing of design as problem solving. When we look at design as a way of learning, we expand the possibilities of where design can go and what design can do. What is unique to the designerly way of learning is that it involves making, crafting in conversation with the world in order to understand and shape it. This article serves as a snapshot of my current thinking, weaving theories and explorations into a sense of what design is and why it matters.</p>

<hr class="section-break" />

<h2 id="designing-as-reflection-in-action">Designing as Reflection-in-action</h2>

<p>Donald Schön’s work in professional education gives us insight into how learning happens in the process of working with the materials of a situation. While observing architecture students working in the studio tradition, Schön conceptualized the practice of design as a specific kind of inquiry that he called reflection-in-action; a “reflective conversation with the materials of the design situation (<a href="https://www.colorado.edu/ftep/sites/default/files/attached-files/ftep_memo_to_faculty_2.pdf">The Architectural Studio as an Exemplar of Education for Reflection in Action</a>, p. 5)”. In this configuration, knowing and making are intricately linked, as in the example of a studio master simultaneously drawing and talking in order to help a student explore some of the challenges she is facing with her own work.</p>

<p>Familiar yet abstract, this is the more tangible side of design that we experience through artifact creation and making things. In <a href="https://mitpress.mit.edu/books/design-unbound-designing-emergence-white-water-world-volume-1">Design Unbound</a>, Ann Pendleton-Julian and John Seely Brown outline this idea in a discussion of rapid iteration, stating “what is unique to design… is the capacity to think and act fluidly, not just as a repetition of sequences of thinking, acting, and prototyping but as a complex web of interaction between cognitive activity as both reasoning and imagination, and acts of making/doing to create meaningful things and context that have agency in and on a white water world. (p. 88)” Reflection-in-action invites practitioners to change the situation at hand and reshape what they are doing while they are doing it. Making is an essential part of action, usually taking the form of an artifact with its own meaning and coherence.</p>

<p class="essay-image-extend"><img src="/images/essays/reflection-in-action.png" alt="smiley" /></p>

<p>The artifacts a designer crafts in the ongoing process of reflection-in-action can be abstract or concrete; concept maps, prototypes, conversations, sketches, models, etc. Historically more attention has been given to material products and goods, but abstract artifacts are often employed in the composition of a process or system. In creating artifacts and placing them in the world—an act of transforming experiences—the designer engages in an ongoing process of reflection-in-action, manipulating the artifact and experiencing the outcomes of those changes. Herold Nelson and Erik Stolterman have a wonderful passage in <a href="https://mitpress.mit.edu/books/design-way-second-edition">The Design Way</a> that illuminates this process:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“The way design ideas are brought into the world, as crafted material, is a critical part of the design process. Producing good designs requires building successful interrelationships and interconnections with the material of the real world. As the world speaks back, joining the designer in a dialogue, we move out of a polarity between objectivity and the subjectivity into a holistic interrelationship. That which is being innovated is part of the material process itself. When a design is brought into the world, there is no longer a distinction between that-which-is and the not-yet-existing. In this conjunction, we see the real nature of our designs and how they become a part of the world. (p. 176)”</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="design-as-sensemaking">Design as Sensemaking</h2>

<p>While Schön’s theories of reflective practices illuminate how designers move from indeterminate situations to determinate ones, they are less clear on how <em>understanding</em> happens. If design studio practice is centered around “the relationship between changing things and understanding”, how does that understanding unfold?</p>

<p>Humans are meaning-makers by design. To get a sense of how understanding happens, I looked to Brenda Dervin’s <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/19970710233153/http://communication.sbs.ohio-state.edu/sense-making/lit/1983_4.html">theory of sense-making</a>. Coming from the field of communication studies, sense-making describes a process of continuous dialogue with a situation through which we arrive at stable, although limited and tentative, observations or facts. Sense-making’s core assumption is that “reality is neither complete nor constant but rather filled with fundamental and pervasive discontinuities or gaps (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/19970710233153/http://communication.sbs.ohio-state.edu/sense-making/lit/1983_4.html">p.4</a>).” It is the process of dealing with those gaps, the “constructing” activities of information seeking, that we come to some sense of understanding (this works at both individual and collective levels). Said another way, sense-making highlights our ability as humans to “circle phenomena from various perspectives… [providing] the means for us to arrive at a more comprehensive, more fully informed, potentially more useful understanding of the situation (<a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/sense-making-methodology-reader-selected-writings-of-brenda-dervin/oclc/51871729">p. 7</a>).”</p>

<p class="essay-image-extend"><img src="/images/essays/sense-making.png" alt="smiley" /></p>

<p>What’s important about sense-making, especially in understanding the meta-activities of design, is that it cedes the idea of an objective reality and assumes there is no “neutral” observing. When we design, we are in the situation we seek to understand, becoming the “maker of ideas of situations (<a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/sense-making-methodology-reader-selected-writings-of-brenda-dervin/oclc/51871729">p.67</a>).” The gap-bridging process involves both in-the-head and physical activities of making ideas, using strategies, connecting, sources, choosing words, etc. While Dervin doesn’t use the language of ‘thinking’ and ‘feeling’ in her own work, she does look at the interplay of situational and psychological experiences, the interconnectedness of inner and outer worlds of human existence, which I used to inform the mapping above. In sense-making humans are seen in through their experience-in-the-world, “as a body-mind-heart-spirit moving through time and space, with a past history, present reality, and future dreams or ambitions ( <a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/sense-making-methodology-reader-selected-writings-of-brenda-dervin/oclc/51871729">p.7</a>).” Embodied thinking and feeling captures the essence of the human in the sense-making process, bridging gaps to create meaning and understanding.</p>

<h2 id="sense-making--reflection-in-action">Sense-making + Reflection-in-action</h2>

<p class="essay-image-extend"><img src="/images/essays/learning-cycle.png" alt="smiley" /></p>

<p>If you combine Schön’s reflection-in-action with Dervin’s sense-making along two different axes, you get what looks like the Experiential Learning Cycle—a process of transforming experience into knowledge. This transformation takes place in cycles that involve two dialectics:</p>

<ol>
  <li>concrete experience (<em>feeling</em>) and abstract conceptualization (<em>thinking</em>)</li>
  <li>reflective observation (<em>reflecting</em>) and active experimentation (<em>acting</em>)</li>
</ol>

<p>Feeling and thinking are grouped together in a dialectic of “grasping experience”, while reflecting and acting comprise the “transforming experience” dialectic. Everyone goes through these cycles in the process of learning, but how you resolve the dialectics is indicative of your learning style. In Kolb’s words, “Integrated learning is a process involving a <em>creative tension</em> among the four learning modes that is responsive to contextual demands [emphasis added].”</p>

<p>If you couldn’t tell from my added emphasis, there is something very interesting in the creative tensions that exist within the learning cycle because it starts to point to <em>tension</em> as a locus of creativity, rather than design itself. It’s a subtle nuance, but useful in that we can see the tensions design methods utilize—constraints, ambiguity, sense-making, divergence, convergence, etc. foster creativity, but we can also see where those tensions exist in other fields. The history of humanity is bursting with creativity well outside the realm of design.</p>

<p>There is something unique about design as a way of learning, however, in that design is interested in what could be, rather than what is. Herbert Simon (1969) and Richard Buchanan’s (1992) assertion that the difference between science and design is that “design thinking deals primarily with what <em>does not yet exist</em>,” while science “seeks to explain <em>what is</em>.” Science discovers, design invents. Where science works to uncover an objective world, design brings forth multiple worlds simultaneously.</p>

<h2 id="worldmaking">Worldmaking</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Worldmaking as we know it always starts from worlds already on hand; the making is a remaking.” — Nelson Goodman</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Worldmaking refers to the ways we collectively make the spaces we inhabit through symbolic practices. The human drive towards meaning-making leads us to unconsciously build our world from social conditioning, scientific rationality, artistic traditions, and our own struggle for survival. In this context, worldmaking is an acknowledgment of the interpretive frames and practices that we create our worlds through rather than an assessment of the fundamental nature of physical reality. Damian Cox makes sense of this in the following way:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Goodman’s worldmaking is a disciplined business. We do not always make worlds when we manipulate symbols. Worldmaking is constrained by coherence, consistency, the fit with intuitive judgement and intelligible purpose and these virtues add up to what Goodman calls the “rightness” of a version. Right versions make worlds, and are produced by many different kinds of people. Scientists create worlds; philosophers create worlds; artists create worlds; an advertising agency might create a world. World’s are the product of any ambitious, successful attempt to create an order of things (“<a href="https://www.academia.edu/6111032/Goodman_and_Putnam_on_the_Making_of_Worlds">Goodman and Putnam on the Making of Worlds</a> p. 36”).</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Design makes worldmaking visible, transforming it into a conscious act through intentionality, awareness, and an interest in the ways in which the world could be. In the process of articulating these worlds, the things that we make—the nouns—are expressions and references to the underlying logic of the world in creation. Worldmaking in some ways could be considered the essence of design experimentation, something Schön pointed to in his discussion of virtual worlds. For the designer, the ability to “construct and manipulate virtual worlds is a crucial component to his ability not only to perform artistically but to experiment rigorously (<a href="https://www.thriftbooks.com/w/educating-the-reflective-practitioner-toward-a-new-design-for-teaching-and-learning-in-the-professions-higher-education-series_donald-a-schn/272745/?mkwid=s0GErMpGO%7Cdc&amp;pcrid=70112878392&amp;pkw=&amp;pmt=&amp;plc=&amp;pgrid=21323665512&amp;ptaid=pla-292616666626&amp;gclid=EAIaIQobChMI0sf2qNnV4wIVg56fCh0K7ggXEAQYAyABEgK0o_D_BwE#isbn=1555420257&amp;idiq=8790061">p. 75</a>).”</p>

<p>Going back to the idea of materials, Nelson Goodman offers a subset of methods that contribute to worldmaking: composition and decomposition, weighting, ordering, deletion &amp; supplementation, and deformation. Pairing this with H. Nelson and Stolterman’s articulation that “materials are what a designer brings together using structural connections or compositional relationships (p. 174),” and keeping in mind that materials are not limited to the physical, we start to get a curious inclination of how broad the meta-activities of design can go.</p>

<p>Design is a dynamic and unending cycle of grasping and transforming experience through the process of worldmaking. When coupled with the technics of design as craft, we can see worlds emerge through our experience of a brand, a service, or a product tied together through the logic of business in an invitation to a certain way of being. But we can move into other areas with different materials—business, organizations, governments, policy—and begin to use design to bring forth new worlds and possibilities.</p>

<hr class="section-break" />

<p>In the 20th century design, tightly coupled with craft, combined intentionality and human-centered practices to create things that people valued. The challenges of the 21st century invite us to move beyond things and to design for complexity and emergence. In order to do this we must move our work to higher levels of perception, applying the fluidity of thinking, acting, and understanding to our conversations with indeterminate situations. My specific interest is in how the activities of design can inform the practice of worldmaking in organizations, exploring new ways of working that facilitate flourishing at the individual, company, and societal levels. Beyond business, the importance of design as learning through worldmaking configures design as a meta-cognitive activity through which we explore and bring forth new possibilities in any domain. Attuned to ideas of what could be, design is the way by which we consciously move through reflection-in-action and sense-making in order to bring forth new worlds.</p>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

  </channel>
</rss>
