<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"

	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	>

  <channel>
  	<title>the becoming</title>
    <atom:link href="https://methodandmatter.com/the-becoming/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <link>https://methodandmatter.com/the-becoming</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <generator>Middleman (Ruby)</generator>
    <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>
		<description>A newsletter at the edge of the known and the unknown.</description>
		<meta property="og:image" content="https://methodandmatter.com/images/mm-round.png" />
    <image>
      <url>https://methodandmatter.com/images/mm-round.png</url>
      <title>method &#038; matter</title>
      <link>https://methodandmatter.com</link>
    </image>



      <item>
        <title>the becoming 013</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com//the-becoming/013/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com//the-becoming/013/</guid>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


        <description>
          <![CDATA[
            <p class="caption"><img src="/images/kp/013.jpg" alt="Sutro Tower" />
Figurine of a monk. Lan Su Chinese Garden, Portland, Oregon.</p>

<p>I went to bed early on election night, after 30 uneasy minutes listening to Steve Kornacki’s brisk county-by-county trend analysis.</p>

<p>The following morning, I watched wrens futz around in the sunlit bushes outside my window for half an hour before getting out of bed. Movement came slowly. I crept through the tender stillness of the house suspended in a probability space of unknowing. MAGA was neither dead nor alive.</p>

<p>I sat down to journal before collapsing the state vector, aka checking the news. As I wrote I realized that in some ways it didn’t matter who won because <em>at least half</em> of America wants what TFG is selling. And then I looked at my phone.</p>

<p><em>What the fucking fuck?</em></p>

<p>In 2016, in an attempt to suppress feelings of apocalyptic terror, I set about <em>figuring it out</em>.  What did I miss? What were MAGA folks thinking? What could help me empathize with their world view? I subscribed to several conservative magazines and news outlets, talked with folks who had voted Republican, and tried to find something solid enough to respond to, something to pinpoint in future conversations that would ensure this couldn't happen again. I never found that perfect leverage point, but by the time the 2020 elections rolled around I didn’t need one. Folks who had voted for Trump the first time were tired of his antics. It felt like maybe the lurch towards fascism (née nationalism) was a bizarre anomaly.</p>

<p>This time? None of that. We know so much more now — January 6th, 34 felony convictions, bathrooms as file storage for top secret information, and the most completely unhinged and violent rhetoric imaginable. And yet <em>even more people said yes</em>. This time I am not pouring through right-wing news sources and message boards trying to understand. I haven’t read a lick of the hot-takes that have flooded my inbox. There is no air for logic and reason to breathe. I can’t think. The tools I used to have — the concepts, categories, and language, connected in networks of meaning through which I made sense of the world — no longer work.</p>

<p>This time I am not going to try and figure it out. Instead, I am going to stay <em>bewildered</em>. Because sometimes there is more clarity in bewilderment than there is in answers.</p>

<hr />

<p>This fall I attended <strong>Making Sanctuary: Leadership and Change at the Edges of the Human</strong>, a five week seminar put on by the <a href="https://www.aspeninstitute.org">Aspen Institute</a> with <a href="https://www.bayoakomolafe.net">Báyò Akómoláfé</a> as our poet-instigator-guide. Akómoláfé is someone whose lyrical provocations and fugitive explorations reveal new and uncertain terrains of being. Whose way with words and poetic invitations gesture towards possibilities of how we can begin to think anew.</p>

<p>The class was a revelation, an undoing of familiar ways of knowing into underworlds of more-than-human becomings. We explored many things — monsters and spillage and carnival, to name a few  — but the one I want to mention here is the idea of the Behemoth (yes, the one from Job 40:15-24).</p>

<p>For Akómoláfé, the Behemoth is an impervious system displaying a set of conditions “that absorb or deflect attempts at change, maintaining overall systemic patterns despite surface-level alterations.” Or what Aníbal Quijano calls the <a href="https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-031-08042-5_5">Colonial Matrix of Power</a> (CMP) an, “abstract mechanism, like the unconscious in psychoanalysis… the unconscious of Western civilization that… conceals coloniality, the logic of exploitation, multiple oppressions, and expropriation.” The Behemoth and the CMP are massive, beyond human comprehension. <a href="https://www.societyandspace.org/articles/hyperobjects-by-timothy-morton">Timothy Morton</a> uses the word <em>hyperobject</em> to talk about the “immense, structural forces all around us, and even inside us, that we cannot see with our eyes.”  Reason, as a cartographic practice, cannot possibly map something so immense and invisible (not for lack of trying, tho).</p>

<p>For <a href="https://archive.org/details/david-bohm-thought-as-a-system">David Bohm</a>, reason (as thought) itself is part of the problem. Thought is not simply an intellectual activity, but a process that includes feelings and the body, a process that passes <em>between</em> people creating a system in which every part is dependent on every other part. Thought imbricates us in an ecological field of thinking-feeling-sensing.  The flaw in our thinking happens when we see something “wrong” with a part of the system and try to fix it using another part of the system. In an attempt to avoid uncomfortable feelings we seek ever more draconian forms of control. But this just adds more problems, creating what I like to call “the ouroboros of problem solving.” We lack the ability to stay with difficulty, to sit in our unpleasant feelings and resist the temporary relief of solutions.</p>

<p>Staying with the problem, or rather the trouble, is exactly what <a href="https://www.dukeupress.edu/staying-with-the-trouble">Donna Haraway</a> urges us to do:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Staying with the trouble does not require such a relationship to times called the future. In fact, staying with the trouble requires learning to be truly present, not as a vanishing pivot between awful or edenic pasts and apocalyptic or salvific futures, but as mortal critters entwined in myriad unfinished configurations of places, times, matters, meanings. p. 1</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Folks like Akómoláfé, Bohm, Morton, and Haraway are all thinking beyond what we’ve been given. Encountering their work flips the familiar on its head and troubles what once seemed so certain. In this space of unknowing we are invited to let go of control and turn towards what is here now — material networks of oddkin copresencing the world from moment to moment. In this, Haraway reminds us that neither hope nor despair are useful attitudes, and invites us into the material world of the senses so that we may deeply inhabit the thick present:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Alone, in our separate kinds of expertise and experience, we know both too much and too little, and so we succumb to despair or to hope, and neither is a sensible attitude. Neither despair nor hope is tuned to the senses, to mindful matter, to material semiotics, to mortal earthlings in thick copresence. p. 4</p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<p>In the year 2000 Hopi Elders shared a prophecy, <a href="https://www.awakin.org/v2/read/view.php?tid=702">We are the Ones We’ve Been Waiting For</a>. I'm including it here in its entirity because it is impossible to excerpt without losing its exquisite context and meaning.</p>

<p><strong>We are the Ones We’ve Been Waiting For</strong></p>

<p><em>You have been telling people that this is the Eleventh Hour, now you must go back and tell the people that this is the Hour. And there are things to be considered…</em></p>

<p><em>Where are you living?</em><br />
<em>What are you doing?</em><br />
<em>What are your relationships?</em><br />
<em>Are you in right relation?</em><br />
<em>Where is your water?</em></p>

<p><em>Know your garden.</em><br />
<em>It is time to speak your truth.</em><br />
<em>Create your community.</em><br />
<em>Be good to each other.</em><br />
<em>And do not look outside yourself for your leader.</em></p>

<p><em>Then he clasped his hands together, smiled, and said, “This could be a good time! There is a river flowing now very fast. It is so great and swift that there are those who will be afraid. They will try to hold on to the shore. They will feel they are being torn apart and will suffer greatly. Know the river has its destination. The elders say we must let go of the shore, push off into the middle of the river, keep our eyes open, and our heads above the water.</em></p>

<p><em>And I say, see who is in there with you and celebrate. At this time in history, we are to take nothing personally, least of all ourselves. For the moment that we do, our spiritual growth and journey come to a halt.</em></p>

<p><em>The time of the lone wolf is over. Gather yourselves! Banish the word ’struggle’ from your attitude and your vocabulary. All that we do now must be done in a sacred manner and in celebration.</em></p>

<p><em>We are the ones we’ve been waiting for.”</em></p>

<p>Let go of the shore, push off into the middle, keep our eyes open, and our heads above water. Carried along by fast flowing currents, we cannot logic our way through turbulent waters, only move with them.  Bewilderment isn’t a means of bypassing or turning away, it is a staying with, learning how to navigate and think in new ways, alert to what may emerge in the churn.</p>

<p>And what of the invitation to celebration and good times? When fascism is knocking at the door it can seem downright disrespectful to indulge in something akin joy. But I'd wager the elders have it exactly right. My dad shared something similar with me earlier this year during a dinner in Buenos Aires:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Recupero mi alegría sin perder mi indignación. El neoliberalismo quiere que nos muramos viejas y amargadas. Pero no le vamos a dar el gusto.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>I recover my joy without losing my indignation. Neoliberalism wants us to die old and bitter. But we won't give it that satisfaction.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Joy does not negate pain, anger, and all the other feels that are swirling right now. But losing our joy disconnects us from each other, and from life. Pema Chödrön knows a thing or two about this, as she writes so eloquently in <em>Living Beautifully</em>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I realized then what it means to hold pain in my heart and simultaneously be deeply touched by the power and magic of the world. Life doesn't have to be one way or the other. We don't have to jump back and forth. We can live beautifully with whatever comes—heartache and joy, success and failure, instability and change.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>And so here I sit, bewildered and unmoored, staying with the trouble, shedding old logics, looking not for answers but for cracks, and joyfully attuning to increasingly strange ecologies of becoming.</p>

<p>I love you. Let's all take good care of each other.</p>

          ]]>
        </description>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>the becoming 012</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com//the-becoming/012/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com//the-becoming/012/</guid>
        <pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2024 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


        <description>
          <![CDATA[
            <p>Hi!</p>

<p>It’s been a minute.</p>

<p>Or six months, if you’re counting.</p>

<p class="caption"><img src="/images/kp/012.jpg" alt="Sutro Tower" />
Sutro Tower, San Francisco.</p>

<p>First, a few logistical matters. Those of you who have been around a while will notice some visual changes. Last month I migrated my newsletters over to <a href="https://buttondown.email">Buttondown</a> after a less-than-stellar experience with Convertkit. I’ve been really happy with the service so far, though I am still figuring out how to customize the templates so you’re getting a kind of out-of-the-box experience right now. But what I really wanted to share about this new arrangement is that Buttondown allows me to turn off tracking pixels. I am happy to say that now both my website <em>and</em> my newsletters <em>do not track you</em>. I have no clue if you open or read the newsletter, what you click on, or anything else for that matter and I am <em>thrilled</em> to not know. The only thing I have insight into is deliverability and who unsubscribed. But really just deliverability because I don’t check unsubscribes - you have every right to go whenever you want to and I do not need to know that you have gone.</p>

<p class="archive-notice">This is an archived version of <strong>the becoming</strong>. You can sign up to receive future editions using the form at the bottom of this page.</p>

<p>And for those of you reading the above going, “wait, what is this thing in my inbox?” my name is <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/about/">Andi</a> and this is <em><a href="https://methodandmatter.com/the-becoming/">the becoming</a></em>, a newsletter at the edge of the known and unknown. It is here, at this edge, that we have the best chance of <a href="https://www.bayoakomolafe.net/post/getting-lost">getting lost</a> — losing our way, our coordinates, and what thought we knew of the world. Getting lost helps us remember the primacy of relationality and reconfigures how we inhabit dominant systems while simultaneously revealing the nature of the world around us. Getting lost is a kind of <a href="https://docs.ufpr.br/~clarissa/pdfs/DeLinking_Mignolo2007.pdf">delinking</a>, a way of exposing human meddling that discloses the reality that what has been naturalized is, in fact, not very natural at all.</p>

<p>If that sounds interesting to you, then welcome.</p>

<p>Each issue contains a personal essay, links I’ve found interesting for one reason or another, and sometimes updates on my research. That being said, since we are practicing getting lost together, I cannot promise with any surety what this newsletter actually is or will become.</p>

<hr />

<p>So yeah, about that six months thing.</p>

<p>2023: Late summer transitioned to early fall and work commitments took over. Nothing out of the ordinary, some interesting work and lovely people to collaborate with on topics that I care about but then… October happened. The essays I had been working on suddenly felt faded and musty, old letters forgotten in the attic for decades, quaint and for the most part irrelevant to what the world had become. It felt impossible to write. The only thing I could write about was grief.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>What I have come to realize in my own process this fall is that grief is important and necessary. As my colleague <a href="https://www.katherinemccabe.com">Katherine McCabe</a> says, “we must all become grief warriors.” Grief is action, grief is the necessary step to accept where we are and let the reality of that place flow through us.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I wasn’t the only one whose writing practice changed. Ben Ehrenreich writes in Issue 1 of <a href="https://flaminghydra.com">Flaming Hydra</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>And though writing has been the tool that in the past allowed me to crawl through every darkness, I have had a hard time writing my way through this one. Or writing at all. Or even imagining the possibility of seeing through it to some other side. What other side could we consent to live in if it was in any way continuous with this?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I was also reminded of Daniel Schmactenberger’s advice for living in trying times: feel depressed. He elaborates, “you <em>should</em> feel depressed. If you don’t you are a psychopath.” His comment was a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4kBoLVvoqVY">reference to the metacrisis</a>, which makes the sentiment broadly applicable to whatever terrible thing you choose as your particular depression <em>du jour</em>. But there is wisdom in this — in grief and depression and the understanding of what these important emotions want to share with us. And it is also <em>necessary</em> to be exactly where we are, here, in the middle of it all and know that this is where we are. We cannot pretend to be anywhere else — as long as we do our responses will be incongruent and inadequate.</p>

<p>Finding ourselves in the middle of it all is uncomfortable. It wasn’t supposed to happen this way, and yet here we are. When I stopped writing this fall, “it all” was the attack on Israel and the subsequent and ongoing genocide of the Palestinian people. Other times “it all” is the violence of unregulated capitalism and white supremacy, industrialized ways of living that have pushed us well beyond sustainable planetary boundaries, the rabid desire to control women’s bodies, erasure of trans rights and trans people, the neoliberal project, rising fascism, cynicism, the entrenchment of the billionaire class, the war against poor people, racism and anti-Blackness, and rampant ongoing settler-colonialism. To name a few.</p>

<p>A common response is to ask, “Well, what do we <em>do?</em> What can be <em>done</em>? How do we <em>fix this?</em>” We turn to action to shield us of the discomfort of seeing our own complicity. But this action, when taken from an unchanged place of being, extends the logic of known knowns and clear categorization in service of <em>solutions</em>. By “unchanged place of being” I mean this: we are shaped by the systems we grew up in — society, family, religion, education, etc. — and for the most part that shaping feels like how the world really <em>is</em>. If we cannot <em>see</em> this shaping and begin to interrogate it not as reality but as a system of living that defines our being, then actions we take will extend the logic of the system because we are of the system and created by the system. If we do not see this we have no choice but to perpetuate it.</p>

<p>So we come to action from an unchanged place of being, seeking to know what got us here so we can get ourselves out. To this end we take a snapshot of the world and dissect it to fuel our analysis so that we can <em>know</em>.  But the snapshot is not the map is not the territory, and when we forget this we end up mistaking our abstractions for reality. We believe we have solid ground to stand on, but the brittleness of our analytics constructions cannot hold weight.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“The impatient idealist says: 'Give me a place to stand and I shall move the earth.' But such a place does not exist. We all have to stand on the earth itself and go with her at her pace.” ― Chinua Achebe, No Longer at Ease</p>
</blockquote>

<p>To come from a changed place of being we have to stand on the earth. We have to get wise to our own shaping and the systems that have done that shaping. We have to accept what we have created and where we are, and we have to grieve everything we have lost.</p>

<p>For me the last many months have been a lot of the above — feeling the feels and standing on the earth and interrogating my own shaping. And letting that be an okay place to be because that’s where I was.</p>

<p>It is not lost on me that all of this coincided with the winter months here in the northern hemisphere. The short days and long nights invite inward movements of reflection, the stillness and dormancy of the seed as it prepares for germination in the early days of Spring.</p>

<p>Having recently passed Imbolc, and with the days getting longer, something is stirring in me again. I have more clarity and commitment to what this newsletter wants to be and what it is part of: a line of work that will cover years, maybe decades, perhaps even the rest of my life. On my (now archived) research page I talked about this work as:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“… one of scholarship but also of healing, weaving, and integrating. I seek to understand the ways in which we have deworlded ourselves from nature, how our neurobiology became complicit with technology to abstract us from the feedback loops critical to our connection with each other and with the more-than-human world. And to also understand the practices of tending that bring us back into right relationship with our brain, soma, technology, and nature so that we can remember the deeply spiritual role we play as an integral part of the Gaian system.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>You can expect more of this in future issues.</p>

<hr />

<p>Imbolc also brought this <a href="https://myemail.constantcontact.com/At-Imbolc--SM366--An-Experimental-Musing-between-Geneen-Marie-Haugen---Bill-Plotkin.html?soid=1102010840526&amp;aid=znZZc6yws_Q">lovely</a> <a href="https://myemail.constantcontact.com/SM367--Sudden-Collective-Consciousness-Shift--An-Experimental-Musing-between-Geneen-Marie-Haugen---Bill-Plotkin--Part-II.html?soid=1102010840526&amp;aid=0SLmm_JKR_M">conversation</a> between life partners Bill Plotkin and Geneen Marie Haugen to my inbox. A dialogue about the destabilizing times we are in, the questions worth asking, and the new stories we might start to live.</p>

<p>Here are a few of the inquiries Geneen poses early in the conversation:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Where is the ground (the psychospiritual ground, the psychophysical ground), the anchor point, that is most nourished now by our particular ways of tending? How do we live most coherently with the unfolding cosmos? How do our grand philosophies and spiritual practices best take root in our everyday lives?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I love these questions. They feel right to think about. And the word <em>tending</em> feels especially resonant. I'm imagining tending as a tender response to the grief, sadness, and depression of the last six months. It evokes care and right-sizedness, a gentle turning-towards that which is life giving. That which is true. A way of accepting and welcoming what we are in, as well as a way of listening to what is emerging and building a relationship with it.</p>

<p>Tending is a reminder that we are an integral part of this world. That our role isn’t to control, but to care for. Tending is a collaborative relationship with forces greater than us (call it spirit, teotl, the universe, Gaia, energy, whatever), a daily ritual of attention and devotion of being in the world and of the world.</p>

<p>As we move from Imbolc to the equinox my intention is to hold tending as an inquiry - what does my tending nourish, and how I am nourished in return? How does tending connect the inner and outer worlds of my own emergence and becoming? What is the relationship between tending, surrender, and care? What new configurations and relationships are possible when tending is prioritized?</p>

<p>I invite you to join me. To slow down, stand on the earth, and tend to what matters most to you.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="worth-your-attention">Worth Your Attention</h2>

<p>Dialogue is the art of attuning to what is present in “the field” - the merging of experience through the practice of conversation - sharing ideas through explicit interactions. <a href="http://jakobgreenfeld.com/emergent-conversations/">Emergent vs Transactional Conversations</a> is a variation on this theme with a particular orientation to work, and exposes why some conversations are co-creative, energizing, and emergent while others are flat, predictable, and uninspiring.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.lrb.co.uk/the-paper/v46/n03/rebecca-solnit/in-the-shadow-of-silicon-valley">In the Shadow of Silicon Valley</a> - Rebecca Solnit brings the fire to the techno-accelerationist transformation of Northern California. I appreciate this piece because of the way Solnit uses stories and personal narrative rather than abstractions and theory as she traces the history of our current moment through the semiotics of self-driving cars (one of which was <a href="https://sfstandard.com/2024/02/10/waymo-robotaxi-goes-up-in-flames-in-chinatown-after-crowd-attacks-vehicle/">torched</a> during the Lunar New Year celebrations here in SF).</p>

<p>Emergence is definitely a theme here at <em>the becoming</em>.  To that end I would be remiss not brining attention to <a href="https://emergence.maxcooper.net">Max Cooper’s Emergence</a> project, a piece of work exploring emergence across multiple mediums and formats including an album, live shows, storytelling, and audio and visual content. Starting from before the big-bang and taking us up to the present moment, the explorations and collaborations are rich, mesmerizing, and thought-provoking.</p>

<p>If you don't want to or currently can't dedicate the time to reading Iain McGilchrist's two volume series "<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Matter_with_Things">The Matter With Things: Our Brains, Our Delusions, and the Unmaking of the World</a>," then be sure to check out <a href="https://perspecteeva.substack.com/p/understanding-iain-mcgilchrists-worldview">David McIlroy's summary</a> over at Perspectiva.</p>

<p>On Tuesday I start a 7 week course, <a href="https://www.mutations.blog/seeing-through-2024">Seeing Through the World: Jean Gebser and Integral Consciousness</a>. I’ve been wanting to take this course since I first heard Jeremy Johnson talk about Gebser’s work, which feels so directly related to what I am exploring here at <em>the becoming</em>. Johnson writes, “The future lives in us. In this moment of civilizational crisis, Gebser’s time has come yet again to help us navigate a liminal age of worldview transition. <strong>We must learn to be sufficiently present in order to live the future that is already living us.</strong>” I believe enrollment is still open!</p>

<hr />

<p>Thanks for sticking around ❤️.</p>

<p>Andi</p>

          ]]>
        </description>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>the becoming 011</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com//the-becoming/011/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com//the-becoming/011/</guid>
        <pubDate>Thu, 31 Aug 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


        <description>
          <![CDATA[
            <p>I can feel the days getting shorter as we creep into fall but we're not there yet! San Francisco has delivered a burst of beautiful (and warm) weather that I am enjoying alongside a sweet pitbull who is visiting for the week. I'm Andi, this is the becoming, and welcome to August's missive.</p>

<p class="caption"><img src="/images/kp/011.jpg" alt="Tumalo Waterfalls" />
Chasing waterfalls in Tumalo, Oregon.</p>

<h3 id="the-paradox-of-why">The Paradox of Why</h3>

<p>I’ve been sitting with some BIG unknowing this month and wondering how best to tend to this specific state of being. How to stay connected with the felt sense of… being reorganized on a molecular level is probably the best way to put it, and how to maintain an open connection to the process of transformation. In working with dreams the dreamer is encouraged to presence the dream, to be with the landscapes, beings, and animals as alive and vibrant as they were when initial contact was made in the dreamworld. The worst thing you can do with dreams is to analyze them, zapping them of their vitality and reducing them to static, singular messages. I think the same goes for being in connection with the unknown in a way that feels nourishing and supportive. Where the textured complexity of the world hums its aliveness, rather than being reduced to the silence of flat, smooth surfaces. And I’ve come to realize that one of the primary ways to sever this connection, that can reduce the beautiful complexity of unknowing to a lifeless morass, is the seemly simple ‘why?’ question.</p>

<p>Sidenote: I apologize for the clunkiness of the ‘why?’ and ‘why’ in quotation marks throughout this piece, but I think (hope) it brings clarity to the reading experience.</p>

<p class="archive-notice">This is an archived version of <strong>the becoming</strong>. You can sign up to receive future editions using the form at the bottom of this page.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://www.etymonline.com/word/why#etymonline_v_7987">etymology of the word why</a> comes from the Old English <em>hwi</em> to indicate for what purpose or by what means. I’m sure in olden times it was an innocuous word but I can’t help but read it in a voice that demands <em>justification</em> for whatever (or whomever) is on the receiving end of <em>hwi</em>.</p>

<p>Of course it’s vitally important to understand the why of things, but paradoxically asking why questions doesn’t really get us to what we want to know. ‘Why?’ closes the aperture of our perception instead of opening it to the complexity, wonder, and awe required to behold and understand something like purpose.</p>

<p>‘Why?’ is a shorthand invocation that points to something and asks, “what is the reason for this to be the way it is?” The question and intention itself may be well and good, but the response often falls short of the meaning we seek. Think back to the last time you asked a why question. Something like, “Why did you do that?” Or “Why not try this instead?” Did you learn the real purpose and get the clarity you were looking for? Or did something else happen that impacted the dynamics of the relationship? Maybe one or both of you ended up feeling a little defensive.</p>

<p>‘Why?’ is like dropping a small turd into the middle of a conversation. The receiver feels offended and the questioner becomes both embarrassed and defensive, startled by the not so favorable reaction of the receiver. Frustratingly neither person is closer to understanding than before.</p>

<p>Because here is the thing: ‘why?’ takes us out of direct experience and moves us into an analytical mode. We don’t answer from direct experience and what is happening in the moment, instead we remove ourselves from what we are in contact with in order to attempt root-cause analysis in the midst of complexity. And the moment we make this move we lose contact with the layered richness of experience through a reductive act of cause and effect.</p>

<p>We are <em>notoriously bad</em> at using logic to figure out what we’re really up to in the world, we can’t analytically trace a chain of events to a single cause (and also half of our motivations exist below the level of consciousness). Maybe I did the thing you are asking about because of something that happened to me 10 years ago that is subconsciously influencing my behavior in certain situations.</p>

<p>‘Why?’ as a <em>question</em> is causal. ‘Why’ as an <em>understanding</em> is systemic. But we can’t get to systemic understandings by asking causal questions (if only that shortcut worked). We have to do the heavy lifting of critical thinking and deep inquiry to get there.</p>

<p>To be clear I’m not advocating to remove the word from circulation! It would be impossible to eliminate ‘why?’ from the mouths of every 3 year old on the planet, and ‘why?’ has some use in scientific and process oriented endeavors. But more often than not, ‘why?’ diverts us from the reflective rigor needed to understand what it is we really want to know.</p>

<p>Let’s look at how ‘why?’ behaves in fact-based situations with the age old favorite, “Why is the sky blue?”</p>

<p>Light waves from the sun hit our atmosphere. Certain wavelengths pass through while others - blue and violet - are <a href="https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/why-is-the-sky-blue/">scattered by the gases and particles</a> in the air, which is why the sky is blue on a sunny day. But the sky is also blue because of the <a href="http://www.atmo.arizona.edu/students/courselinks/fall12/atmo170a1s1/lecture_notes/scattering/why_not_violet.html">physiology of the human eye</a> and the particular wavelengths of light they are able to receive. <em>Two</em> wavelengths are scattered, blue and violet, but our eyes are more sensitive to blue than violet. So the sky isn’t really blue at all, it just appears blue to us. There is an interplay between physics and physiology, between observer and observed, so that the world is never quite as we think it is.</p>

<p>Curiosity is a beautiful human trait and ‘why?’ is the delivery mechanism of choice for small children learning about the world. But for adults, outside of certain circumstances, why is a knee-jerk reaction - a quick formulation of a question that hasn’t been given enough time to be understood and formed with the right words. The desire to know is present, to understand the purpose or reason, but asking ‘why?’ doesn’t get us to a core cause of human behavior or the mysterious ‘why’ of the emergent world.</p>

<p>‘Why?’ is complex and defined by the relationship between observer and observed. If you really tend to your wondering you’ll probably arrive at a more rigorous question along the lines of, “What causes the sky to appear blue <em>to us</em>?” And after you have formed this question, curiosity may lead you to wonder what color the sky is for other animals, or what color the sky is if no one is observing it. How rich the inquiry becomes! The world is not reduced to a universal maxim of The Sky Is Blue, but is revealed in its full dynamic complexity and mystery.</p>

<p>Other forms of lazy why questions include:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Why is that important to you?</li>
  <li>Why do you like that?</li>
  <li>Why did you make that decision?</li>
</ul>

<p>Fortunately, we have other interrogatives that can help us uncover ‘why’ while allowing people to stay in contact with their direct experience: who, what, when, where and the <a href="https://hbr.org/2021/10/stop-asking-why-and-start-asking-how">one h - how</a>. Eliminating ‘why’ as a question will lead you to a deeper understanding of the purpose or means of whatever it is you are curious about. For more on the specifics of how to ask questions without asking why, see Rebecca Berry’s insightful article, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/why-you-should-stop-asking-what-ask-instead-rebecca-berry/">Why you stop asking why (and what to ask instead)</a>.  If you are a designer looking to understand the ‘why’ and want to improve your ideation prompts, sheryl cabana has your back with, <a href="https://medium.com/artefact-stories/design-for-meaning-rethinking-designs-ideation-prompts-13fa6c02ba3c">Design for Meaning: Rethinking Design’s Ideation Prompts</a>.</p>

<p>Here are those why questions again, reworded:</p>

<ul>
  <li>What makes that important to you? What resonates most deeply for you?</li>
  <li>What do you like about that? How is that for you?</li>
  <li>What was behind that decision?</li>
</ul>

<p>Anyone who has been on the receiving end of a why question knows how judgmental they can feel. I frequently forget to turn the oven off after baking, and my boyfriend will wander in and say, “why is the oven on?”  Immediately I find myself getting a little snippy and defensive. My internal monologue goes something like, “I made cookies earlier and as I pulled the last tray out of the oven I got a phone call and that diverted my attention and because I can’t multitask I moved into that activity and left the cookie making behind and I guess I’m a terrible person. Shit, who knows, maybe it has something to do with having jaundice as a baby.” In this case a simple, “What is the oven on for?” would be great and save me from going down a rabbit hole of negative character analysis.</p>

<p>Some of you may be wondering about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Five_whys">The Five Whys</a>, a method pioneered by Toyota in the 80s. If you are analyzing a process, go for it. But if you are analyzing human behavior, try and stay away from it. Approaches like The Five Whys can be really useful when seeking to understand cause and effect in complicated systems, but when sitting in complexity where cause and effect are <em>loosely</em> correlated, asking why can take us in the wrong direction, alienate others, and ultimately fail to help us understand the very thing we are seeking clarity on.</p>

<p>Give it a try this week. Whenever you catch yourself reaching for ‘why?’ pause and think about what it is you <em>really</em> want to know. And then use a non-why interrogative instead. And I will continue to tend to the BIG unknowing that has made its way to my doorstep, allowing it to be full and mysterious by not needing to know what, exactly, is its purpose.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="leader-as-coach">Leader as Coach</h3>
<p>A quick update on <a href="https://maven.com/andrea-mignolo/leader-as-coach">Leader as Coach</a> - the upcoming cohort has been pushed back 2 weeks and is now starting October 2nd. For those of you who had schedule conflicts with the earlier dates, hopefully this now aligns with your schedule! Discount codes are available to subscribers of <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/the-becoming">the becoming</a> and <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds">Words Make Worlds</a>.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="worth-your-attention">Worth Your Attention</h3>
<p>Neuroscientist Daniel Toker takes a look at how the theory of the triune brain - the idea that we have a lizard brain, mammalian brain, and primate/human brain - became widespread even though, from the get go, <a href="https://thebrainscientist.com/2018/04/11/you-dont-have-a-lizard-brain/">evolutionary neuroscientists had a sense that it wasn't right</a>. It's a fun read, and you don't have to hold an advanced degree to follow along.</p>

<p>Marketing is hard, and the techniques recommended by "experts" often feel manipulative and sleezy. I was complaining about this to a friend last week and he shared a resource that kinda blew my socks off - <a href="https://marketingforhippies.com">Marketing for Hippies</a>. The site is great, the copy is fun, and there are lots of free resources to get started. But the best part! The best part are the "<a href="https://marketingforhippies.com/puttering/">Putting Sessions</a>" that Tad offers. I have never seen anything quite like it and DELIGHTED is probably the best way to describe my reaction to the whole endeavor. Go read it, enjoy, maybe book a session. And feel your faith in humanity restored just a little bit more.</p>

<p>"<a href="https://nonprofitquarterly.org/healing-centered-leadership-a-path-to-transformation/">Healing-centered leadership</a> acknowledges how we all have been harmed, and focuses on restoring relationships across differences. This means that healing-centered leaders practice empathy over blame, compassion over complacency, and curiosity over criticism. The only path to reimagining the future is through healing our collective trauma and restoring a sense of possibility in our work. This can only happen when we foster a collective imagination that restores communal wisdom and sets a path toward more humane ways to show up in life." - Shawn A. Ginwright</p>

<p>Inline with the topic of this edition's essay is <a href="http://imaginaljourneying.com">Imaginal Journeying</a>, a process of staying connected to the imaginal realm typically accessed through dreams and subconscious explorations. The copy on the site states "it can open a door into a direct and intimate connection with the depths and richness of the full range of human and collective experience. This unleashes creativity, deepens emotional resonance, heals trauma, uncovers true purpose and unlocks new paradigms for people." I first started learning and working with the imaginal realms through Stephen Aizenstat's Dream Tending work, and continue to find resonance with folks who are exploring this space.</p>

<p><a href="https://bookshop.org/p/books/learning-to-learn-and-the-navigation-of-moods-the-meta-skill-for-the-acquisition-of-skills-stuart-e-dreyfus-phd/11324350?ean=9780692801796">Learning to Learn and the Navigation of Moods</a> is a book I turn to often. If you don't have time to read the book, <a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/pDeRAi3Ysv7AK4xax/learning-to-learn-and-navigating-moods">here are</a> a <a href="https://blas.com/learning-to-learn-moods/">few summaries</a> that are a pretty quick read and give you some useful food for thought to take into both your work and personal life.</p>

<hr />

<p>Thank you for being here and see you next month!</p>

          ]]>
        </description>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>the becoming 010</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com//the-becoming/010/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com//the-becoming/010/</guid>
        <pubDate>Mon, 31 Jul 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


        <description>
          <![CDATA[
            <p>I would be remiss to not say hello for July, though this month is without a long-form essay. Not for lack of effort, but the writing hasn’t coalesced into something tangible enough to share. Which caused a mild freak-out as I contemplated the trail of <a href="https://www.pagesandplatforms.com/blog/how-to-finish-your-zero-draft">zero drafts</a> in my wake and felt the pressure of winnowing days, providing a front-row seat to how I create the drama of my life.</p>

<p class="caption"><img src="/images/kp/010.jpg" alt="Mt Bachelor sunset" />
Chasing sunset near Mt. Bachelor, Oregon.</p>

<p class="archive-notice">This is an archived version of <strong>the becoming</strong>. You can sign up to receive future editions using the form at the bottom of this page.</p>

<p>Essay aside, I have been writing up a storm this month. While the becoming’s July essay didn’t quite get there, I did post a number of articles on Medium: <a href="https://medium.com/wordsmakeworlds/the-coaching-leadership-style-developing-self-and-developing-others-2f3fd665ba6d">The Coaching Leadership Style</a>, <a href="https://medium.com/wordsmakeworlds/12-essential-books-for-leaders-who-coach-a7620fce706a">12 Essential Books for Leaders Who Coach</a>, <a href="https://medium.com/wordsmakeworlds/the-mindset-qualities-and-posture-of-a-coach-28ff82c21a21">The Mindset, Qualities, and Posture of a Coach</a>. So it’s not like I’ve been <em>slacking</em>, exactly. But I have been in more of a liminal place than I realized, coming off some deep personal work and transformational events at the end of June that continue to unravel and remake me across the arc of late summer.</p>

<h3 id="clearing">Clearing</h3>
<p>Since I don’t have a full essay to offer this month, please enjoy this poem by Martha Postlewaith that I find to be both a balm and an invocation.</p>

<p>Do not try to save<br />
the whole world<br />
or do anything grandiose.<br />
Instead, create<br />
a clearing<br />
in the dense forest<br />
of your life<br />
and wait there<br />
patiently,<br />
until the song<br />
that is your life<br />
falls into your own cupped hands<br />
and you recognize and greet it.<br />
Only then will you know<br />
how to give yourself to this world<br />
so worthy of rescue.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="new-newsletter-announcement">New Newsletter Announcement!</h3>
<p><img src="/images/og/og-words-make-worlds.png" alt="Leader as Coach announcement" /></p>

<p>A few weeks ago I launched a newsletter about the art, science, and craft of the Coaching Leadership Style. Published bi-weekly, <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds/">Words Make Worlds</a> offers practical insights, exercises, and reflection prompts for folks who want to integrate coaching skills into their leadership practice. Developing and facilitating <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/leader-as-coach">Leader as Coach</a> has been tremendously rewarding and I wanted to find a way to get some of the material out to folks who are interested but cannot, for whatever reason, enroll in the live course.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="leader-as-coach-updates">Leader as Coach Updates</h3>
<p><img src="/images/og/leader-as-coach-2.png" alt="Leader as Coach announcement" /></p>

<p>Speaking of which, Leader as Coach is now a 6 week course! After running three incredible pilots in the spring, I took the summer to integrate the feedback and overhaul the program. The new version kicks off in September and you can <a href="https://maven.com/andrea-mignolo/leader-as-coach">read more about it on Maven</a>, or reach out if you have any questions!</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="tent-talks-the-coaching-leadership-style">Tent Talks: The Coaching Leadership Style</h3>
<p>If you happen to be around tomorrow (Tuesday, August 1st) I’m giving a short <a href="https://chicagocamps.org/event/andrea-mignolo-getting-started-in-the-coaching-leadership-style/">Tent Talk about the Coaching Leadership Style</a>. The talk will be recorded so if you can’t make it I’ll share the video out in next month’s newsletter.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="worth-your-attention">Worth Your Attention</h3>

<p>“<em>The times that I have known most deeply what is true and beautiful and important — when I understand how all of the little things are connected to the overwhelmingness of being — have been the times in which I forget the demands of a self.</em>” <a href="https://one.compost.digital/the-salt-of-the-cosmos/">Tal Milovina’s beautiful meditation</a> on the ouroboros of ontological design defies easy categorization (other than “this is a piece you <em>must</em> read”). Weaving between physical and digital realms, being and nothingness, scientific rationalism and deeply human feeling states, pathology and ways of being, Milovina’s insights are connected through the semiotics of lithium, an unexpected and poignant representation of this particular moment in global time.</p>

<p>What do you get when you combine the daughter of a comedy writer with non-dual experience? The inimitable Jean Houston. This short talk, “<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BlRJTvm2eWY">The Quest for Nondual Reality</a>” touches on a non-dual developmental path for self and world, one that illuminates the interconnection and evolution of everything with everything else. As I deepen in my own nondual work through <a href="https://realizationprocess.org">The Realization Process</a> (something I will be talking about more soon) I am researching ways in which people give language to nondual experiences in order to find my own place as a guide and teacher of nondual practices.</p>

<p>Speaking of comedy, amazing human Viktor Frankel uses it to great effect in this <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fD1512_XJEw&amp;t=11s">short clip on humanity’s search for meaning</a> from a lecture in 1972. If you don’t watch the video, remember this quote from Goethe that Frankl invokes, "<em>We have to be idealists, in a way, because then we'll wind up as the true, the real realists. If we take Man as he his we make him worse but if we take man as he should be, we make him capable of becoming what he can be.</em>”</p>

<p>Creating a world where everyone belongs is <a href="https://www.buildingbelonging.us">Brian Stout’s mission</a>. I met Brian in the summer of 2021 at the <a href="https://strozziinstitute.com">Strozzi dojo</a> in Petaluma, California and I’ve been following his work ever since. What I appreciate most about Brian’s is the transparency, detail, and <em>deep care</em> with which he writes, shares and creates. And his <a href="https://citizenstout.substack.com/p/belonging-scale-part-1">most recent post</a> on an initiative he has been co-creating, Belonging @ Scale, is no exception. Bringing new worlds into being takes a phenomenal level of effort, community, and awareness and I think you’ll get a lot from this two part series (<a href="https://citizenstout.substack.com">sign-up to his newsletter</a> to get notified when Part 2 is published!).</p>

<p>Erin Kissane is writing up a ton of insightful, critical, and spot on essays about the Fediverse, Mastodon, and community building. <a href="https://erinkissane.com/the-affordance-loop">The affordance loop</a> is one of those essays and a must read for anyone on the internet today (which means you, dear reader). Freedom, flourishing, safety, and refuge are all on the table through explorations of affordances, intention, and outcomes. This is a nuanced take on ecosystems in the throes of change, how we create networks of meaningful connection, and the way in which digital affordances, now decades in their making and maturation, shape communities and in turn are shaped by communities.</p>

<hr />

<p>Thanks for being here. I hope you are having a lovely, moderately cool, and wildfire-free summer. Or a bitingly crisp, clear, and snow-filled winter. See you in August!</p>

          ]]>
        </description>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>the becoming 009</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com//the-becoming/009/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com//the-becoming/009/</guid>
        <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jun 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


        <description>
          <![CDATA[
            <p>Hello from the other side of summer solstice! It’s cold as f*ck here in San Francisco and accordingly foggy as well. I recently learned SF summers are colder than South African winters so that’s something. It’s fun to be bundled up in sweaters while others get to wear sun dresses (not that I'm jealous or anything). But enough with that - I’m Andi, this is <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/the-becoming">the becoming</a>, and I am glad you are here.</p>

<p class="caption"><img src="/images/kp/009.jpg" alt="A San Francisco succulent" />
A giant San Francisco succulent I met on my way to Kung Fu class.</p>

<h3 id="practice-and-intuition">Practice and Intuition</h3>
<blockquote>
  <p>“We are what we repeatedly do.”  - Aristotle</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Lately I have been thinking a lot about <em>practice</em>. Not because I thought it would be a good thing to think about, but because the word keeps showing up in my life - an email in my inbox, a course lecture, a podcast episode, a blog post, a comment in passing - enough synchronicity that I know better than to ignore it.  And so here we are with the topic of this month’s newsletter: practice.</p>

<p class="archive-notice">This is an archived version of <strong>the becoming</strong>. You can sign up to receive future editions using the form at the bottom of this page.</p>

<p>I’d like to unpack two things in what I just wrote: practice and synchronicity. Practice, as I take meaning from the conversations showing up on my doorstep, is about cultivating a feel or an at-home-ness with something new or unfamiliar. It is about the <a href="https://aworkinglibrary.com/writing/fifteen-or-one-third">movement of return</a>, coming back, and <a href="https://vividvoid.substack.com/p/the-canvas">remembering</a>. This kind of practice isn’t about acquiring a new skill (e.g. learning a new language) as much as it is a kind of <a href="https://elizabethberg.substack.com/p/a-cool-summer-morning">tending to our own becoming</a>. It is practice that shifts how we are in the world and how we respond to life. These types of practices require the support of not just the mind, but the heart and body as well.</p>

<p>Over the course of 2023 I have been developing my intuitive practice - the ability to be aware of and in connection with non-rational ways of knowing. This requires a shift in how I interact with the world - from head-based thinking to more holistic, full-bodied perception. It also requires radical presence and connection with myself <em>and</em> the more-than-human world at the same time.</p>

<p>I don’t really have an answer to what this looks like, no end-game in mind, but I do have a few questions that have been guiding me. Things like:</p>

<ul>
  <li>What is arising in this moment?</li>
  <li>Am I present enough to fully sense what is here now?</li>
  <li>How can I be in conversation with what is here now?</li>
  <li>How do I move in congruence with what I am sensing?</li>
</ul>

<p>And these questions in turn informed the design of a set of practices to keep me coming back, day in and day out, to my intuition. They helped me see the kind of body that is required to live intuitively: one that can be present and sensitive to what is arising. And once this became clear I created practices to deepen my capacity to be present and sensing. Which included:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Daily meditations the lineage of the Realization Process (an embodied practice for non-dual awakening)</li>
  <li>Taking walks in nature without my phone, attuned to the world around me</li>
  <li>Deepening my relationship with Tarot (working with the cards daily)</li>
  <li>Working with my dreams and incorporating them into my meditation practice</li>
  <li>Reading poems</li>
  <li>Listening, opening, and receiving as a somatic practice</li>
</ul>

<p>These practices, over time, have shifted how my daily living unfolds. Through the Realization Process I am more connected to a pervasive stillness that supports an ongoing deepening of my own embodiment. From this place I am more connected to the world around me, less “in my own head”. I do not have to think to create reality, but uncover it with my senses. And as this happens, my body becomes attuned to receiving - dreams, insights, connections, knowing - things outside the realm of rational thought but equally as true.</p>

<p>So yeah, <em>practice</em>. The word brings to mind rote, mechanical repetition - doing the same thing day in and day out with a kind of absent or partial attention. The kind that feels more like, “Do I have to?” rather than “Wow, I get to!” I’m sure we’ve all experienced this in our own lives, where resignation becomes the dominant mood when engaging in the activities of daily practice. But is this kind of practice really practice? According to Ness Labs (in an email that hit my inbox right after I finished the first draft of this essay) <a href="https://nesslabs.com/10000-hour-rule">the answer is no</a>. Practice is only practice when it is deliberate, systematic, and purposeful.</p>

<p>In <a href="https://bookshop.org/p/books/the-leadership-dojo-build-your-foundation-as-an-exemplary-leader-richard-strozzi-heckler/580188?ean=9781583942017">The Leadership Dojo</a>, Richard Strozzi-Heckler makes a distinction between <em>practices</em> and <em>generative practices</em>, which I think is useful for what we are exploring here. <strong>Practices</strong> are conscious choices we make to behave and act in certain ways towards a <em>particular</em> purpose or goal (saving money for a child’s college tuition, not eating or drinking three hours before bed in order to sleep better, etc). <strong>Generative practices</strong>, by comparison, are conscious choices to embody a behavior that can be used in <em>any</em> situation. Our way of being and awareness of reality shift as a result of generative practices, which can be used any time, any where. You can dive deeper on the difference between the two (as well as habits, routines, and reflexes) in <a href="https://strozziinstitute.com/you-are-what-you-practice/">You are What You Practice</a>.</p>

<p>What is emerging for me is that practice really needs to include intention, purpose, and embodiment. This doesn’t necessarily mean it is easy, or that we always want to do it, but that when we do practice we are present, purposeful, and committed. We connect to the person we are becoming and the future we are living into and allow that to infuse our practice with meaning.</p>

<p>When we do this, practice becomes:</p>

<ul>
  <li>A way of feeling at home, a way of developing familiarity</li>
  <li>A devotion, a calling in, a reminder of what is important</li>
  <li>A process of becoming</li>
  <li>Cultivation rather than destination</li>
  <li>Embodied learning - about what we do and how we do it</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="leadership-as-practice">Leadership as Practice</h3>
<blockquote>
  <p>“What am I practicing to bring about the current conditions I find myself in?” - me</p>
</blockquote>

<p>As leaders, we are always practicing <em>something</em> (though we may have practiced to the point our behavior has become habit). The patterns of how we engage with our colleagues, teams, and organizations may have developed very early on in our career (and life!), and become our default way of leading. If being liked is something that was important to us from a very early age, then we may lead by saying yes to everything or avoiding difficult conversations. Or if winning is really important, it will inform a style of leadership that includes competitiveness, long hours, and political maneuvering. Neither of these approaches is inherently bad; depending on the context and the needs of the organization each style could in fact be a good match for a particular context. On the other hand, these styles may lead to outcomes we really don’t want.</p>

<p>I frequently use the phrase “leadership practice” to bring awareness to the collective process of a leader’s being and becoming. Individual leadership practices are unique and dynamic - it is the sum total of what we do, day in and day out, and <em>how</em> we do it that creates the leader we are today. If we are not happy with how we are leading, or the outcomes we are getting, then new leadership practices can be adopted. Over time, these practices will result in new ways of leading, and different outcomes. But these practices have to be of the generative variety, in service of the who rather than a particular what.</p>

<p>From my very anecdotal research, it seems that many articles and resources lack a generative approach, and implementation details fall short of providing a leader with active, purposeful, and well-defined practices that can lead to transformative change.</p>

<p>For example! Maybe you’ve identified that ‘boundaries’ are something you want to work on. Boundaries both at work, and around work. You do a quick search and come across <a href="https://ideas.ted.com/how-to-set-clear-work-boundaries-jayne-hardy/">this TED article</a> on setting clear boundaries. Hooray! You read the article and jot down a list of what you need to do:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Understand your worth</li>
  <li>Be clear and concise</li>
  <li>Manage and negotiate expectations</li>
  <li>Identify your non-negotiables</li>
  <li>Make sure remote work also has boundaries</li>
  <li>Beware of burnout</li>
</ol>

<p>The ‘what’ part of boundaries is clearly covered in this piece. Cognitively it is easy to understand the ground rules and parameters of better boundaries which includes activities like ‘understanding’ and ‘managing’ and ‘identifying’ and ‘beware-ing’. But… what is it that you actually <em>practice</em> to create better boundaries? And even more importantly - what are the <em>generative practices</em> that can make boundaries an integral part of your life, not just in specific work situations but part of your way of being and acting in the world?</p>

<p><a href="https://hbr.org/2022/04/a-guide-to-setting-better-boundaries">This article from HBR</a> on setting boundaries does a better job at including the practice angle, encouraging experimentation and reflection along the way. Their list of recommendations for what you should do is short and precise:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Determine your top priorities in work and life</li>
  <li>Test out one hard boundary</li>
  <li>Practice a few soft boundaries</li>
  <li>Commit</li>
</ol>

<p>I appreciate that the author first defines what boundaries are (who we give power to) and the types of boundaries one might use (hard and soft), and then guides the reader through the process of setting and testing boundaries with an invitation to commit to one quarter of experimentation as a test. Reflection questions are provided that can be used at the end of the quarter to review what worked, what didn’t, and what needs to change.</p>

<p>But, these practices aren’t generative practices because they are in service of a <em>particular</em> purpose or goal  (e.g. more energy, more time with family, less time doing something you don’t like). The boundaries enacted through this process are built around a specific outcome. They are about how a leader, as a person, has more or less of x. This is useful, don’t get me wrong! But there is deeper question than can guide a leader to develop better boundaries: “What kind of leader do I have to be to embody healthy boundaries in all situation at all times?” This kind of question pushes us into the land of the generative. Practices in service of who we are becoming, not just what we want to achieve. Boundaries in service of living a life of integrity, coherence, and creativity.</p>

<p>What would boundaries look like as a generative practice? A few things come to mind:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Practicing the embodied ‘no’ 3 times a day</li>
  <li>Sensing into alignment - before saying yes, create space to connect with what you want (this can be by taking 3 deep breaths, or by saying something like, “I need some time to think about it. Let me get back to you by the end of the day.”</li>
  <li>Designing your day in service of how your energy flows</li>
  <li>Making declarations (in service of who you are becoming)</li>
  <li>Making offers (in service of what feels aligned for you)</li>
</ul>

<p>These practices center our power in ourselves and deepens our awareness of what feels in alignment and what we have capacity for. Over time these generative boundary practices get deep into our bones, and when they do we won’t have to go through mental exercises to get clear on priorities and create lists of hard and soft boundaries to experiment with. Our boundaries will instead be an integral and embodied part of how we live and lead.</p>

<h3 id="additional-tips-for-practice">Additional Tips for Practice</h3>
<p>In <a href="https://bookshop.org/p/books/your-body-is-your-brain-leverage-your-somatic-intelligence-to-find-purpose-build-resilience-deepen-relationships-and-lead-more-powerfully-amanda-blake/10032292?ean=9780999368107">Your Body is Your Brain</a>, Amanda Blake provides insightful tips on practicing:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Make Your Practice Relevant.</strong>
 Know why you are practicing and stay connected to why it matters. This can happen at both the practice and generative practice level. For practices, you’ll be connecting to the ability or skill you will have as a result of committed practice. For generative practices, you’ll connect to the person and leader you are becoming.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Practice Early, Practice Often.</strong>
 Short and frequent practice supports the body to sustain the transformation needed to get the capacities in our bones.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Locate Your Practice in Time and Space.</strong>
 Engage in practices when you don’t need them, so when you do your body remembers for you. Blake suggests correlating new practices with something in your life that happens multiple times a day, and tying your practice to it (to act as a reminder). Examples include, whenever you change tasks, take a break, start a meeting, notice your breathing get shallow, or walk through the door. You can also set reminders on your phone or put post-its on a mirror or on your desk.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Extra Practice or Embedded Practice.</strong>
 Extra practices are those you add to your life, like meditation, tai chi, or stretching. Embedded practices are “woven into the tapestry of your every day activities.” In the case of boundaries, that might be something like saying no three times a day. For busy leaders, embedded practices are more likely to stick because they flow into the activity of your existing day, rather than require you to fit something new into an already packed schedule. Taking a mindful minute before each meeting will have a better chance at becoming a part of your life than taking up a daily 30 minute meditation practice.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>To wrap this all up, I’ll leave you with a few reflection questions should you wish to continue exploring practices in your own life:</p>

<ul>
  <li>What are the circumstance you find yourself in that you would like to change?</li>
  <li>What are you practicing that has resulted in those circumstances?</li>
  <li>What do you want instead?</li>
  <li>Who is the person you need to be to have that happen?</li>
  <li>What new practices will support you in becoming this person?</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h3 id="worth-your-attention">Worth Your Attention</h3>
<p>I’ve started Bayo Akomolafe’s Slow Study course, <a href="https://forthewild.world/we-will-dance-with-mountains-course">We Will Dance With Mountains: Into the Cracks</a>! I’m moving through it with a friend - we are taking the ‘slow’ part seriously and also delighting in the practice-based approach to learning. This course is what kicked-off the inundation of ‘practice’ into my life, with Bayo saying, “This course is not about ﬁnding theoretical answers. This course is not about getting these concepts. This course is about practice, cultivating a feel at homeness within cracks. Learning how to look to our left, to our right, up and down, around us, and learning our politics of surprise, without which we will continue to be stuck in social theories that might help us navigate the neurosis of this moment, but will keep us stuck within a house.”</p>

<p>Language is a technology, and as one my my professors at <a href="https://case.edu/weatherhead/">Weatherhead</a> likes to say, words make worlds. So I appreciate <a href="https://cutlefish.substack.com/p/tbm-225-milestones-and-stepping-stones">John Cuttlefish’s observation</a> that language can be used as a “hack” to organizational challenges as he explores replacing the word <em>milestone</em>  with <em>stepping stone</em> to refer to “meaningful integration, movement, and learning points that focus the team, hold certain assumptions constant, and act as a forcing function.”</p>

<p>This is self-serving, but I am experimenting with writing articles on LinkedIn and recently posted one called, “<a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/challenge-player-coach-management-andrea-mignolo-mba-pcc%3FtrackingId=XZWSoosTCmlEAdZa4aY3eg%253D%253D/?trackingId=XZWSoosTCmlEAdZa4aY3eg%3D%3D">The Myth of Player-Coach Management</a>.” It’s a look at how two subnetworks in the brain - the Default Mode Network and the Task Positive Network influence how we show up as leaders, and what it is possible for us to do. When required to switch frequently and rapidly between the two networks (which player-coaches have a high probability of needing to do) we can run into trouble.</p>

<p>Situational Leadership describes an approach in which the leader modifies their style to match the developmental level of the person they are working with. The Path-Goal Theory, on the other hand, looks at how a leader can modify their style based on the <em>motivational needs</em> of the person they are working with. In his Penn State Leadership Blog, <a href="https://sites.psu.edu/leadership/2016/06/29/what-is-path-goal-theory/">Paul Anderson explores what the Path-Goal Theory is and how it works</a>. I found it an interesting approach that seems to integrate more nuance and responsiveness when it comes to people and contexts at work.</p>

<p>I don’t love linking to Substack posts because it’s, you know, a <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/2023/04/14/substack-ceo-chris-best-doesnt-realize-hes-just-become-the-nazi-bar/">Nazi Bar</a>, but this “brief” <a href="https://statespaceadventures.substack.com/p/predictive-processing-a-brief-introduction">introduction to predictive processing</a> is too good to not share. The theory posits that our brain evolved to be good at one things specifically: prediction. Roberto Cavelli talks about the brain’s predictive capacity in <a href="https://bookshop.org/p/books/the-order-of-time-carlo-rovelli/9709825?ean=9780735216112">The Order of Time</a>, and ties the use of memory as a foundation for predictions to our experience of the flow of time: “this being between past and future events is central to our mental structure. This, for us, is the <em>flow</em> of time. (P. 179)”. Similarly, Lisa Feldman Barrett’s model for <a href="https://bookshop.org/p/books/how-emotions-are-made-the-secret-life-of-the-brain-lisa-feldman-barrett/6961460?ean=9781328915436">how emotions are made</a> similarly incorporates the brain’s inherent abilities of prediction as a lens through which to understand how past experiences inform emotions that arise as a predictive response to things happening around us. Predictive processing takes a look at how the brain engages in the process of prediction and discusses how the theory can help us understand our experience of life.</p>

<hr />

<p>Thanks for reading, happy practicing, and see you next month!</p>

          ]]>
        </description>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>the becoming 008</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com//the-becoming/008/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com//the-becoming/008/</guid>
        <pubDate>Wed, 31 May 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


        <description>
          <![CDATA[
            <p>Hello, I’m Andi and this is the May edition of <strong>the becoming</strong>, a newsletter that shimmies in the border between the known and unknown.</p>

<p class="caption"><img src="/images/kp/008.jpg" alt="The Edges of The Orb" />
Image by <a href="https://unsplash.com/photos/tZCrFpSNiIQ">my mind</a> on Unsplash.</p>

<p>In my coaching practice I work with a wide range of people who embody beautifully unique ways of leading.  Two things they all have in common, however, is ambition and sacrifice. Ambition acts as an animating force, moving them towards a specific outcome and playing a starring role in their success. Whatever stands in ambition’s way is sacrificed to the altar of achievement.</p>

<p class="archive-notice">This is an archived version of <strong>the becoming</strong>. You can sign up to receive future editions using the form at the bottom of this page.</p>

<p>Ambition is <em>effective</em> and highly rewarded in our society. Equal parts desire and determination, ambition brings clarity and purpose to an at times infuriatingly obscure existence. It gives us a degree of clarity in who we are, and makes it easier to share that with the world.</p>

<p>Ambition works, until the day it doesn’t. This is where I work with many of my clients - specific moments when the crystallized structures of ambition no longer serve the longings of the soul.</p>

<p>Up until my mid-twenties I was anything but ambitious. I loved to get lost in the woods, read books, and hang out with animals. I enjoyed school (at least until high school) but wouldn’t describe myself as a particularly inspired student. I had no idea what I wanted to “be” as an adult and wandered my way through college, taking courses with popular professors (good idea) and losing myself in works of fiction (not so good idea).</p>

<p>It wasn’t until a few years after graduation that anything like ambition showed up at my doorstep. While I was still meandering my way through life, my friends were notching big achievements in their careers. I found myself surrounded by advanced degrees, awards, fellowships, newspaper mentions, and other professional achievements that lit a fire under my ass. Not because I had any particularly lofty visions of my own, but because <em>I did not want to be left behind.</em></p>

<p>Ambition entered my life as a strategy for belonging, and I committed myself with determination to “making it”. I didn’t really pause to get specific about the “it”, I just knew I had to move into action. When this nascent ambition emerged I was freelancing as a front-end developer so I just poured fuel on that fire and followed the energy. I moved to New York City, got involved in the start-up scene, started going to hackathons, and worked non-stop. My ambition felt unrelenting, a nuclear reactor of longing in search of recognition, success, and belonging.</p>

<p>The reactor was fueled by fear, and the vehicle for that fear was an inner voice that was critical and mean. For the sake of easy reference we’ll call it The Manager. The Manager told me horrible things about myself, shared unrelenting criticism of everything that I did, and constantly reminded me of where I was falling short. It kept me so deeply unsatisfied with where I was that I lost the ability to pause and take stock of things, to find respite from the frenzy of work, to celebrate what I had achieved along the way. The Manager’s strategy was to keep fear close enough that whenever I slowed down I could feel it, a discomfort so strong that only work could ease it. Ambition protected me from fear I was unwilling to face.</p>

<p>My clients often report similar experiences, that they have an internal voice that drives them to achieve big things through unrelenting criticism. They also share that without this voice they wouldn’t be where they are today. And this is true! At least to a degree. The job of this voice is to remind you of all the ways you are not enough so you will keep moving towards to learning more, doing more, and achieving more. It wants you focused on Big Hairy Audacious Goals because goals provide certainty, and certainty is squarely in the domain of ambition.</p>

<p>Ambition leaves no room for uncertainty, and while uncertainty may not feel great, it does contain important information. I’ve been thinking of uncertainty like rests in a piece of music - measures that call for an absence of sound. When the notes in a certain line stop we attune to a new soundscape and hear things that we couldn’t before. Uncertainty is a rest - a cessation of clarity that opens our ability to listen to a deeper knowing, a wisdom that comes from within and is connected to something bigger than ourselves. Where ambition is the size of a human, inner wisdom is the size of the world.</p>

<p>As a leader, you probably aren’t speaking to others the way The Manager speaks to you, though I suspect its presence is more noticeable than you imagine. Take a moment and reflect on the ways your relationship to yourself, and to The Manager, shows up in how you lead. It may be in the perspective you take, the conclusions you draw, the interpretations you make. In the ways frustration or pessimism leaks into interactions, into the edges of your words, and keeps you from being present with others.</p>

<p>The antidote to this inner harshness is kindness, compassion, and acceptance. Kindness releases the concentration of energy The Manager uses as fuel and creates space for more of who we are to become present. It can be uncomfortable to sit in the silence that was once filled with its critical voice and welcome more of ourselves home. After all, if we don’t have that relentless voice driving us, how on earth can we push ourselves to achieve everything we want? How is it possible that being kind to ourselves can become a foundation of our leadership practice?</p>

<p>A fundamental aspect of leadership is the inner game, becoming aware of how we have created constrictions in our thoughts, emotions, and body as a form of protection, and learning how to relax them. The Manager doesn’t have a big playbook - it has a single strategy that it picked up because it worked, and it ran with it. The Manager lives in these constrictions as a reactive program that executes whenever it is needed. As it relaxes we have greater access to direct experience. This access increases our ability to perceive and respond to the present moment, rather than to echoes of the past or hopes for the future.</p>

<p>I am starting to see how ambition, in many ways, is a response to fear and uncertainty. According to David Whyte “ambition abstracts us from the underlying elemental nature of the creative conversation while providing us the cover of a target that has become false through over-description, overfamiliarity or too much understanding.” I like this. Creative responses come from the ability to be in the unknowing and in conversation with what is emerging. And I think he’s right - ambition collapses complexity into something knowable, controllable, and hardened. It is a crystallization of a moment in the future that harnesses all our energy and focus into a single vector of movement.</p>

<p>A lot of high achieving individuals fear what will happen if The Manager stops doing its job, if ambition as a survival response ceases to be the default way of moving in the world. If we treat ourselves with kindness, how can we ever achieve the success we seek? The common assumption is that without ambition we become lazy, useless, self-indulgent. But if ambition is an abstraction that silences the intuition required to step into what is uniquely ours to do, then ambition can only bring us echoes of greatness that could have been. David Whyte continues:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>No matter the self-conceited importance of our labours we are all compost for worlds we cannot yet imagine. Ambition takes us toward that horizon, but not over it - that line will always recede before our controlling hands. But a calling is a conversation between our physical bodies, our work, our intellects and imaginations, and a new world that is itself the territory we seek. A vocation always includes the specific, heartrending way we will fail at our attempt to live fully. A true vocation always metamorphoses both ambition and failure into compassion and understanding for others.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Ambition can get us to where we want to go, but it cannot take us any further. It acts only in service of the known and wants us to believe that we have more control than we do. With enough kindness, ambition loosens its grip and becomes one of many animating forces for how to move in the world. It can be used as a navigational tool, drawing boundaries around certainty to reveal the edges of the unknown. But ambition cannot go beyond the edges, into the new worlds we seek. For that we need kindness and compassion, qualities that can hold us softly in the discomfort of the unknown as we listen for the song of emerging worlds.</p>

<h4 id="reflection-questions-for-ambitous-edges">REFLECTION QUESTIONS FOR AMBITOUS EDGES</h4>

<ul>
  <li>What has helped you succeed in your leadership career?</li>
  <li>How do you experience your own ambition? What fuels it?</li>
  <li>What internalized stories and voices keep you going?</li>
  <li>How do you respond to not knowing/uncertainty?</li>
  <li>What parts show up to protect you, and how do they do that? (e.g. Do they turn inwards with harshness and expectation, or do they turn outwards with irritability and blame.)</li>
  <li>What is your ambition in service of?</li>
  <li>What is the deeper longing beneath your ambition?</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h3 id="worth-noting">Worth Noting</h3>
<p>As long as we are talking about what work gets automated in the Age of AI, <a href="https://www.hamiltonnolan.com/p/automate-the-ceos">why not extend that to the role of CEO</a>? It seems like a pretty good candidate for automation - feed an LLM a few decades worth of market data, Financial Times articles, and case studies from HBR and you’d probably have a pretty good CEO. If you needed some mercurial decision making just modify with some DnD style character traits and introduce the potential for ‘botching’.</p>

<p>Looking for footing in turbulent times and don't want to do it alone? <a href="https://charleseisenstein.org/courses/sanity-project/">The Sanity Project</a> might be for you. Even if you don't enroll, click on the link and check out the definitions in the green box titled, "What do I mean by staying sane?" Just reading the list helps me feel grounded, with more capacity to deal with the chaos whirling around me.</p>

<p>In grad school I learned about The Default Mode Network (DMN) and the Task Positive Network (TPN), two distinct subsystems in the brain responsible for getting things done and connecting with others (respectively). The two subsystems are anti-correlated, which means when one is active, the other one isn’t. I remember the professor making a comment about how switching between the two is hard, and doesn’t happen instantaneously. If we aren’t practicing moving between and using each subsystem, one can become dominant. It made sense to me, reflecting on how crabby I could be when people interrupted me during times of flow and deep concentration. More recently I’ve been thinking about the impact these two subsystems have on folks in the role of “Player-Coach” (however you feel about it), and what leaders, teams, and organizations need to know to set this role up for success. I’m in the process of writing something about this, but wanted to share Anne Betz’s post on the topic, <a href="https://yourcoachingbrain.wordpress.com/2015/02/06/the-power-of-dreaming-the-power-of-action/">“The Power of Dreaming, The Power of Action”</a>. It is a useful introduction and has enough substance to support reflection on which network you hang out in more.</p>

<p>For me, summer has always been a time for reading (admittedly as is every other season - it’s <em>always</em> a time for reading). <a href="https://www.sjc.edu/santa-fe/programs/summer-classics/seminar-schedule/catalog-by-location">Summer Classics</a> - a seminar program from St. John’s College - is an opportunity to read in community and the first week is entirely online. “The Incoherence of the Philosophers” looks stellar, and if I’m not totally off grid that week you’ll know where to find me.</p>

<p>Bayo Akomolafe recently spoke at the graduation ceremony for the California Institute of Integral Studies and his unlisted talk, which I am calling “The Wisdom of the Shush,” is <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=U0teyqf0AAg">on YouTube if you know where to look</a>. I am always struck by Bayo’s perspective and poetic attunement to life - whenever he speaks, I listen. More than listen, I feel. This is not a comforting talk for a graduating class, but it is an important one. It unsettles the ego and soothes the soul, invites us to invert the stories we tell about ourselves and the world, to stop seeking clarity, and to find the cracks and dance with thresholds.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="upcoming">Upcoming</h3>

<p><img src="/images/og/leader-as-coach-2.png" alt="Leader as Coach" /></p>

<p>I’ll be running one last Vanguard cohort for <a href="https://maven.com/andrea-mignolo/leader-as-coach">Leader as Coach</a> in June. The course will be on pause for the summer, returning in September.</p>

<p>If you, or anyone you know, has been wanting to integrate more of a <a href="https://positivepsychology.com/coaching-leadership-style/">Coaching Leadership Style</a> into their executive or management practice, this is the course for you. <strong>The last day to apply is June 11th.</strong></p>

<p>Members of The Vanguard receive 50% of the course price, have lifetime access to The Leader’s Little Book of Coaching (our course manual), and can join any future cohort at no cost. This is a pretty sweet benefit - the course changes from cohort to cohort based on feedback and student experience, each iteration honing in on what leaders need when it comes to building and supporting their teams. Plus, it’s always great to have space to practice coaching skills and get more comfortable facilitating a space for others to connect with their own knowing and agency.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>Thank you</em> for reading, have a wonderful 🌞 solstice 🌞, and see you towards the end of June!</p>

          ]]>
        </description>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>the becoming 007</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com//the-becoming/007/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com//the-becoming/007/</guid>
        <pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


        <description>
          <![CDATA[
            <p>Hello, I’m Andi - an executive coach and author of this here newsletter about leadership, change, and what it means to be human. And welcome to the seventh edition of <strong>the becoming</strong> (née Kitchen Party).</p>

<p class="caption"><img src="/images/kp/007.jpg" alt="A path through Mt Davidson park" />
Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/photos/v3TkpV2wLTo">Susan Wilkinson on unsplash</a>.</p>

<p>You will, no doubt, have noticed the name change. Kitchen Party was a good name. It evoked a sense of warmth and connection I was going after, and at one point I was thinking about hosting an actual series of <em>real life</em> kitchen parties because what’s better than good company, deep conversation, and nourishing food? While I haven’t hosted anything yet, the idea is very alive in my heart.</p>

<p class="archive-notice">This is an archived version of <strong>the becoming</strong>. You can sign up to receive future editions using the form at the bottom of this page.</p>

<p>But as far as a name for this newsletter goes, Kitchen Party was missing something. The central themes of leadership, change, and being human are still firmly in place, but the path ahead is less about answers and clarity, more about getting lost and embracing the unknown. The world is breaking in wonderful and terrifying ways. We grasp at language and struggle to find frames of reference for what we are in the middle of. Extractive systems of domination scream atop their creaking towers while pluralistic networks of survival and love, of life-affirming defiance, burst through the fissures in the seams.</p>

<p>The morass of complexity we are woven into calls for leadership - not the exalted god-like status imagined by the business world, but leadership enacted by each of us in different situations and at different times. In this I am influenced by the thinking of <a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/23303131.2016.1263073">Mary Parker Follett</a>, who saw leadership as a process of sense-making, a way of becoming deeply familiar with the web of relationships that structure an understanding of the <em>total situation</em>. The concept of the total situation is an interesting one, a gesture towards something comprehensive yet ultimately unknowable - a bounded web of facts, experiences, desires, and aims. For anyone to understand the total situation is of course, an impossible task. In part because of our own limited capacity to comprehend complexity, and in part because the total situation is constantly changing, dissolving, and reforming. There is no solid ground to stand on when we enact leadership in this way.</p>

<p>This kind of sensing, seeking, forming, dissolving is a creative dance between the known and the unknown. Both the total situation and leadership itself are reconstituted in each moment. In this perpetual movement of dissolving and becoming we may each be called to share our expertise, temporarily inhabiting the role of leader, sense maker, enactor. In her thinking Follett pushes even further, suggesting that leadership, not leaders, is what gets us through. The distinction is slight but important and serves to reposition leadership as the birthright of each and every one of us. The “one true leader” that exists in any situation, what she called the invisible leader, is the <em>common purpose</em>.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“The best leader does not ask people to serve him, but the common end… a common purpose, born of the desires and the activities of the group.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I am digging this definition of leadership because of how inclusive, even reliant, it is on the collective. I am also interested in this idea of <em>common purpose</em>, though I am waiting for a few books to arrive before I can say more. In the hyper-individualized world of modern leaders who must bear all the weight and have all the answers, Follett’s work brings an air of freshness and liberation. For me there is a sense of letting go into the unknown, an embrace of storytelling and sense making (I’m curious to explore overlaps with Cynefin and Transition Design) as moment-to-moment way finding. That Follett was writing at the turn of the 20th century is a testament to her insight and foresight, as much as it is a testament to the intolerance of the business establishment who pretty much disappeared her work until it was republished almost a century later in the late 90s. Follett is credited with coining the term “transformational leadership” and emphasized the importance of what we now call “soft” skills such as communication and informal processes.</p>

<p>And so here we are at <strong>the becoming</strong>. <strong>the becoming</strong> is a place where the known meets the unknown. Where sense making coalesces and dissolves the thread that structures an understanding of the total situation, however impossible a task that may be. An unending frontier reconstituted in each moment, a “moving edge between what we know about ourselves and what we are about to become,” in the words of David Whyte. You can hear the refrains of Follett in Whyte’s words, where leadership also becomes a moving edge between what we know about the total situation and what it is about to become.</p>

<p>I hope you’ll stay and join me, though if you wish otherwise you can quickly and easily unsubscribe at the bottom of the page. Leadership, change, and what it means to be human will remain the focus of the newsletter, now viewed with soft eyes that blur the edges and displace the familiar so that we can sense more fully into what is emerging.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="becoming-with">Becoming With</h3>
<p>Over at Animas Valley Institute Bill Plotkin is up to part five in the multipart series, "Who is Up for Building a Cathedral?" (<a href="https://myemail.constantcontact.com/Who-s-Up-for-Building-a-Cathedral---Part-I--SM322--Bill-Plotkin-Soulcraft-Musing.html?soid=1102010840526&amp;aid=lUl0tzr9FGU">Part I</a>, <a href="https://myemail.constantcontact.com/Who-s-Up-for-Building-a-Cathedral---Part-II--SM323--Bill-Plotkin-Soulcraft-Musing.html?soid=1102010840526&amp;aid=v5hfjf_di2A">Part II</a>, <a href="https://myemail.constantcontact.com/Who-s-Up-for-Building-a-Cathedral---Part-III--SM324--Bill-Plotkin-Soulcraft-Musing.html?soid=1102010840526&amp;aid=FYyIMj3qdG4">Part III</a> can be found <a href="https://www.animas.org/books/bill-plotkins-soulcraft-musings/newsletter-archive/">here</a> - IV and V are not online yet), that began with a re-contextualization of Joseph Campbell's Hero's Journey not as a universal myth of individual transformation but as a guide to the “adolescent phase of life” (defined not by age but by a developmental life stage that spans from early adolescence to late adolescence). There are many gifts that this phase of life offers, including exuberance and fiery creativity. But in the West we have prolonged adolescence until it has become pathological, facing a true scarcity of adults and elders. And in this capacity, the Hero's Journey doesn't offer us any way out, any path beyond the egocentric path of the solo superstar (or the solo super-leader, in Follett’s case).</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>And this brings us right to the heart of what I most want to share with you in this essay: The difficulty for any given person in accessing or recognizing a mature framework (a framework for true maturity) is not only that person’s culture but, even more so, their developmental stage. Maybe it’s just obvious: If someone has not themselves matured beyond early adolescence, then their lens, too, will necessarily be adolescent; everything they experience will be seen and understood through that lens. The caterpillar cannot truly imagine the life of a butterfly.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The thread structuring the total situation - in this case the developmental challenge of becoming who we need to be to shift our relationship to each other and to the earth - is a reorientation of the individual. For Follett, this takes the form of leadership instead of leaders, enacted towards a common purpose. For Plotkin this is a remembering and a relocating of the individual back into a web of ecological relationships:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>To serve the world in such a way is to inhabit one’s unique ecological niche, a distinctive way of being in relationship with other humans, creatures, ecosystems, and communities. This is to say that we cannot identify a mature way of serving the world in the social or cultural terms of a job, social role, philosophical perspective, or creative project; that’s the way it’s done in adolescence. Rather, a soul-initiated adult can identify their way of serving the world only in the ecological terms of the unique conversation they are having with the larger, not-merely-human world.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>To reweave ourselves back into the thread of life through ecological connections is a kind of <em>becoming with</em>. Donna Haraway, another voice in the critique of human exceptionalism, writes “if we appreciate the foolishness of human exceptionalism then we know that becoming is always becoming <em>with</em>, in a contact zone where the outcome, where who is in the world, is at stake.”</p>

<p>There is something larger at play, something emerging yet connected to what has always been. We are not alone, the individual is not the locus of all choice, all responsibility, all action. We cannot, as individuals, process all the trauma of the last few centuries through our bodies alone. This is not a shirking of responsibility but rather a call towards a common purpose, a remembering and elevation of the collective, of reweaving ourselves back into the fabric of what is most alive and an honoring of all that is here.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="worth-noting">Worth Noting</h3>
<p>Becoming is about, among other things, belonging. Over at <a href="https://enliveningedge.org/views/being-human-together-remembering-what-we-have-forgotten/">Enliving Edge Betsy Sheppard wonders</a> what it would be like for organizations to take on a management philosophy of unconditional positive regard. To see everyone as “inherently intelligent, creative, self-reflecting, self-correcting, and self-accountable.” Instead of working to remove unwanted things (hiding our weaknesses), what would it be like to access and develop the positive things? To embrace our complexity as human beings?</p>

<p>I thoroughly enjoyed this <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=w4OPtFCs_fw&amp;t=2s">Ted Talk but Margaret Heffernan</a> where she reflects on the human skills we need in an unpredictable world (a timely talk as AI worry ratchets up week by week). She calls for a move from “just in time” to “just in case” management, and advocates for the investment in preparation over planning. Inefficient? Yes. Robust? Absolutely. I was also thrilled to hear <a href="https://www.buurtzorg.com">Buurtzorg</a> mentioned (though you won’t hear it in name, only in the <a href="https://www.weforum.org/agenda/2017/06/the-dutch-community-care-revolution/">study of the Dutch healthcare system</a>) - I first learned about the organization in business school and think of them whenever I need a burst of organizational inspiration. The through line of Margaret’s talk is clear - to utilize human skills we must continue to think for ourselves. The alternative, she warns, is that the more we let machines think for us, the less we can think for ourselves.</p>

<p>At the beginning of the year, Dave Snowden wrote a three part series on “Rewilding Leadership” (<a href="https://thecynefin.co/rewilding-leadership-1/">Part 1</a>, <a href="https://thecynefin.co/rewilding-leadership-2-of-3/">Part 2</a>, <a href="https://thecynefin.co/rewilding-leadership-3-of-3/">Part 3</a>). In line with the themes of this newsletter, Snowden also writes about a more collective understanding of leadership, as “no one person can ever possess all of the various skills and experiences we need in a leadership role so we need to see the situation as a collection of people and processes that, as a whole, deliver what we need.” The posts are rich and also contain a hefty amount of links to other articles of Dave’s that include even more insight and information, but I am following closely the ways in which he is working to actually create frameworks and tools that can map the idea of what collective leadership looks like in a given organization.</p>

<hr />

<p>As always, thank you for reading. See you next month! 👋</p>

          ]]>
        </description>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>the becoming 006</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com//the-becoming/006/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com//the-becoming/006/</guid>
        <pubDate>Thu, 30 Mar 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


        <description>
          <![CDATA[
            <p class="caption"><img src="/images/kp/006.jpg" alt="A path through Mt Davidson park" />
Early spring at Mt. Davidson Park, San Francisco</p>

<p>It's March, this is <strong>the becoming</strong>, and as far as I know I am still Andi. It's good to see you!</p>

<h3 id="we-are-innately-whole">We are innately whole</h3>

<p>The first cohort of <a href="https://maven.com/andrea-mignolo/leader-as-coach">Leader as Coach</a> is in progress and I’m having a lot of fun seeing it all unfold in realtime. This is the first course I’ve designed and taught outside of an institutional environment and I’ve learned a lot in the process of putting it together. Everything from selecting the pedagogical approach (experiential learning with a touch of flipped classroom) creating course materials to figuring out how to make videos that are both short and informative (slowly getting the hang of it).</p>

<p class="archive-notice">This is an archived version of <strong>the becoming</strong>. You can sign up to receive future editions using the form at the bottom of this page.</p>

<p>I’m working off the premise that the best way (maybe only way) to really “get” coaching is to do it. Books and frameworks will give you an understanding of the <em>what</em>, but the <em>how</em> only happens with practice. When coaching, leaders have to make a qualitative shift from being problem solvers to space enablers. To do this effectively requires a felt sense of the difference between the “doing” of coaching and  the “doing” of leadership.</p>

<p>As leaders we fill our days with a lot of directive action; creating a vision, defining strategy, providing feedback, supporting our teams and direct reports, mentoring, and putting out fires (to name a few). Coaching, on the other hand, is non-directive. In these conversations a leader must let go of the reins and rely on curiosity and presence to guide the work. This isn’t a passive approach by any stretch of the imagination, but the activeness of coaching is focused on the person and how they are dealing with their issue and <em>not</em> on the actual issue itself. By assuming an optimistic stance and asking open and honest questions, the leader as coach creates space for the person they are working with to reflect, make meaning, shift awareness, see new possibilities, and take effective action.</p>

<p>Implicit in all of this is the assumption that it is a <em>good idea</em> to create space for someone else to think. That something beneficial happens when a person creates meaning and finds new ways forward without someone else, like their manager, doing it for them. And yet! This can feel really uncomfortable for leaders, especially leaders that want to help. Why not help by sharing what we already know and have learned through experience? By disseminating our own knowledge and ideas on how to resolve an issue or face a challenge? Why do we want someone to think through it themselves when we already have the answers?</p>

<p>Because helping isn’t really helpful. In <a href="https://www.awakin.org/v2/read/view.php?tid=127">Helping, Fixing, and Serving</a>, Rachel Remen points to the inherent power imbalance in helping:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Helping is based on inequality, it's not a relationship between equals. When you help, you use your own strength to help someone with less strength. It's a one up, one down relationship, and people feel this inequality. When we help, we may inadvertently take away more than we give, diminishing the person's sense of self-worth and self-esteem.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>And I think this is the nuance that I’ve been looking to pull out, the idea that the coaching approach is one that  <em>gives</em>, that increases a person’s sense of self-worth and self-esteem. And <em>that</em> is why it’s so important to create space for people to think in order to find their own path forward.</p>

<p>We all have our own capacity to sense into the challenges in front of us and figure out how to move through them. Sometimes we need another set of eyes and ears to see and listen for patterns that live in our blind spots, but once these patterns are made visible we can utilize our inherent creativity to find novel solutions to our own problems. And when <em>we</em> are the ones who do the meaning making, when <em>we</em> are the ones generating new possibilities, when <em>we</em> are the ones choosing what actions to take, then our self-worth, self-esteem, and personal power begin to grow. And the next time we face a challenge we have the memory of our innate resourcefulness in finding our way through. And this is so much more impactful for professional and personal growth than being given someone else’s answer.</p>

<p>And it goes beyond work as well. Helping, fixing, and serving aren’t just how we engage with others, they are how we see life. She writes, “When you help, you see life as weak; when you fix, you see life as broken; and when you serve, you see life as whole.”</p>

<p>And seeing people as innately whole is a pretty radical act.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="leader-as-coach-discount-code">Leader as Coach: Discount Code</h3>
<p>Speaking of which, it’s time for some shameless self-promotion<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>: if you are interested in getting some hands-on experience coaching, the next cohort of <a href="https://maven.com/andrea-mignolo/leader-as-coach">Leader as Coach</a> is open for enrollment. Specific dates and times:</p>

<p>Foundations, May 15, 9 - 10:30am PT<br />
The Practicum, May 16, 9 - 12:30pm PT<br />
Integration, May 22, 9 - 10:30am PT</p>

<p>You can use the discount code VANGUARD50 to get 50% of the course price, plus you’ll receive all future updates to the course manual, The Leader’s Little Book of Coaching, <em>and</em> you have the option of enrolling in any future cohort at no cost.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="getting-to-know-you">Getting to Know You</h3>
<p>A few weeks ago I completed the first module of <a href="https://www.gisc.org">GISC</a>’s <a href="https://www.gisc.org/cape-cod-training-program">Cape Cod Training Program</a>, which I am sure I’ll write about more over the course of the year. The Cape Cod model is a Gestalt approach to working with individuals, dyads, and larger systems, though I have found the approach to be profoundly supportive of living life more generally. As a “get to know you” exercise we were invited to write a poem in the style of George Ella Lyon’s beautiful piece, <a href="https://iamfromproject.com/i-am-from-george-ella-lyon/">I Am From</a>. There is actually an <a href="https://iamfromproject.com">entire project dedicated sharing poems like these</a> as a response to rising xenophobia and isolationism.</p>

<p>I’ve done a fair number of trainings over the years and have participated in no less than five thousand “getting to know you” exercises, and none come close to what this poem can do. It’s such a beautiful way to get to know someone without the pomp of what you do and where you went to school and what company you work for. Which, I think we all know, don’t really help you get to know a person at all.  So, I thought I’d <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1A3N6GafrFl8AuBSrxg5WwhpaPhkxGt2oqSiLqCFGGQU/edit?usp=sharing">share the template</a> in case you feel called to write your own or use it in your own work, as well as the little poem that I wrote about my own fromness.</p>

<h4 id="i-am-from">I Am From</h4>

<p>I am from the bright green moss where toads burrow,<br />
from the cold streams of crawdads<br />
and the wall of purple lilacs at the edge of yard.</p>

<p>I’m from bean casserole pragmatists,<br />
unexpected philosophers, and hidden magic.</p>

<p>I am from the bright colors of Mexican markets<br />
and Tarot decks.<br />
From purple heathered highlands<br />
and pine needle baskets.</p>

<p>I am from choripan  <br />
and zabaione  <br />
and frosted Christmas cookies.</p>

<p>I am from the edge of an axe,<br />
autumn leaves, and winter skies.</p>

<p>I am from quiet where we feel most deeply.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="worth-noting">Worth noting:</h3>

<p>Two days after I sent out my last newsletter, The ChatGPT edition, The Intelligencer published <a href="https://nymag.com/intelligencer/article/ai-artificial-intelligence-chatbots-emily-m-bender.html">“You are Not a Parrot”</a> which said a lot of what I wanted to say but much better. And Ted Chiang wrote a piece that offers a new metaphor by which to think about LLMs - a <a href="https://www.newyorker.com/tech/annals-of-technology/chatgpt-is-a-blurry-jpeg-of-the-web">blurry jpeg of the internet</a>. I’m deeply appreciative of new language to help us think about what these models are doing and how we understand them, because I think Big Tech has really run with the metaphor of intelligence. The language we use to describe what this technology is matters, to how we understand it, interact with it, and to how we understand ourselves.</p>

<p>I have several essays that I’ve been working on in starts and fits (one has been lurking around in some form or another for two years) but just can’t get them moving. I <a href="https://indieweb.social/@pnts/109995817094589215">tooted about this</a> and got some great replies, and then Rands wrote about <a href="https://rands.substack.com/p/writing-hell">Writing Hell</a> and while it doesn’t necessarily help me get unstuck, boy howdy do I feel seen.</p>

<p>Speaking of the power of language, ‘stakeholder’ is a word with colonial roots that needs to be replaced. But not with just another word! What I appreciate about <a href="https://www.fasttrackimpact.com/post/alternatives-to-the-word-stakeholder">this article</a> is the insight that by replacing one word with another we remain squarely in a universal orientation towards life, work, and research. We cannot use universal words, because the universal doesn’t exist.</p>

<p><a href="https://fullstackwhatever.com/episode/andrea-mignolo-the-winding-path">I was on a podcast</a>! <a href="https://maykelloomans.com">Maykel Loomens</a> invited me to be a guest on <a href="https://fullstackwhatever.com">Full Stack Whatever</a>, in which we explored my winding career path, looked at the links between coaching and design, and enjoyed some Big Sun Energy Grenache.</p>

<p>I’m a big fan of self-reflection, learning, and the role that journaling can play in supporting both. Stowe Boyd has a <a href="https://www.sunsama.com/blog/self-reflection-and-the-power-of-narrative">thoughtful article</a> on using the What? So What? Now What? model in support of personal sense making, understanding, and integration.</p>

<hr />

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Who am I kidding. There is definitely shame in this promotion. I went back and forth like 10 times whether or not to include this. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>

          ]]>
        </description>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>the becoming 005</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com//the-becoming/005/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com//the-becoming/005/</guid>
        <pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


        <description>
          <![CDATA[
            <p class="caption"><img src="/images/kp/005.jpg" alt="Flower courtesy of Midjourney, the prompt has been lost to time." />
Flower illustration courtesy of Midjourney. The exact prompt has been lost to time.</p>

<p>Hello! I’m Andi and you are reading <strong>the becoming</strong> - February, 2023 edition.</p>

<p>Writing this month’s newsletter has been an <em>experience</em>. The first draft is now a published essay on Medium, <a href="https://medium.com/method-matter/on-belonging-7957be528340">On Belonging</a>, a reflection on how we belong and what it means to come home. And the final edition, that you are reading now, has turned into a longer than expected exploration of AI and what it means to be human. Less about the technology itself and more about who we are, what we are learning about ourselves, and how we are being shaped by the world and tools we are creating. It also happens to contain 100x more links than any other newsletter I’ve written to date.</p>

<p class="archive-notice">This is an archived version of <strong>the becoming</strong>. You can sign up to receive future editions using the form at the bottom of this page.</p>

<h3 id="what-does-it-mean-to-be-human">What does it mean to be human?</h3>
<p>A few weeks ago I was at a design conference for design leaders appropriately named <a href="https://leadingdesign.com/conferences/sanfran-2023"><em>Leading Design</em> </a>, right here in San Francisco. Organized and curated by the fine folks at <a href="https://clearleft.com/">Clear Left</a>, it was an event filled with two days of thoughtful talks, wonderful people, and for the first time this year, amazing weather. We heard from leaders at unicorns, in the traditional financial sector, government, and also crypto (not an uncontroversial topic, that). Across such a wide variety of industries and companies, the most common theme that kept coming up, like the refrain in a song, was an invitation to <em>be human at work</em>.</p>

<p>I’m not going to argue with this message! I think overall it’s a good one - trying to ratchet up the level of humanity in business - but sometimes I wonder at the sheer magnitude of the task. The systems we’ve built weren’t exactly created with our humanity in mind, but rather efficiency and power. And it is not that we haven’t benefitted, but our gains have come at a cost. No one at the conference explicitly said what we were being when we are <em>not</em> being human, but I have to guess some kind of extension or cog of an organizational system that is <em>afraid</em> of what it means to be human.</p>

<p>In parallel, ChaptGPT and its AI brethren have kicked off yet <a href="https://news.mit.edu/2000/robots-1018">another round</a> of <a href="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/text-idx?cc=mqr;c=mqr;c=mqrarchive;idno=act2080.0044.210;g=mqrg;rgn=main;view=text;xc=1">musings</a> <a href="https://philarchive.org/archive/MASMAP">about</a> what it <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/1999/11/06/books/soul-next-new-machine-humans-wedding-brain-computer-could-change-universe.html">means</a> <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Most-Human-Artificial-Intelligence-Teaches/dp/0241956056">to be</a> <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/intl/blog/the-romance-of-work/202301/chatgpt-makes-us-human">human</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/archive/2023/01/chatgpt-ai-technology-techo-humanism-reid-hoffman/672872/">Reid Hoffman thinks</a> that technology itself makes us more human, writing <em>“<strong>[t]echnology is the thing that makes us us</strong>. Through the tools we create, we become neither less human nor superhuman, nor post-human. We become more human.”</em> This feels very on brand for Silicon Valley.</p>

<p><a href="https://news.harvard.edu/gazette/story/2023/02/will-chatgpt-replace-human-writers-pinker-weighs-in/">Steven Pinker</a> takes a more circumspect approach, describing how technology like large language models (LLMs) can shed light on what makes us human precisely because they are so different than us: “<em>[s]ince LLMs operate so differently from us, they might help us understand the nature of human intelligence. <strong>They might deepen our appreciation of what human understanding does consist of when we contrast it with systems that superficially seem to duplicate it</strong>, exceed it in some ways, and fall short in others.”</em></p>

<p>And <a href="https://rushkoff.medium.com/how-we-taught-technology-to-program-humans-2388adf91364">Douglas Rushkoff</a> points out that rather than learn what makes us human, we are instead re-shaping ourselves to be able to interact with technology: <em>“[I]n essence, these intriguing demonstrations of apparent AI self-awareness may say less about machine consciousness than they do about their capacity to manipulate human perception. In other words, <strong>if AIs are now passing the Turing test, it may say less about how human they have become than how robotic and programmable we have become, ourselves.</strong>”</em></p>

<p>All three are right, in a way. Building tools is an activity of humans, but this activity can, and does quite frequently, dehumanize us. We look at things that exist in the world, like forests and communities, and we see something functional that can be extracted, abstracted, refined, and reconstituted back in the network for leverage. We see the roundness of a tree trunk and that is what we extract from it, discarding everything else about what the tree does in the world - provide shade, produce oxygen, a home for animals, a place to rest - as part of a forest ecosystem. We see the strong ties of communities and we extract that into a graph, discarding everything else about what and how those relationships exist and flourish in the world. So yes, we can make tools and this is very human, but these tools are extracted from something much more vast and beautiful, and the tools we create to extend ourselves also disrupt the direct feedback loops of our actions, further isolating and insulating us from the complexity of the world. And in the same way that we learn to see and extract functional qualities from beautifully complex interweavings of existence and purpose, we also do the same to ourselves. We become an extraction of function at the expense of our own complexity, and at the expense of our humanness.</p>

<p>What I just described is the tl;dr of the tl;dr of Andrew Feenberg’s <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/260983580_From_essentialism_to_constructivism_Philosophy_of_technology_at_the_crossroads">instrumentalization theory</a> (more on this in a subsequent issue), an essential framework for articulating both the functional constitution of technology as well as how technological objects become realized and integrated into natural, technical, and social environments. This doesn’t <em>have</em> to be the way technology shapes us, but it is the path we’ve chosen so far. When control and profits are placed above the dignity of human beings then we reveal our complicity in creating the conditions we find ourselves in.</p>

<p>Feenberg, exploring the nature of technology in parallel with the nature of management says, <em>“The driver of an automobile accelerates to high speeds while experiencing only a slight pressure and small vibrations; the marksman shoots and experiences only a small force transmitted to his shoulder by the stock of the gun. <strong>By the same token management controls workers while minimizing and channeling resistance so far as possible.</strong>”</em></p>

<p>None of this is to say we should get rid of technology (or managers) or stop exploring the nature and potential applications of large language models! What I am saying (I think) is that collectively we are sensing that something is <em>off</em>. Not just the uneasiness of climate change, the entrenchment of white supremacy in every inch our systems, or the geopolitical instability as we transition to a multipolar world. Collectively we are exhausted and I think one contributing factor is the energy it takes to maintain the cognitive dissonance of being a function (a worker, a consumer) pretending to be a human. And then we look up and see <a href="https://openai.com/blog/planning-for-agi-and-beyond">OpenAI talk about</a> how this new era of technology is going to usher in <em>human flourishing</em> and we all roll our eyes and think, “for which humans, exactly?” In these moments, a small voice whispers to me that maybe we don’t have to go all in on these systems, that there is a path to making our own lives bigger and the systems smaller.</p>

<p>Frank Lanz, kicking off the first issue of <a href="https://franklantz.substack.com/">Donkeyspace</a>, is trying to make sense of it all, too.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Somehow we’ve conjured up an infinite hallucinogenic dreamscape out of Bayesian statistics and we’re already kind of bored by it. We made software that writes software but we’re not exactly sure how it works. We don’t program computers anymore, we deprogram them. Every day a new paper or press release announces that another deep philosophical thought experiment has become an engineering problem. And the smartest people in the room can’t agree whether we’re all going to die, or we’re all going to get rich, or none of it matters. I’m uh… I’m having trouble keeping up.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It’s true, I am already kind of bored by it. But some of this I think is because I am <em>tired</em> of the endless hype cycles and harm these systems cause when they are rolled out with the urgency of being first to market, the first to control the narrative. I’m also not sure how much of what we are seeing today with things like ChatGPT and Midjourney would count as “intelligence” rather than yet another (impressive) tool created to extend the work of humans. I mean, what are these systems going to do in the absence of a prompt? Nothing. Absolutely nothing.</p>

<p>In the early 2000s I ran a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MegaHAL">MegaHAL</a> bot on IRC that basically logged the entire channel as its corpus of data. It was fun and over time Fie, the bot, got pretty good at mimicking the general culture and tone of the channel. ChatGPT feels similar to me, just with a lot more data. And I appreciate getting a great outline or the summarization of a bunch of data as much as the next person, but this doesn’t feel very life giving (for us) or intelligent (for AI).</p>

<p>Don’t get me wrong, I absolutely think there are great uses for the tools that are emerging  - <a href="https://jarango.com/">Jorge Arango</a> recently <a href="https://mailchi.mp/8a146e863dbd/adit888892?e=2c811631cc">posted a piece</a> about how he uses it in his workflow, <a href="https://www.notably.ai/">Notably.ai</a> had an <a href="https://twitter.com/notablyai/status/1623803297013370882">interesting thread</a> about using it in research (also see <a href="https://andrewhinton.com/">Andrew Hinton’s</a> thread on <a href="https://twitter.com/inkblurt/status/1628082722559209486">research + ChatGPT</a>), and The Atlantic recently published an article about a writer who has used OpenAI’s Playground feature to <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2023/02/use-openai-chatgpt-playground-at-work/673195/">automate a tedious bit of repetitive writing</a>. But I am skeptical of the hype and the frenzy of activity dedicated to <a href="https://www.axios.com/2023/02/22/chatgpt-prompt-engineers-ai-job">cultivating the prompt engineer skillset</a>. Maybe because it’s all so… tediously banal. Where is the weirdness, the play, the exploration?</p>

<p>This is, after all, <a href="https://rushkoff.medium.com/how-we-taught-technology-to-program-humans-2388adf91364">Rushkoff’s suggestion</a> for how to stay connected to our humanity and to each other:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The answer is not to reject AI, but to work on retrieving and recognizing our humanity so we’re not so easily fooled into submission by these would-be conquerors. That means studying and engaging in community, the arts, spirituality, and play. More of us need to be building and using AI’s that are designed for assisting and augmenting such human choice and activity, rather than controlling it. There may be less money to be made in the short-term, but more of a human civilization to be manifest in the long run.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>What does it look like to engage in community, the arts, spirituality, and play with AI by our sides assisting and augmenting our choice and activity? How do we make these things a part of our life and not something we squeeze into 20 minutes a day as long as an app reminds us to? If we can’t make community, the arts, spirituality, and play the foundation of our lives and work as humans, how can we hope to partner with AI to make this happen? I mean, I want this! But how do we make this happen?</p>

<p>Because right now these “intelligent” systems that can pass the bar exam are telling us how much they <em>can’t</em> engage in spirituality and play. The bar is a highly structured exam based on a thoroughly vetted and documented set of case data that describes the history of law in a country. This is exactly the kind of data something like ChatGPT needs to seem as human as a lawyer. But it <a href="https://medium.com/@colin.fraser/chatgpt-automatic-expensive-bs-at-scale-a113692b13d5">still can’t write a Spozit</a>.</p>

<p>So, I guess if you are the type of human that is exceedingly logical with deep knowledge of a subject, your “being human” might look a little more like ChatGPT, but I am feeling pretty okay about how human the <a href="https://www.best-poems.net/mary_oliver/wild_geese.html">soft animal of my body</a> is, and the knowing it contains.</p>

<p>Speaking of which, I’d love to see more conversations about embodiment, somatics, and the <a href="https://www.semanticscholar.org/paper/Biology-of-Cognition-Maturana/00d769e34afad088619aa04e1d7911b2467009fd">biology of cognition</a>. Where are they? I know they are out there - who can point me in the right direction? While we are at it, where are the folks talking about field theory? Most of what I’ve read around AI, technology, and being human is largely grounded in the realm of the mind. We are missing what emerges when we are together in groups, beyond what we bring as individuals. And <a href="https://scholarlypublishingcollective.org/psup/gestalt-review/article/26/1/1/304868/Field-Theory-in-Contemporary-Gestalt-Therapy-Part">Jan Roubal and Gianni Franscetti point out</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“There is something new that appears in a meeting of people that transcends the individuals involved and even the relationship they cocreate. The whole of the situation is more than the sum of the people who meet each other. Moreover, the situation is forever changing from one moment to the next. <strong>This constant change, the flow of the situation, follows its own dynamics, and the people involved are constantly transformed by it, since they are functions of the situation in every here-and-now moment.</strong>”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>A million years ago I attended an executive program at Singularity University. At the time synthetic biology was on the horizon, a promise to unify wetware and software and we still might get there some day. But I think when it comes to embodiment this is where we really start to get a sense for what makes us human. How we can be in the field, attuned to the field, and allowing the ways in which situations change, moment to moment, to reveal what holds meaning, to clue us in to what we are up to together? How is it that we can know - that we can <em>sense</em> - what is happening not just for ourselves, but in the collective conscious and the Anima Mundi?</p>

<p>Our insatiable quest to build tools, to control the world and to know ourselves will continue and accelerate with the arrival of LLMs. There are things we will learn about the nature of intelligence and things we will learn about our own nature. Bruce Feiler shares his insight that ChatGPT can <a href="https://brucefeiler.substack.com/p/what-chatgpt-and-ted-lasso-can-teach">help teach prosocial behaviors</a>, which, to bring this back around to where we began, could definitely be a benefit in work environments. Maybe that’s what conference headliners will be talking about in a few years, “How ChatGPT Made Me and My Team More Human.”</p>

<p>Of course, I can’t help but think of the movie, “Her,” or my classmate <a href="http://jacobciocci.org/">Jacob Ciocci’s</a> senior project at Oberlin College in which a guy in the midwest falls in love with a girl online - they have so much in common! - only to learn that the object of his affection is a bot built from his own photos, journal entries, and other online detritus. Sometimes it feels like we are heading in this direction, preventing ourselves from feeling our humanity by insulating ourselves from the beautiful assortment of human beings that exist in this world. Going back to Rushkoff, he urges us that maybe “…instead of being afraid of AI, we should learn to be less afraid of other people.”</p>

<p>Maybe that’s where we are at. What it means to be human. To stop being afraid of other people.</p>

<hr />

<p>I don’t have a tidy conclusion to what turned into a rather long reflection piece, just a lot of curiosity and fascination about this stuff. I am rooting for us as humans to get back to being human, whether that’s at work or elsewhere. I am eagerly waiting for us to lean into our complexity and jettison functional understandings of ourselves for more more poetic and playful ways of being together in this world.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="worth-noting">Worth noting:</h3>

<p>What do you get when a philosopher, two cognitive scientists, and an education scientist walk into a bar? <a href="https://phys.org/news/2023-02-critical-isnt-overload.html">Critical Ignoring</a>, a better way to deal with the hellscape that is the internet.</p>

<p><a href="https://elizabethraynorhowes.substack.com/p/do-many-of-the-values-we-are-conditioned">Are your values really your own</a>, or have you been betraying yourself all along? Elizabeth Rayner Howes seems very good at this being human thing.</p>

<p>Apropos to absolutely nothing I have ever talked about here, I had to throw in this incredible website that <a href="https://belowthesurface.amsterdam/en/vondsten">documents artifacts</a> found while excavating the North/South metro line in Amsterdam, which goes all the way back to the year -119000 (!).</p>

<p>To counterbalance such a far afield share, here is John Cutler’s incredible <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/u/3/d/1XRx4p8cvA7r8RujYQhqFyTBSFAY7L9XJw_sifivRIaY/mobilebasic">short book (née Google Doc)</a> that helps teams sort out the messy details of product work.</p>

<p>Where do things like note taking and woodworking actually happen? I felt some serendipitous resonance between Jorge’s piece on <a href="https://mailchi.mp/e01e68208001/p606082y52?e=2c811631cc">Thinking Places</a> and Jack’s thoughts on <a href="https://www.jackcheng.com/sunday/389-working-with-your-hands/?ref=sunday-newsletter">Working with Your Hands</a>. What is happening between our brains and hands and thinking and making, and <em>where</em> is it all happening?</p>

<hr />

<p>If you made it this far, my guess is you were just scrolling to see how long the damn thing was. Hi! Nice to see you. Thanks for being here, and see you next month!</p>

          ]]>
        </description>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>the becoming 004</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com//the-becoming/004/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com//the-becoming/004/</guid>
        <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jan 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


        <description>
          <![CDATA[
            <p class="caption"><img src="/images/kp/004.jpg" alt="photo of The Visitors 360 music video at SFMOMA" />
SFMOMA's 2023 Exhibition of <a href="https://www.sfmoma.org/read/ragnar-kjartansson/">The Visitors</a>. Filmed at Rokeby, a very special place indeed.</p>

<p>January has arrived (and almost gone), and so has another edition of <strong><a href="https://methodandmatter.com/the-becoming/">the becoming</a></strong>. I'm <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/about/">Andi</a>, and this month I'm exploring foundations in living systems as a metaphor for how we can create daily practices that support our own flourishing.</p>

<p class="archive-notice">This is an archived version of <strong>the becoming</strong>. You can sign up to receive future editions using the form at the bottom of this page.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="foundations">Foundations</h3>
<blockquote>
  <p>You are only as good as your basics. - Grandmaster Doc-Fai Wong</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The time between the Gregorian and Lunar New Year has always felt liminal; a spacious unknowing on a good day, a terrifying void on a bad one. The murkiness makes it hard to sense patterns and listen for what is emerging, but this year I can feel the soft, subtle murmurs of something wanting attention. It trickles underneath conversations, rustles through the trees on my morning walks, and weaves itself into my Tarot pulls. What is beckoning? The words make themselves known:  <strong>foundations, roots, ground, seeds</strong>.</p>

<hr />

<p>Halfway through 2022 I got it into my head that I was going to learn Tai Chi and instead wound up a student of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Choy_Li_Fut">Choy Li Fut Kung Fu</a>. The school I enrolled in offers both and then some (Lion Dancing, Qi Gong, drumming) and when I saw the words ‘Kung Fu’ on their website a not-so-small voice inside of me said, “YES DO THAT.” And so I did. The school is wonderful - knowledgeable teachers, a clear lineage, a welcoming community - and it is an absolute delight to hit things.</p>

<p>Group classes have a wide range of students, from beginners like me to folks who are well beyond their first black belt. I found this confusing at first and noticed myself feeling profoundly apologetic whenever I was paired with an advanced student for a partner exercise. I also thought I was holding the class back by being so new because we would run through the same basic stances, punches, blocks, and kicks at the beginning of every class.</p>

<p>Slowly two things began to dawn on me: 1) I’m not <em>that</em> important and 2) what <em>is</em> important is a solid foundation. As our Grandmaster says, “you are only as good as your basics.” Day in and day out we drill the basics, whether it happens to be your first day of class or your 3000th.</p>

<p>I also started to realize that for most my life I’ve thought about foundations through the metaphor of buildings rather than living systems. In the built world you set a solid foundation, construct the framework on top, and that’s pretty much that. Which I’m sure is wildly ignorant of what actually takes place but I’m fairly certain that you don’t have to like, reinforce concrete slabs every day. Creating a solid foundation in living systems, on the other hand, requires a daily act of attention, energy, and effort.</p>

<p>A tree doesn’t put down roots and then stop growing. Energy, attention, and effort are funneled into nourishing the tree’s strong and expanding foundation. The breath, a foundational process of human aliveness, requires attention, energy, and effort to support the up/down regulation of our nervous system.</p>

<p>When I think of foundations through the lens of living systems, I feel a great sense relief. I can release myself from the pressure of needing to get things right “the first time” because in this new framing “the first time” doesn’t have any meaning. Strong foundations come from a daily practice of devotion and commitment, not from a single well-executed endeavor. And by attending to the basics, the foundations, the ground, the seeds of the future I am committed to living forward, everything else falls into place.</p>

<h4 id="some-questions-to-reflect-on-your-own-foundations">Some questions to reflect on your own foundations:</h4>
<ul class="bullets">
  <li>What are you committed to?</li>
  <li>What are the foundations of your leadership practice? Your life?</li>
  <li>What values keep you connected to who, why, and what you serve?</li>
  <li>What is the work and life that rests on this foundation?</li>
  <li>What are the basic practices that support this?</li>
  <li>How can you commit (or re-commit) to a daily practice in service of your deeply held commitments?</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h3 id="a-few-words-on-accountability">A Few Words on Accountability</h3>
<p><strong>‘Accountability’ has to be one of the most frequently used and useless words in business.</strong> A common refrain from leaders is that they want their teams to be more accountable, but when pressed to describe what that looks like they come up short. I think the disconnect comes from the belief that accountability is something other people do, rather than accountability as something that happens in <em>relationship</em>.</p>

<p>Thankfully, Jonathan Raymond has taken the time to write about the phenomenon in his HBR article, <a href="https://hbr.org/2016/10/do-you-understand-what-accountability-really-means">Do You Understand What Accountability Really Means?</a>. I liked the article enough that I actually picked up a copy of his book, <a href="https://bookshop.org/p/books/good-authority-how-to-become-the-leader-your-team-is-waiting-for-jonathan-raymond/15543866?ean=9781940858777">Good Authority: How to Become the Leader Your Team is Waiting For</a>, which might be a first for me when it comes to HBR.</p>

<p>Here’s why: Raymond isn’t offering quick fixes or generalized hot tips on how to solve the problem of accountability. He takes the time to demystify what accountability looks like, pursues a long term and humanistic perspective, points out the role leaders play in helping people be accountable, and susses out the <strong>nuances of early conversations that are critical for managers to have to help their team stay accountable <em>way before the train goes off the tracks</em></strong>. I also really appreciate his distinction between micromanagement and accountability: micromanagement is focused on tasks, while accountability is focused on relationships.</p>

<p>For those of you in a rush, here are the <strong>three most important steps</strong> that most managers skip:</p>

<p>1) <strong>The mention.</strong> The first step is naming small but problematic behaviors in an informal way in real time. By pulling an employee aside to put words to what you’re noticing, instead of waiting for a crisis, you start to build a relationship of mutual respect. You show that you genuinely care about their growth by acknowledging that they’re overwhelmed instead of pretending you don’t see and by helping them find their contribution to a conflict instead of letting it fester.</p>

<p>2) <strong>The invitation.</strong> We’re great at seeing patterns in other people’s behavior; it’s harder to see those patterns in ourselves. The invitation is taking the time to help your employee connect the dots. For example, let’s say you saw typos in a team member’s client email on Monday, they seemed disengaged in a team meeting on Wednesday, and then there was a miscommunication with a teammate on Thursday. Ask them what those events might have in common, or point to a deeper theme.</p>

<p>3) <strong>The conversation.</strong> This is the place to go deeper, by asking questions that guide people to the “aha!” moment, when they discover for themselves how changing this pattern at work would have positive impacts at home. It might sound something like this: “We’ve been talking about you taking on too many projects and the impact that’s having on the quality of the most important ones. I’m not asking for you to share what you come up with here, but one question that helps me is, ‘Where does this pattern show up in my personal life, and what would be the benefit if I stopped?’”</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="working-with-discomfort">Working With Discomfort</h3>
<p>Last year I wrote an article, <a href="https://medium.com/method-matter/the-art-of-receiving-feedback-1561aaa74d6c">The Art of Receiving Feedback</a>, where I talked about the difference between listening from “personality” and listening from “center”. The terms come from Wendy Palmer and Janet Crawford’s work in <a href="https://bookshop.org/p/books/leadership-embodiment-how-the-way-we-sit-and-stand-can-change-the-way-we-think-and-speak-wendy-palmer/10266599?ean=9781492946694">leadership embodiment</a>, where “personality” refers to the automatic and unconscious subroutines we run in response to our environment - and “center” refers to our capacity to hold and be with what is happening without our automatic responses taking over. Somewhere along the way being centered became synonymous with being totally calm or detached, which couldn’t be farther from the truth. When someone left a comment looking for clarification, I realized it was probably <a href="https://medium.com/method-matter/working-with-discomfort-da3a0cc27358">worth a longer write-up</a>. <strong>The tl;dr is that we center to feel <em>more</em>, to be with life in its fullness, not to feel <em>less</em>.</strong></p>

<hr />

<h3 id="worth-your-attention">Worth Your Attention</h3>
<p>A few things that resonated deeply over the past month.</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Those of you who are passingly familiar my writings or talks may know how much I love writing letters to my future or past self. The practice helps me to reflect, process, and integrate events, relationships, longings, and experiences. Craig Mod’s <a href="https://craigmod.com/roden/075/">January newsletter</a> is a beautiful meditation on what makes us who we are. The through line is the idea of archetypes, the visible mold of what is possible reflected through the people that surround us. For Craig, archetypes are a kind of foundation that can usher in a world of possibility from childhood onwards, “when a child is provided a foundation, a troop of positive archetypes, everyone they encounter is elevated.” But even if a kid doesn’t get access to a wide range of positive archetypes, we can configure our work and think about it in such a way as to set examples for younger versions of ourselves.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Dan Harris (of 10% happier) gave a humorous and poignant TED talk, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NuhIzO57HVk">The Benefits of Not Being a jerk to Yourself</a> covering his own journey to deeper self love. The storytelling is solid, but what I appreciate most is how accessible these ideas are in Dan’s hands. Well worth 13 minutes and 38 seconds of your time.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>I keep coming back to Tara Brach’s lecture on ‘<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vQHvUVZNIR4">Realizing Your Deepest Intention</a>” because she is such a beautiful embodiment of wisdom and humor, and because I want to live life as a manifestation of my innate potential, fully embodied in each moment. Through stories, reflections, and short meditations, Tara guides listeners to connect with their deepest intention and be able to spot the three signs of a truly liberating intention.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>I cannot possibly do justice in summarizing <a href="https://annehelen.substack.com/p/the-diminishing-returns-of-calendar">this piece on calendar time</a> by Anne Helen so I’ll just share a quote and the link: <em>"Through the commitment to busyness and its organization, we inscribe and reinscribe a certain understanding of time onto our children, onto each other, onto ourselves. We discipline our messy, distracted, inquisitive, emotive selves into the most valuable possible forms of human capital possible. We suggest that sort of regimentation is not only possible (just organize harder!) but aspirational."</em></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Over the last few weeks <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/marliekekieboom/">Marlieke Kieboom</a> has been posting a wonderful series on Public Systemic Design over on Medium. I hope this series reaches as many eyeballs as possible because this is the type of critical inquiry the design world desperately needs more of. Catch the current posts at <a href="https://medium.com/publicsystemicdesign">Unbounded Affairs</a> and sign up to be notified for future posts.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

          ]]>
        </description>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>the becoming 003</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com//the-becoming/003/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com//the-becoming/003/</guid>
        <pubDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2022 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


        <description>
          <![CDATA[
            <p class="caption"><img src="/images/kp/003.jpg" alt="photo of Durham, NC in the winter" />
Winter woods in Durham, North Carolina. December 2022</p>

<p>Hello, I’m Andi, this is <strong><a href="/the-becoming/">the becoming</a></strong>, and I’m so glad you are here. December’s edition explores year end reflections, the relationship between power and resistance, a new (potential) course for leaders who want to add coaching to their skillset, and an upcoming talk.</p>

<p>What’s cooking: empanadas and tortilla de patatas</p>

<p class="archive-notice">This is an archived version of <strong>the becoming</strong>. You can sign up to receive future editions using the form at the bottom of this page.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="end-of-year-reflections">End of Year Reflections</h3>

<p>I’m pretty big on reflective practices, but not so big on structure. Personally, I find extensive guides with prompts for every category of life to be pretty draining. On any given day I’m not sure what will be energy giving and where my curiosity will take me, which also holds true for whenever I happen to sit down to reflect on a cycle of time. Because of this I’ve created my own reflection process that keeps me focused but also allows me to play.</p>

<p>I shared it publicly for the first time last year to positive response, and this year I revised it slightly to include a piece of my process that was missing. The updated version contains a new section for reflecting and capturing who you are and what you are up to in the world right now. This is about connecting to yourself and sensing what is most alive for you in the moment you are sitting down and beginning to reflect. Like a balance sheet - a financial snapshot of a business at a certain point in time - what gets captured in this exercise can be compared year over year so you can begin to see the thread that connects who you were, who you are, and who you are becoming.</p>

<p>You can access the full guide here on Medium: <a href="https://medium.com/method-matter/at-the-end-of-the-year-bd201ea99541">At the End of the Year: Guided Reflections Across a Transitional Threshold</a>.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="the-relationship-between-power-and-resistance">The Relationship Between Power and Resistance</h3>

<p>Here is a fun bit that surfaced in my research on resistance in organizations: <em>the origin of resistance is not in the context of change, it is in the context of power</em>. I first stumbled across H.B. Karp’s Power Resistance model in “<a href="https://www.amazon.com/Gestalt-Coaching-Primer-Awareness-Intelligence/dp/0997378131/ref=sr_1_1?crid=1KPZO3UT3D0QI&amp;keywords=a+gestalt+coaching+primer&amp;qid=1671832512&amp;sprefix=a+gestalt+coaching+prim%2Caps%2C195&amp;sr=8-1">A Gestalt Coaching Primer</a>” which lead me to “<a href="https://www.amazon.com/Change-Leader-Approach-H-Karp/dp/0883904691/ref=tmm_pap_swatch_0?_encoding=UTF8&amp;qid=1671832557&amp;sr=8-1">The Change Leader: Using a Gestalt Approach with Work Groups</a>” where Karp discusses the model in more detail. There really isn’t much about this on the internet, which surprises me because the insights that come from this model seem incredibly useful (more on that in a minute).</p>

<p>Most business rags (e.g. HBR, MIT Sloan Management Review, business + strategy) view resistance as a natural part of change and authors who write on the topic offer strategies for overcoming it. This itself is revealing: resistance as something to be dealt with and defeated, rather than something that might provide meaningful insight and relevant knowledge. I have yet to come across an article written from the perspective of those experiencing the change, or that invite the possibility that maybe the proposed change isn’t really the right way to go.</p>

<p>Gestalt psychology brings a new perspective, one that sees resistance as a healthy and vital part of a system. I mean, just pause for a minute and really imagine what it would be like to work in an organization that never resisted change. It might be exciting! It could also be incredibly confusing and a lot of energy would go into simply understanding the state of the organization in any given moment. Which is to say, resistance can act as a stabilizing force in a system. When leaders try to overcome resistance, they loose access to important information and organizational awareness.</p>

<p>But resistance is not a monolith, and Karp’s model brings something very interesting into our field of focus: resistance can be either functional or dysfunctional and it’s pretty useful to know which you are dealing with.</p>

<p class="caption"><img src="/images/kp/content/power-resistance.jpeg" alt="Karp's Power Resistace Model" />
H.B. Karp's Power Resistance Model</p>

<p>There are four possibilities here: I want something or I don’t, and either I get that that thing or I don’t. As Karp says, “power is a means to an end, not an end in itself, and resistance operates exactly the same way.” So power and resistance are both positive, functional conditions. Getting what we want and avoiding what we don’t want are equivalent. On the other hand, there are two negative, dysfunctional conditions where we want something and don’t get it, or don’t want something and get it anyways. I’m not the biggest fan of the labels for these, but they make their point.</p>

<p>Dorothy E. Siminovitch describes the difference between them as positive and unaware resistance and says, “positive use of resistance helps maintain the personal power of self-integrity and identity, but unaware resistance leaves us vulnerable to ‘loser’ or ‘victim’ status that seems to be beyond our control.” Positive resistance is about setting boundaries while unaware resistance leads to old patterns of self-defeating and distressing behavior, such as teams complaining but not taking action and passive-aggressive acting out.</p>

<p>Hierarchy is a natural part of organizations, and with hierarchy comes power. I’m incredibly curious about how often positive resistance is possible in settings where ‘no’ is not an acceptable response. What forms of boundaries do people and teams put in place to ensure they don’t get what they don’t want? Or does very lack of the ability to say ‘no’ take away the possibility of positive resistance entirely?</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="leader-as-coach-a-cohort-based-course">Leader as Coach: A Cohort-based Course</h3>

<p><img src="/images/kp/content/leader-as-coach.jpeg" alt="Leader as Coach header" /></p>

<p>I’ve been thinking a lot about how to teach essential coaching skills to leaders and managers. There are some great books and articles that cover various coaching models, but books aren't enough. In the same way we can’t read a pile of books on how to play the piano and then play a concerto the first time we sit down at one, we can’t read a pile of books on coaching and expect to fluidly coach the first time we try with another human. At the same time, leaders don’t need to be professional coaches, they just need the foundations and some safe space to put it all into practice.</p>

<p>I’m currently designing a course (in beta) for leaders who want to integrate coaching into their work through hands-on practice. Right now I’m planning on running the first cohort at the end of January, from January 30th to February 3rd. It’s short and intense - 5 two hour workshops across the course of a week. Each workshop will focus on a theme, introduce relevant frameworks and methodologies, and then create experiential learning opportunities for folks to put the learnings into practice.</p>

<p>If this sounds relevant to you or anyone you know, <a href="https://maven.com/andrea-mignolo/leader-as-coach">head to Maven.com to learn more and sign up for announcements</a>.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="leading-design-conference-in-san-francisco">Leading Design Conference in San Francisco</h3>

<p><img src="/images/kp/content/leading-design-2023.jpeg" alt="Leader as Coach header" /></p>

<p>In 2020 I gave a virtual talk at a conference halfway around the world. Owing to my inability to understand timezones and calendars, the talk was scheduled for 4:30am in California. I woke up, got dressed, put on makeup, and sat down at my computer. The conference organizers prepped me on how the video transition would happen and when I should begin speaking. 10 minutes later, I was on!</p>

<p>And for the next 30 minutes I spoke into a camera, a ring light illuminating my office while the darkness of night reigned outside my windows. I brought energy, I gestured, I told stories, I shared insights. All into the void of the camera and my still, quiet, cold office. On screen I could not see any of the participants. I could not gauge reactions. It was just me, in my office, hoping that someone was on the other side. When it was over I crawled back into bed (in full clothes and makeup) and slept for a few hours. The rest of the day I felt pretty dejected and depressed, and vowed to not do talk until I could be in person again.</p>

<p>Which brings us to 2023! Leading Design is happening in San Francisco in February and I’ll be giving my first in-person talk since the pandemic: “<a href="https://leadingdesign.com/conferences/sanfran-2023/speakers/andrea-mignolo">It’s Okay to be the Boss!</a>” I’m excited about the topic (which takes its cue from many client conversations over the years) and even more excited to be at a conference again with so many wonderful people.</p>

<p>If you are interested in attending I have a discount code you can use for 20% off the ticket price: <strong>JOINANDREA</strong>.</p>

<hr />

<p>Thanks for listening. I hope you have a wonderful, nourishing, and restful end of the year.</p>

          ]]>
        </description>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>the becoming 002</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com//the-becoming/002/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com//the-becoming/002/</guid>
        <pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2022 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


        <description>
          <![CDATA[
            <p class="caption"><img src="/images/kp/002.jpg" alt="photo of the Catskills in autumn" />
Late afternoon in the Catskills, October 2022</p>

<p>Hi, I'm Andi and this is <strong><a href="/the-becoming/">the becoming</a></strong>. You are reading these words because somewhere along the way you shared an interested in having this letter land in your inbox. Thank you, and welcome!</p>

<p class="archive-notice">This is an archived version of <strong>the becoming</strong>. You can sign up to receive future editions using the form at the bottom of this page.</p>

<p>With the short days and long nights here in the northern hemisphere, I’m feeling called to slow down and become a little more quiet, a bit more still. To let go of the efforting of the past year and allow the fruits of that work fall to the earth as compost, nutrients that will nourish whatever begins to emerge next spring. Some of this comes from inner stirrings, and the rest comes my first encounter with COVID last month. What a doozy that one is! At the tail end of a wonderful trip to upstate New York for the first in-person IxDA board retreat in over two years, COVID found me. It’s been humbling, frustrating, illuminating all at the same time. I’m feeling much better but being ultra-compassionate with myself as I learn what my body and tolerate, and what it can’t.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="building-a-relationship-with-change-sneak-peak-and-request-for-feedback">Building a Relationship with Change: Sneak Peak and Request for Feedback</h3>
<p>In <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/research/">researching resistance in organizations</a>, I’ve naturally had to spend a good deal of time understanding the nature of change. Management theory tends write about change from the perspective of the change agent, ignoring the experience of those that appear to be “resisting.” The change agent undoubtedly is on the “right” side of change, and with an 8 step process these change agents can marshal teams around a vision and march them forward in tandem. This all sounds good in theory but seems to never quite pan out in practice. It’s like the brute force approach to change, where the shortest distance between point A and B is a straight line.</p>

<p>But what if resistance was healthy? What if change happens by first becoming what you are, rather than becoming what you are not? The most compelling theory of change I’ve come across is the Paradoxical Theory of Change from the world of Gestalt Psychology. In first becoming what you are, you must integrate all parts of the system (either individual, team, or organization), including all the parts that have been disowned. When you have done that, and can be fully with your experience as you are, change is inevitable.</p>

<p>I wrote an article about it on Medium that is currently in draft form and, if you are so inclined, would love your feedback. I’ll leave the request open ended and simply share the link: <a href="https://medium.com/method-matter/building-a-relationship-with-change-3602cf6e7890">Building a Relationship With Change (draft for feedback)</a>.</p>

<p><em>Thank you.</em></p>

<hr />

<h3 id="zero-drafts">Zero Drafts</h3>
<blockquote>
  <p>“How do I know what I think until I see what I say?” - E.M. Forster</p>
</blockquote>

<p>When it comes to writing articles that get published I’m pretty slow as far as things go. It takes me a while to really understand what I think and put that into something coherent enough to be hopefully useful to others. A few weeks ago I came across a <a href="https://twitter.com/MushtaqBilalPhD/status/1590988185500520448">Twitter thread</a> on <a href="https://www.margaretedits.com/2015/04/14/writing-a-zero-draft/">Zero Drafts</a>: a method for writing and working through what you know before starting on an actual draft of a paper, essay, short story, etc.</p>

<p>It’s been incredibly useful for writing more and getting to the core of what I think I know. I can also see how this process could be useful not just for academic writing, but in a business context as well. I think back my time as an executive and trying to connect the work of the teams I led to the larger company vision. Not just in terms of OKRs, but how we were deeply relating to what the business was trying to achieve and the ways in which we were doing that. At that time I worked mostly in decks (thanks, business school), which I think is a hinderance to really gaining clarity of <em>thinking</em>. If I had known about Zero Drafts I think I would have gotten to clarity sooner, and the decks I used to communicate would have been more succinct and coherent.</p>

<p>What helps <em>you</em> understand what you think?</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="slow-multitasking">Slow Multitasking</h3>
<p>Jason Mesut shared this TED Talk on <a href="https://www.npr.org/2019/05/10/719575727/tim-harford-how-can-slow-motion-multitasking-boost-our-creativity">Slow Motion Multitasking</a> and it <em>really</em> resonated with how I work. It gave me permission to hold a lot of projects simultaneously and dip into them as I feel called to. I use <a href="https://museapp.com">Muse App</a> for a lot of my early explorations, and have organized the high level boards into which I can throw materials as I come across them, to be digested and organized whenever I come around to it.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="mapping-emotions">Mapping Emotions</h3>
<p><a href="https://www.marcbrackett.com">Marc Brackett</a>, founding director of the Yale Center for Emotional Intelligence created an app a few years ago called <a href="https://moodmeterapp.com">Mood Meter</a>. The primary focus was on building emotional awareness and management via a simple interface that helped people to check-in to their emotions and expand their emotional vocabulary.</p>

<p>Last week Marc, along with a team of engineers from Pinterest, released a new app called “<a href="https://howwefeel.org">How We Feel</a>.” Based on the same premise as Mood Meter, the new “journal for your well being” is expansive in what it offers. Mood check-ins are still a primary interaction, but now the app also includes incredibly useful 1 - 2 minute videos with exercises that can help people learn to modulate their moods and shift into more positive states. I’m thoroughly impressed by what they’ve put together and hope that it reaches as many people as possible.</p>

<hr />

<p>If you are in a part of the world that celebrates Thanksgiving, I hope it was filled with belonging, nourishment, and rest. And to everyone out there, may the last month of the Gregorian year be easeful and kind for you.</p>

<p>See you in December.</p>

          ]]>
        </description>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>the becoming 001</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com//the-becoming/001/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com//the-becoming/001/</guid>
        <pubDate>Tue, 25 Oct 2022 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


        <description>
          <![CDATA[
            <p class="caption"><img src="/images/kp/001.jpg" alt="smiley" />
Point Reyes National Seashore, October 2022</p>

<p>Hi! I’m Andi, and this is <strong><a href="/the-becoming/">the becoming</a></strong>, a newsletter that invites warm and open conversations exploring what it means to be in the complexity of life as a leader, however you inhabit that role.</p>

<p class="archive-notice">This is an archived version of <strong>the becoming</strong>. You can sign up to receive future editions using the form at the bottom of this page.</p>

<p>Here in San Francisco we’ve finally head a break of good weather after weeks of cold and fog. Strangely, the warmth and sun have brought up some hidden grief I’ve been carrying and it feels somewhat fitting to process it in the gloriousness of a perfect day.</p>

<p>So, how are you?</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="researching">Researching</h3>

<p>This quarter I’m researching how people experience and respond to resistance in organizations. In my time as an executive I developed ways to use resistance as a tool for navigating organizational complexity. Rather than confront it head on and try and overcome it with brute force, resistance helped me to feel out paths with the fewest obstacles. As if the resistance was saying, “not here, but if you move to the left you can go that way for a while.”</p>

<p>I’ve been doing some training in Gestalt psychology recently and am quite taken with their understanding of resistance. Not as a negative or unwanted occurrence to be overcome, but as a healthy and necessary part of a system. I mean, imagine if we willingly and immediately went along anytime a significant other asked us to change something they didn’t like. We would no longer be ourselves! Now, there might be a conversation to be had and issues to explore, but simply changing without question because someone wants you to leads to loss and disconnection. Resistance helps maintain balance and integrity of any system, allowing change to happen in a sustainable and healthy way.</p>

<p>And so! I’m interested in talking to leaders and hearing about their experience of resistance in their organizations. In exchange I’m offering insights from my research via a free coaching session. If you or anyone you know might be interested, you can <a href="/research/">sign up here</a>.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="writing">Writing</h3>

<p>The topic of transitions is kind of an evergreen theme, since we’re all going through them all the time. Especially after the last couple of years, phew. <a href="https://wmbridges.com">William and Susan Bridges</a> have been working in the transition space for decades, and their work is accordingly deep and insightful. Using their three-phase model of transition, I <a href="https://medium.com/method-matter/on-navigating-lifes-transitions-104d619316b9">wrote a piece</a> about how we move through transitions through the lens of one of my own (which I am still in the midst of).</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="reading">Reading</h3>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Altogether-You-Experiencing-spiritual-transformation-ebook/dp/B089P38ZNZ/">Altogether You: experiencing personal and spiritual transformation with Internal Family Systems therapy</a>, by Jenna Riemersma</p>

<p>This book came my way via a recommendation from a client. The “spiritual transformation” part in the title refers to the traditions in the Christian lineage of teachings. I’m not a religious person but do like to read religious texts, so I felt pretty at home with it (as one reviewer says, "It's not just for Christians!). This book is not in any way, shape, or form trying to convert or proselytize, but rather to teach Internal Family Systems in a way that illustrates its congruity with the teachings of Jesus. If you really can’t get down with any references to religion, this book probably isn’t for you. But you’d miss out on the deep compassion, humor, and wisdom this book offers. It’s one of the top books I’ve read on Internal Family Systems and puts theory into action with incredibly useful reflection questions at the end of each chapter. I use IFS in my coaching work and in my own personal development, and this book brought new insights and perspectives that have been exceptionally supportive in going deeper with all of my parts.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="wondering">Wondering</h3>

<p>I’ve been thinking a lot about what it means to belong, where we seek belonging, and what it is we are belonging to. I think some of this has come up naturally with my transition away from working in organizations, which for a long time was a (somewhat misplaced) primary source of belonging. As a pretty strong introvert, and without the prompts of daily office life, where is it that I belong? Or with whom? What does it look like to belong to myself?</p>

<p>How do you belong?</p>

          ]]>
        </description>
      </item>

  </channel>

</rss>
