<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"

	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	>

  <channel>
    <title>method &#038; matter</title>
    <atom:link href="https://methodandmatter.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <link>https://methodandmatter.com</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <generator>Middleman (Ruby)</generator>
    <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>
		<description>From the desk of Andrea Mignolo</description>
		<meta property="og:image" content="https://methodandmatter.com/images/mm-round.png" />
    <image>
      <url>https://methodandmatter.com/images/mm-round.png</url>
      <title>method &#038; matter</title>
      <link>https://methodandmatter.com</link>
    </image>


			<item>
        <title>[Essay] How metaphors shape our understanding and experience.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/metaphors/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/metaphors/</guid>
				<pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<blockquote>
  <p>"The deep structure of thought is based on feelings, memories, beliefs and values, and is revealed through our behaviors and our choice of words. In individuals, this deep structure is referred to as our personality; in organizations, it is called 'corporate culture.'" — Roger Ellerton</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>"The challenge facing modern managers is to become accomplished in the art of using metaphor to find new ways of seeing, understanding, and shaping their actions." — Gareth Morgan</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Metaphors are not just poetic turns of phrase used to embellish speech with an ornamental flourish, they are fundamental to how we perceive and think about the world. Metaphors help us to understand our experiences and create meaning—who we take ourselves to be, what the nature of our work is, how we orient in relationships, how we get stuck, what challenges feel like, and what feels possible (to name a few!). As <a href="/writing/essays/living-in-language">unique observers</a>, we experience the world through the intersection of language, emotion, and the body. Our knowing is highly experiential and metaphor is one of the primary ways we create conceptual coherence across experiences.</p>

<p class="caption"><img src="/images/wmw/pig.jpg" alt="What is a pige?" />
What is the pig? via Garath Morgan</p>

<p>I love this illustration from Gareth Morgan's book, <em><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Imaginization-Gareth-Morgan/dp/1576750264">Imaginization</a></em>, where we see  a pig surrounded by unique observers. Taken as a whole, the question, "What is the pig?" reveals the complexity of what at first glance seems pretty simple. The pig is not just an animal, of course, it is in fact many things all at once, depending on who you ask. For the artist the pig might be a muse, to the child a best friend, to the butcher a livelihood, to the philosopher a figment of the imagination. How each person imagines the pig will reveal certain aspects of how they see and interact with the world, while obscuring others. For example, the child who sees the pig as a best friend will not have access to the possibility of the pig being a form of sustenance.</p>

<p>The same is true for organizations—the images we hold of what an organization is determines what is and isn't possible for how the organization behaves. If you look at theories of management from the last century, the metaphor underpinning our concept of an organization is "organization as machine." And the component parts of this machine, the functions, are reified in business schools which in turn reinforce the make up of the organization. Finance, Marketing, Sales, R&amp;D, Legal, Operations, Human Resources, Customer Service. Therein lies your organization, give or take.</p>

<p>The machine metaphor works well for businesses that are comprised largely of routine and predictable tasks. Personally, I have never been part of an organization with routine and predicable tasks. Trying to adhere to a mechanistic metaphor in a chaotic age, well, most of us know how absolutely frustrating, dehumanizing, and pervasive mechanistic structures can be. And while attempts have been made to develop new ways of organizing, most have not yet fully escaped the organization-as-machine metaphor.</p>

<p>While we may not be able to change the metaphoric orientation of the organizations we work for, awareness of mechanistic underpinnings can help leaders navigate their roles. The most critical move is to  acknowledge and accept that your work is carried out within a mechanistic structure. A structure that seems almost designed to prevent people from fully exercising their autonomy and care for the populations the organization serves. Daniel Schmachtenberger calls corporations "obligate sociopaths" which is incredibly provocative and also an entirely different topic. Suffice it to say, if you're looking for another metaphor to understand your place of employment, this might be a viable option.</p>

<p>Now, this might sound bad! But while are constrained to some degree by these mechanistic structures, we're not powerless within them. This is where the <a href="https://www.dukeupress.edu/on-decoloniality">wisdom of decolonial scholars like Papa Mignolo</a> comes in. As he says, "you cannot decolonize the institution, but you can do decolonial work inside of it." He was talking about the academic world, but it applies to most organizations. Just as decolonial thinkers work within institutional constraints while imagining and creating alternative ways of knowing and being, leaders can work within mechanistic structures while fostering more human-centered practices.</p>

<p>One of the most fertile areas to bring our discernment to is the domain of leadership. What metaphor describes the kind of leader you are? What does this metaphor make possible, and what does it hide? What metaphor do you think others might use to describe your leadership? If you want to know how you are doing as a leader, ask the people you work with what animal or storybook character best describes you. The answers will be far more illuminating than any 360 report. And this isn't just a clever leadership hack—it works because metaphorical thinking is fundamental to how we make sense of our world.</p>

<p>Metaphors are <em>everywhere</em>.  In the book <em><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Metaphors-We-Live-George-Lakoff/dp/0226468011/ref=sr_1_1?crid=3GW9615LG5YSK&amp;dib=eyJ2IjoiMSJ9.tE-eptaf3Nm5LcLLS9T934anAaR4kwQBA2LFJdnPYC9oewn3avLsRMUDs5zLzAm7ktMTUdA3jpsawpq23aRZANWP7VDkVl_n_TrdCr4XU2-n8GWVJaCCvwKK6MteHguKaWHdDKyM81bNvbthOHQUxxOM6sRiHE-1HNYmconVwyyA-ARnLatJMWaGXtKYNSJ_zpzgOh1GoNqeMsmXkhtBrAso7wrCncUVA2PUMSIpFw0.eeTCAAcmjuHT4FO31N05WMym139WXuOniKWH7R00PJQ&amp;dib_tag=se&amp;keywords=metaphors+we+live+by&amp;qid=1737231084&amp;s=books&amp;sprefix=metaphors+we+live+by%2Cstripbooks%2C158&amp;sr=1-1">Metaphors We Live By</a></em>, George Lakoff and Mark Johnson define metaphor as "understanding and experiencing one kind of thing in terms of another." For Gemma Fiumara, metaphor links embodied schemata with cognitive processes, illuminating the biological origins of concepts like balance, scale, force, and cycles. Metaphor lives not only in language, but also in (and through) the body. Metaphors are <em>pervasive</em>.</p>

<p>As a leader, paying attention to metaphors—in imagery, gesture, and sound—is a great way to gain insight into how folks on your team (or anyone in the organization, really) are relating to a situation, opportunity, or challenge. For example, I worked at an organization where senior leadership always wanted to know "whose throat to choke" on any given project or initiative. Yet they couldn't seem to make the connection between the metaphor of accountability-as-violence and the undercurrent of blame pervading the organization's culture. Or a presentation that was given by a new hire: one of the first slides showed a photo of a wintery mountain tundra, with a man out front scanning the horizon. Behind him several people strained against the ropes of supply-laden sleds, pulling them up a steep incline. This image was used to show metaphorically how he saw his role (out front) and where he saw everyone else (pulling heavy weight behind him). And yet, this person was surprised that once promising collaborations suddenly turned cold.</p>

<p>Metaphors <em>matter</em>. They largely exist beyond our conscious awareness, which is what makes them such a powerful structure for leaders to work with. Metaphors are a rich source of information about how folks on your team, in your department, and in the organization itself think about the challenges and opportunities in front of them. Metaphors can be used to unblock individuals and teams when they are stuck. I once worked with a team who felt, metaphorically, that they were the night maids—they felt their role was to clean up after everyone and they largely felt invisible. They hadn't decided this before hand, it's just something that evolved over the course of many years. What they wanted, instead, was to be quilters. To weave together disparate parts of the organization and to create a beautiful offering that made things better for everyone involved. A little more comfortable, a little more fun, a little more connected, a little more visible.</p>

<p>As leaders, we often encounter deeply embedded metaphors that shape not just our organizations, but our entire way of thinking about interaction and conflict. Sometimes these metaphors are so entrenched in how an entire culture views the world, so woven into the material of reality, that we forget they are metaphors to begin with. Take, for example, how we think about disagreement in organizations. Lakoff and Johnson spend an extensive amount of time with the culturally pervasive metaphor "argument as war". Not just the language we use to talk about arguments (e.g. "He <em>attacked every weak point</em> in my argument"), but the very belief that arguments can be won and lost is tied up in metaphor.</p>

<p>As an alternative, they invite us consider a culture where argument is viewed as a dance, where the "participants are seen as performers, and the goal is to perform in a balanced and aesthetically pleasing way." This reframing from combat to collaborative performance isn't just theoretical— it has profound implications for how we lead. When leaders shift from seeing workplace disagreements as battles to be won to seeing them as opportunities for collective meaning-making, it transforms both the process and outcomes of difficult conversations.</p>

<p>I like to think of arguments as a process of dramatic and participatory storytelling, where people energetically and enthusiastically share their perspective. Each perspective contributes to enlarging the sense of what is happening, to creating a bigger and clearer picture of the whole. When the energy present in the system has been fully released, a shift happens and participants gain access to more spaciousness, at which point they can look at what emerged in the collaborative image-making process with more clarity and presence.</p>

<p>When we begin to examine the ways metaphors construct our daily experiences and interactions at work, new worlds of understanding open up. We can listen to the metaphors used by the people we work with and gain insight into their direct experience. How does the person you are  talking with describe the challenges or opportunities in front of them? How do they think about their colleagues? How do they see organizational dynamics? The organization itself? And what do those metaphors both reveal and conceal?</p>

<p>As you bring your awareness to the metaphors being used by those in your care, think about what other metaphors might open up new ways of seeing. One way to do this is through open and honest questions. For example, "If this challenge were a chapter in a book, what would its title be?" You can also bring metaphor into the conversation, prompting the person or team you are working with to come up with a metaphor to describe the situation (or themselves), and a new metaphor for how they'd like the situation (or themselves) to be.</p>

<p>As leaders in an increasingly complex world, our relationship with metaphor is both a mirror and a compass. It reflects our current understanding while pointing the way toward new possibilities. By becoming more conscious of the metaphors that shape our organizational lives—whether they're machines, dances, or quilts—we gain access to a powerful tool for transformation. The metaphors we choose don't just describe our reality; they actively shape it. What new worlds might you create by changing the metaphors you lead by?</p>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Essay] How we separate and name things to make observations.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/distinctions/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/distinctions/</guid>
				<pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<blockquote>
  <p>Acquiring  new distinctions = improving our capacity for seeing new possibilities and taking  more effective Action in a given domain. This is important to notice.  So we make this fundamental claim: <strong>We look with our eyes, but we observe through  our distinctions.</strong>  — Chalmers Brothers</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Here is a thing we do in language: we separate things from other things and name those things so that we can point to specific features of the world in order to make observations about what we are seeing. Which is to say, more succinctly, we make distinctions.</p>

<p>For example, if I go into a forest by myself I will see trees, plants, birds, insects, and flowers. But if I go into a forest with an herbalist they will be able to make meaningful distinctions about the plants, trees, and flowers—which ones can be consumed, which might be used in the case of illness and injury, and which ones to avoid. What used to appear as bundles of photosynthesizing organisms or radical bursts of color, through the distinctions of the herbalist, reveals the symbiotic and nuanced relationship between humans and our plant allies.</p>

<p>Distinctions play a role in all domains of life. And mastery in any domain requires deep familiarity with specific sets of distinctions. To become a surgeon or a carpenter or a chef requires a fluency with specialized terms that are networked together in a specific way <sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. In the case of a surgeon, the distinctions they acquire through their training allow them to perceive, comprehend, and interact with the human body in a specialized way according to the philosophy of Western medicine. Of course, a practitioner of Traditional Chinese Medicine, also a specialist in the human body, will have an entirely different set of distinctions than those of the surgeon based on the philosophy of that particular lineage. While both specialize in healing the human body, each specific set of distinctions opens up radically different pathways for healing.</p>

<p>My background in design provides me with a set of linguistic distinctions that allow me to observe the human-made world in specific ways. I mean, put a bunch of designers together in an elevator and you’ll see these distinctions at work—the elevator goes nowhere while five people discuss the various affordances and design decisions that went into crafting the elevator, its interface, and how humans interact with that interface. People without this particular set of distinctions simply get in the elevator and press the button for their floor (which is not always as simple as would seem, and then the designers discuss even <em>longer</em>).</p>

<p>Most of the time we aren’t aware of our distinctions. How we see the world seems to be how it is. If we feel stuck, if our actions don't generate the results we want, then there is probably something we are unable to see. When we make new distinctions we can make new things happen. If we can’t change what we can’t see, and distinctions are a way of seeing, then distinctions must be an essential component of change.</p>

<p>In coaching, we can offer distinctions in service of supporting the person we are working with so they can see themselves and their situation in new ways. We can also listen closely to the distinctions people use to understand how the world appears to them—what they are able to see and what remains hidden. Maybe someone on your team is making a distinction about what is happening in a particular project that is going sideways. And that distinction isn’t really helping them resolve the situation they are in. In the coaching role, you can offer a new set of distinctions that changes how they see the situation, which leads to possibilities for new kinds of action.</p>

<p>A typical distinction that frequently gets people stuck is the one that casts the world in terms of right and wrong—as in they are right and everyone else is wrong!</p>

<p>You can see how this perspective limits possibilities—when right/wrong is the primary distinction then there is only one path forward: resist everyone who is wrong and convince them to accept what is right (generally a fool’s errand). This kind of black and white thinking creates conflict and usually increases, rather than decreases, resistance. As a coach you may offer someone new distinctions about the motivations (such as intrinsic/extrinsic) of others, what people care about, and what they are goaled on by the company, which can start to make visible the specific perspectives and truths each person holds. These distinctions open up new possibilities for action that weren’t available under the right/wrong distinction.</p>

<p>It’s also worth taking a moment to point out that the English language has a limited range of distinctions (this is true for every language, none is complete). I note this because, especially in transnational companies where folks from different linguistic and cultural backgrounds are collaborating, we can forget and think our way of making observations is universal, <em>especially when English is the common language spoken in an organization</em><sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>.  And English, because it is the language of colonization, (along with a few others, but none have become the “world wide language of communication” like English has) has mistaken a very provincial worldview for a universal one.</p>

<p>I recently came across <a href="https://mujaawarah.org/en/">a fantastic article</a> that elaborates on the Arabic word <em>Al-muthanna</em>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Al-muthanna refers to a relation between two people that becomes very important in the lives of both, and yet has a life of its own – almost like a common baby. It is neither a legal relation nor intellectual nor economic nor social… it develops in a free and natural way between the two. It is neither a couple nor dual – although the latter is usually used to refer to it. Al-muthanna does not perceive the other as non-I or as a person that is a copy of I, and it is not a higher synthesis/ unity of the two. Each person remains who s/he is but a relation starts developing between the two, a relation that becomes so important in both persons’ lives that neither can live any longer as if it is not there.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This distinction offers new ways of seeing outside of Descartes’ infuriatingly cognitive maxim “<em>I think</em> therefore I am,” and opens up a new existential possibility: “<em>You are</em>, therefore I am.” To see al-muthanna is to shift from disembodied mental isolation to a fully relational way of being, one that is not linguistically distinguishable in the English language<sup id="fnref:3" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>. This isn’t to say the experience of it doesn't exist for English speakers — we probably felt it acutely in our early years. But it is not an experience that has been valued or prioritized in Western cultures that place such a high value on the individual.</p>

<p>Now that I have a word, now that the experience of al-muthanna has been distinguished, I can observe the relationships in my life in new ways.  What does it mean to tend not just to a relationship, but the al-muthanna as well? When I exist because you are, what is now possible that wasn't before? My own explorations of that question have already led to several insights, but rather than get into them here I'll leave you to explore on your own.</p>

<p>To start getting a sense of distinctions and how they work in your life, I’ll leave you with a few reflection questions:</p>

<ul>
  <li>How much am I able to observe with my current distinctions?</li>
  <li>What can I tell about the observational capacity of others based on the distinctions they are using?</li>
  <li>What might I not be observing because I lack distinctions?</li>
  <li>How might I go about learning new distinctions?</li>
  <li>What possibilities become available to me once I have integrated those new distinctions?</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Werner Erhard, Mastery in Living: What it Takes <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Not to mention how heavily noun-based the English language is. But that's for another newsletter. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>The closest English equivalent I can think of is Kurt Lewin's concept of “the field”. I don't think Martin Buber's “I-thou” bears much similarity to al-muthanna. <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Essay] The active process of meaning making.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/listening/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/listening/</guid>
				<pubDate>Thu, 22 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<blockquote>
  <p>Listening is the process by which we make meaning of the world and determine what is real for us." — Alan Sieler</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>How do I know what I think until I see what I say?" — E.M. Forster</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Listening and languaging arise together; languaging creates the world and listening makes meaning of it. Listening is not a passive process of receiving objective information but an active process of meaning making, and this meaning making happens <em>in the observer</em>. Chalmers Brothers writes that “as observers, we ascribe meaning to events and people… meaning lives within The Observer, and is activated by people and events, and projected onto the world.”</p>

<p>Each of us, as an observer, perceives the world in our own unique way, and our speaking reveals these perceptions. And yet our speaking, as I’m sure we’ve all experienced, <em>doesn’t ensure listening</em>! Sometimes instead of engaging others with what we are saying, our words are met with indifference or hostility. We can say the same thing to five different people and get five different reactions! Which means each of us <em>listens</em> to the world in our own unique way, shaped by the  interpretations, mental models, and beliefs we hold. But these interpretations, mental models, and beliefs are invisible to us, like water to a fish. We do not listen to what people say so much as how that saying occurs for us. And understanding this is the key to being able to listen more fully and deeply.</p>

<h3 id="what-is-listening">What is Listening?</h3>
<blockquote>
  <p>“We then say that listening is linguistic, it lives in language. Listening is active interpretation, active internal storytelling to myself. Listening is definitely not passively receiving objective information, but instead has everything to do with building a story, building a narrative, creating an interpretation about what was said or done. Listening is where meaning gets generated, and meaning matters.” — Chalmers Brothers</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In <a href="/writing/essays/living-in-language/">a previous essay</a> I wrote that “the act of languaging consists of observing and speaking, and recursively being changed by what we say on what we see.” Listening is the way in which we are recursively changed by what we language. Listening is observation<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, a kind of observation that doesn't happen just with our ears and eyes, but with our entire body. Our nervous system, the brain's mirror neurons, and our other senses are all part of how we listen.</p>

<p>Our body, as an instrument of observation, is how we attune to one another. Lisbeth Lipari calls this “interlistening” and writes that “listening itself is a form of speaking that resonates with echoes of everything we have ever heard, thought, seen, touched, said, and read throughout our lives.”</p>

<p>These echoes include our interpretations, mental models, and beliefs about the world. Until we become aware of these echoes, they will obscure our ability to fully attune to each other. Effective listening requires presence, openness, and the ability to notice and relax habitual ways of seeing and responding to the world. We have to do the work to quiet these echoes so that we can truly listen.</p>

<h3 id="a-few-thoughts-on-active-listening">A Few Thoughts on Active Listening</h3>
<p>The idea of that meaning exists within the observer and that we listen from echoes of everything that we have experienced in our lives is missing from contemporary frameworks used to teach listening skills. Let’s take Active Listening, one of the most poplar listening frameworks, as an example. The three primary components of Active Listening are: cognitive, emotional, and behavioral.</p>

<p>The cognitive element is about paying attention to both the verbal and non-verbal information we receive. But as we've already discussed, there is no such thing as “receiving information” as if we were machines taking in a direct, lossless transmission. What we receive is filtered through our own Way of Being, the postures and attitudes we hold about the world and about the person we are listening to.</p>

<p>The emotional piece is pretty much about emotional intelligence — being aware of and managing emotional responses that listening can evoke. I appreciate that emotions are included in Active Listening but without the concept of the observer, emotions will be managed rather than understood. Emotions arise in relationship to the interpretations we hold about the world. What kind of observer are we being that our listening provokes x or y emotion?</p>

<p>And finally, the behavioral aspect is about showing attentiveness and interest both verbally and nonverbally. Nodding, sharing small interjections like, “uh huh,” or ”I see” or whatever indicates interest. This one I find gimmicky and performative and would prefer it to be left out of listening practices entirely. Michael Bungay Steiner pokes fun at this in the intro to his TEDx talk, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Kl0rmx7aa0w">How to Tame Your Advice Monster</a>.</p>

<p>For me it feels like Active Listening was built on the transmission model of communication. Developed in the 60s and 70s by engineers working on the challenge of sending and receiving messages electronically, the model posits that what is said and what is received is exactly the same (e.g. the same content will result in the same meaning across all listeners). But of course, humans are not machines but complex, interconnected biological organisms and the act of hearing does not guarantee what is listened to or the meaning made. This is why its so important  that any theory of listening also include an acknowledgement of who we are as observers and how we live in language, uniquely creating our perceptions of the world.</p>

<p>And because Active Listening misses the idea of observers altogether, it can’t get at what closes us off from listening. It’s not about making sure we hear the words and nod our head, it’s about being aware of the ways we become trapped in our own beliefs and then doing the work to loosen their grip and set them aside. Alan Sieler writes that “…we are so attached to our own assumptions and assessments we weave a spell around ourselves, and we do an excellent job in limiting what we can learn from others. We close off the possibility that someone else could have something to say and contribute which could add to our listening.”</p>

<h3 id="what-matters-most-to-us">What Matters Most to Us</h3>
<blockquote>
  <p>“A key element of the linguistic and emotional structure of humans is meaning. We can think of this structure as an interlocking set of concerns and interpretations. When we relate with others, we relate to their meaning—their concerns and interpretations. In our relationships and dealing with each other, our interpretations will continually be triggered. We will always be making our meaning of the words and non-verbal gestures of others.” — Alan Sieler</p>
</blockquote>

<p>We’ve been circling around this idea of meaning, that meaning making happens in the observer and not the speaker. The speaker, of course, is also an observer. As we open our observational capacity by quieting our assumptions and assessments we create the space to attend not only to our own meaning making, but to the meaning making being revealed by another. We attune to what matters most to them, the concerns they are speaking to, and what they care about. We listen as an observer and honor their observer, acknowledging and legitimizing the differences between us. <em>This</em> is the essence of listening.</p>

<p>When we listen to the observer in another, while remaining aware of our own process of observation, we deepen the capacity to listen from and to difference. We can acknowledge what feels true for us, what feels true for another, and accept that each perspective is legitimate. This kind of listening builds trust, fosters respect, and allows each person to be in their own integrity. This isn’t listening to make wrong or to respond, but rather listening to understand.</p>

<p>The ability to listen in this way requires the entire body. We need to be able to sense and accept these differences emotionally, somatically, and linguistically. Sieler offers insight here once again writing, “the way we hold ourselves, in posture and muscle tension, will reflect the degree to which we are linguistically and emotionally open to another.”</p>

<p>Listening at this level opens us to relational attunement, rather than transactional communication. And when relational attunement is at the center of listening true growth and development begins to unfold. As Martin Buber writes, “we can only grow and develop once we have learned to live in relation with others.” This is the kind of listening that coaching inhabits—listening in a way that legitimizes another, that increases our understanding of another, and that creates a genuine human relationship. This listening widens the space of possibility so that growth and development can occur. Sieler again:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Listening is at the heart of the issue of mutual respect and mutual legitimacy. We have a fundamental stance of openness in our listening when we hold the person as a “legitimate other”, which means a person of equal validity, not better and not worse. <em>Holding another as a legitimate other is a Way of Being—it occurs in language, emotions, and our body.</em>”</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="how-we-listen">How We Listen</h3>

<p>To change how we listen and respond, we have to change our interpretations. And in order for that to happen, we have to become aware of them. I’ll close out this issue by sharing a few reflection prompts from Alan Sieler that I've found useful to developing awareness of myself as an observer and who I am as a listener.</p>

<ul>
  <li>What’s going on with me?</li>
  <li>How am I listening right now?</li>
  <li>What am I listening to?</li>
  <li>Where am I listening from?</li>
  <li>How might my prejudices be interfering with my listening?</li>
  <li>How could I shift my body to listen differently?</li>
  <li>Am I holding the the person I am listening to as a legitimate other?</li>
</ul>

<p>Happy (inter)listening,</p>

<p>Andi</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="resources">Resources</h3>
<ul class="extra-bottom-margin">
  <li><a href="https://www.ontologicalcoaching.co.za/wp-content/uploads/2019/10/CHS-Vol-I-promo.pdf">Coaching to the Human Soul: Ontological Coaching and Deep Change Volume 1</a>, Alan Sieler.</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.thriftbooks.com/w/language-and-the-pursuit-of-happiness_chalmers-brothers/389416/?srsltid=AfmBOoqD-oqw9W-EN3wthFIySBW6hLqF8lGdY7JsXxTGwkqVRLSCDhA-#edition=5472378&amp;idiq=7431385">Language and the Pursuit of Happiness: A New Foundation for Designing Your Life, Your Relationships, &amp; Your Results</a>, Chalmers Brothers.</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.psupress.org/books/titles/978-0-271-06332-4.html">Listening, Thinking, Being: Towards an Ethics of Attunement</a>, Lisbeth Lipari.</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.holybooks.com/wp-content/uploads/The-Ending-of-Time.pdf">The Ending of Time</a> - David Bohm and J. Krishnamurti.</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.maximusveritas.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/iandthou.pdf">I and Thou</a>, Martin Buber.</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h3 id="footnotes">Footnotes</h3>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Krishnamurti once wrote, “Pure observation, which is actually listening, is love.” <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Essay] Understanding the generative power of language.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/living-in-language/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/living-in-language/</guid>
				<pubDate>Sun, 04 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						
<p>What does it mean to live in language? Language is like the air we breathe. By the time we are adults we have been languaging for so many years that we hardly give it a second thought. From the moment we wake up to the time we go to bed, we language our existence. Now, if languaging were simply the act of describing the world then I wouldn’t be writing this newsletter. There would be no need to examine how languaging creates our experience because as a descriptive tool language holds no generative power. But on closer inspection language turns out to be exactly that—creative and generative. And when leaders and coaches begin to catch onto this, everything changes.</p>

<p>So! Languaging. You may be alarmed by how I am using the word language here (as a verb!) but I assure you this is intentional. The verbing of language comes from the work of <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1EPmMiaNKjf4LKIVnNw7dmIMh26Ske404/view?usp=share\_link">Humberto Maturana</a>, a Chilean biologist who noted that “anything said is said by an observer.” This feels obvious, but the implications are important.</p>

<p>Each of us, as an observer, perceives the world in our own unique way. Not only because of how we were shaped through our upbringing, experiences, and culture but also because of our biological structure. Seeing doesn’t happen through our eyes alone, it happens through our nervous system, emotional state, and cognitive awareness. I take the infamous quote attributed to Anaïs Nin, “We see the world not as it is, but as we are,” not as a statement about our character, but about our biology. How the world occurs to us is created through our thoughts, emotions, body, <em>and</em> language. This is what Maturana is pointing to when he uses language as a verb. The act of languaging consists of observing <em>and</em> speaking, and recursively being changed by what we say on what we see.</p>

<p>It is precisely this uniqueness, this difference between observers that gives us a clue that language cannot just describe the world as it is. If we are each unique observers then we each have a legitimate claim on what is “real”. But if that's the case, how can we ever make sense of things? One answer to that question can be found just by looking around or reading a history book—the world-generating capacity of language is attributed to a privileged few who were born with and/or have accumulated the right signifiers that their view of things is considered the “right” one (just bring to mind any manager you’ve had who, because of their positional power felt they were always right, and you’ll get a sense of what I mean).</p>

<p>This also happens when we talk to ourselves. Let’s zoom in (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0fKBhvDjuy0">Eames Power of 10 style</a>) to our inner critic. The inner critic is a particular kind of observer, one that occupies a negative view of our capabilities and effectiveness. Inhabiting a pervasive mood of dissatisfaction and frustration, the inner critic can only observe (and incessantly tell us) the thousand million ways we are falling short of expectations. And as part of our own observational facility, the inner critic, who we often mistake as ourselves, influences how we observe the world and what we say about it, thereby generating our reality through language.</p>

<p>If our inner critic is super active and we are beating ourselves up for not being more productive, efficient, smarter, better, prettier, wealthier, name-your-flavor-of-criticism, that will absolutely influence our observations of ourselves, what is happening around us, and the potential actions we can take. We will pay more attention to data that confirms the beliefs of the inner critic and discard evidence to the contrary. And this loop, this reflexive interaction of observation and language, creates our reality. Through languaging we have become lazy, stupid, worthless, and pathetic which, I have to point out, is not an objective, descriptive statement about who we are but the generative power of language to create who we mistake ourselves to be.</p>

<p>As observers we all language our existence in unique ways. What happens when we speak is that we reveal how the world appears to us. We highlight what matters, the beliefs that we hold to be true, what we think is worth paying attention to and what isn't, what we hope for, and what we want to avoid. Language shows who we are and how we participate in creating the world.</p>

<p>This is what I mean by “living in language”. Language is such a part of our material reality that we rarely stop to reflect on it, to understand the role it plays in creating our experience. We take language to be descriptive or a way of transmitting information, which it is some of the time, but our big mistake has been the assumption that this is all language does.</p>

<p>Over the coming weeks I’d like to invite you to pay attention to how you use language. Listen to your inner dialogue and see what you can learn about who you are as an observer and how you language the world. And listen to the conversations you have with others and see if you can sense into what language reveals about each person and the kind of observer they are.</p>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Essay] On structure, permission, and creative evolution.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/seasons/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/seasons/</guid>
				<pubDate>Sun, 07 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<p><em>This essay, originally written for my newsletter Words Make Worlds, reflects on the experience of posting at a regular cadence as I struggled to figure out how find an approach that worked for me. I am keeping it published in my ‘essays’ collection in hopes it might be useful for others struggling with similar questions.</em></p>

<p>A few folks have asked me what happened to the newsletter and I’m writing to let you know it’s still here! By way of explanation, I was in Argentina for a month and gave myself permission to step out of the newsletter cycle which allowed me to realize two things. One, that what I had written so far felt complete. And two, the newsletter itself is nowhere close to done. Complete in that the first 15 issues largely focused on some of the foundational elements and there isn’t much more I want to say about that (for now). And nowhere close to done because there so much more I want to say about coaching.</p>

<p>It took permission and time away to see this. And to understand that the sticky wicket of disconnect between <em>complete</em> and <em>done</em> lay in the structure of the newsletter itself. The structure was the last thing I questioned after weeks of doubting myself and my abilities as a newsletter writer. It was the structure that got in the way of being able to listen closely to what the essence of Words Make Worlds wanted to be <em>as a living creation</em>, beyond what I thought it <em>should</em> be as a <em>thing</em>.</p>

<p>I have learned a lot about structure and permission. I have learned that structure is important but it has to be held lightly enough to become part of the creative process. And I have learned that we <em>have</em> to give ourselves permission to not fully know what something is, to open to mystery and to be in conversation with our creations, to let them evolve and change while allowing ourselves to be simultaneously changed in the process.</p>

<p>In hindsight I realize almost everything I have read about newsletters comes from the world of marketing where structure, consistency, and automation reign. Where creating a content machine is how the marketing engine works.</p>

<p>But I am not a machine, despite an obsession with cyborgs in my early twenties. I am a messy, joyful, creative, curious human. And what I make—newsletters, courses, essays, collages, poems—are equally messy, joyful, creative, and curious. These things have a life within them that wants to be expressed. And I have to be able to listen to that life, to be in conversation with it, so it continues to grow. If I can't listen, if my ideas of what something <em>should</em> be take over, then that life is extinguished and the creative energy disappears.</p>

<p>In a more pragmatic way, Donald Schön sees this conversation as an essential part of making, whatever the materials may be. <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Educating-Reflective-Practitioner-Teaching-Professions/dp/1555422209">He writes</a>,</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Out of musical materials or themes of talk, they make a piece of music or a conversation, an artifact with its own meaning and coherence. Their reflection-in-action is a reflective conversation with the materials of a situation.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Those of us from the world of software may look at this and draw parallels with the product development cycle, but this is a mistake. For Schön, the reflective conversation requires the ability to “listen” to the surprises that reveal “new moves that give new meanings and directions to the development of an artifact.” Product development, on the other hand, is an iterative, repeatable process of delivering something that is feasible, usable, and desirable. If there is any conversation to be had, it is not with the materials of a conversation but with the profit logic that mediates between the business and the market.</p>

<p>The goal of a firm is to make and retain a customer. To create and capture value. This is the profit logic that drives the product development cycle and all other processes within a firm. Once a company finds product-market fit, the business model snaps into place ensuring value is continuously captured. There isn’t room to listen to what a product might want to become because the product was born of the market and will always serve in this capacity.</p>

<p>Compare that to what <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Creativity-Routledge-Classics-75/dp/0415336406">David Bohm believes drives composers, architects, and scientists</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The artist, the musical composer, the architect, the scientist all feel a fundamental need to discover and create something new that is whole and total, harmonious and beautiful. Few ever get a chance to try to do this, and even fewer actually manage to do it. Yet, deep down, it is probably what very large numbers of people in all walks of life are seeking when the attempt to escape the daily humdrum routine by engaging in every kind of entertainment, excitement, stimulation, change of occupation, and so forth, through which they ineffectively try to compensate for the unsatisfying narrowness and mechanicalness of their lives.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It is this narrowness and mechanicalness that mature firms seem to embody and require of their employees, and that the product development cycle serves. Now I'm not claiming that this newsletter is whole, total, harmonious, or beautiful (I have aspirations!), but it certainly took on narrowness and mechanicalness when I followed the <em>shoulds</em>.</p>

<p>You may have noticed that <em>should</em> has made an appearance a couple times already. I have learned that these <em>shoulds</em> are important. Listen for them. <em>Should</em> is a sign that mechanicalness is creeping in, that the oxygen is dwindling and the fire of creation is getting weak. That a narrowness is preventing the ability listen to the faint beckonings of wholeness and beauty. Letting go of <em>shoulds</em> is a compassionate act of permission—to not fully know what a creation is and to allow ourselves to be in conversation with it so we can grow and evolve together.</p>

<hr class="section-break" />

<p>The structure that got me into trouble—Idea + Practice—comes from my strong belief in experiential learning. That ideas themselves aren’t enough, we have to put them into practice, to live them, so that we can come closer to an embodied understanding of what it means to coach. Like many things, you learn to coach by coaching, not by reading about coaching. And so I thought every issue of Words Make Worlds <em>should</em> (there we go again!) exemplify this approach.</p>

<p>But this structure turned out to be unforgiving.  I couldn’t see it at first, instead telling myself I was a bad newsletter writer because I wasn’t hitting the mechanical markers of success I thought I <em>should</em> (ahem). It wasn’t until I gave myself permission that I began to see how structure was getting in the way of creative and meaningful work.</p>

<p>Leader as Coach has offered similar lessons in permission. In the last year and half, eight cohorts have completed the program. And each offering has been different, based what I learned in conversation with both the students <em>and</em> the offering itself. I mean look, my first attempt at designing the course was BIG—I dreamed up a 12 week program that went deep into the world of coaching. Full blast, everything and the kitchen sink. No chance of listening because I knew exactly what it <em>should</em> (again!) be. Maven, the platform that I run the program through, was like “So hey we've seen this a lot and our suggestion is to start small and go from there—like, a one week program.”</p>

<p>12 weeks became one. I got clear on the essence of what I wanted to share and ran that version three times, listening closely as I went. By the third cohort it felt like there was a <em>there</em> there, that I could feel the life of the course, and the next step was to expand into a six week offering.</p>

<p>I was in the middle of the second six week cohort when storms knocked out my internet 30 minutes before class. I hauled ass to a nearby coffee shop where I ran into everyone else in my neighborhood, and in short order we brought down the cafe's wifi.</p>

<p>I couldn’t hold class and had to push everything back a week. I was mortified and upset—the weekly cadence was important! Turns out everyone loved the break because it allowed folks to get in extra practice time. And so Leader as Coach turned into a seven week course, with a break in the middle.</p>

<p>I share this anecdote because, again, <em>permission</em>. Letting ourselves off the hook for needing to have everything figured out at launch. Listening for the surprises and letting them inform what something becomes, not just what we think it <em>should</em> be.</p>

<hr class="section-break" />

<p>The idea of being in conversation with something is increasingly important for me and my work. This newsletter, Leader as Coach, and just about everything else I do is an offering that comes from my heart. This world is chaotic, complex, crazy, and at times terrifying. But despite this, or maybe because of it, we have an opportunity to amplify goodness, love, and care. To reorient ourselves away from the world of things and ground ourselves in a world of relationality and reciprocity. We are not isolated, individual, and alone. We are connected and interdependent. To steal a phrase from <a href="#">Carlo Rovelli</a>, we are “networks of kisses, not of stones.”</p>

<p>Coaching teaches us how to remember this. How to prioritize and be in relationship with others. How to know and see the world primarily as one of co-created realities and to tend to that co-creation intentionally. As <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Seduction-Minotaur-Authoritative-Anais-Nin-ebook/dp/B003H9LJWO/ref=sr_1_1?crid=23DFD9X44OSGK&amp;dib=eyJ2IjoiMSJ9.KsKsYbKzDxpXb7fetc2RvAantQM3KgufydooE5GIORZiYEQi4QRudhyDftHMaPMr68_ggXwdO59pi0oEd43Dxlq3rZD_ZmE3d2i6qiDT71Iomdo5Elnn2O3RULW4GPCCss164rFlOw9eZhOXIzlUGiHQeibg26ETJwYSbayfGsx2Z-fxBetWTrxBl-w72g0SkeCOo2JD-Z_FRD2tNfd6LzmXUt9Yf-1m_y1HeQA7ZNunS1VhTysaRScgJtabCHECb8BRhLIw_ioh5OHK4XGaPwo9Mp3pL-JrdFX1vqQxIlo.n9ybpoKedTQ7lhUm0C2AnKb5SUnfwg2H9Z9db3EIW_0&amp;dib_tag=se&amp;keywords=seduction+of+the+minotaur&amp;qid=1720296681&amp;sprefix=seduction+of+the+mi%2Caps%2C169&amp;sr=8-1">Anaïs Nin</a> astutely observed, “we don't see things as they are, we see them as we are,” and coaching is the way we can see that process in action. When we begin to clue in that the world isn't “just so”, that we are active participants in its creation, things begin to shift and new possibilities emerge. And all of this against the backdrop of work!</p>

<p>This has always been the remarkable part for me. That work can be place of deep personal and communal transformation. There is so much energy caught up in defending our default ways of being. Coaching brings awareness to these patterns of behavior, an awareness that brings release, and when this happens that trapped energy becomes available for true creation and collaboration.</p>

<p>Coaching not only supports others, but the coach as well, and I think this is where the true magic happens. To be a coach, or to inhabit a coaching posture, is to be curious, present, and aware. Of ourselves, of others, of the situation, of the environment. A coaching orientation invites us to hold our perceptions lightly, to name what we are seeing and feeling, and to wonder about what we might be missing that others can add. And to do that in conversation, in relationship, so that we can begin to get a greater sense of the emergent and evolving situation.</p>

<p>Coaching isn’t just a skillset, but a way of leading and of living life.</p>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Essay] The intentional use of self in coaching.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/presence/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/presence/</guid>
				<pubDate>Sun, 03 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<blockquote>
  <p>As coaches or leaders, we can think of presence as a being intervention: simply "showing up" has an evocative effect, the first indication of whether or how people will work with us. Though we may not be able to predict how our presence will affect others, we are responsible for the self-work of reflection and asking to learn what we evoke in others." — Dorothy E. Siminovitch</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In “<em><a href="https://maraineyassociates.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/UseofSelf-Presence.pdf">Use of Self in OD Consulting: What Matters is Presence</a></em>” Tolbert and Hanafin describe presence as representing “the translation of personal appearance, manner, values, knowledge, reputation, and other characteristics into interest and impact. Presence is not manufactured. Everyone possesses presence, regardless of the level of awareness of the impact of that presence. Presence is the use of self with intent.”</p>

<p>If I could summarize in a pithy way what the coaching approach is all about I'd say something along the lines of “Do less, <em>be</em> more.” This is hard for managers—business requires a lot of doing and you don't make your way up the career ladder by sitting around staring at the clouds<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. Of course, we’re not doing that in coaching either but the idea of <em>being</em> is fairly elusive, let alone the idea that <em>being</em> can have a positive impact, business or otherwise.</p>

<p>With <a href="https://maven.com/andrea-mignolo/leader-as-coach">Leader as Coach</a>, presence and <a href="/writing/essays/the-loop-of-awareness">awareness</a> are the first coaching tools I introduce to students. They are the foundations on which everything else is built. Think about the last time someone was fully present and attentive to you, when you felt really seen and heard by another. What was that like? How did it impact you? How did you feel?</p>

<p>In today’s busy, fast-paced, multi-tasking society, the moments in which we are fully present with each other are few and far between. But when these moments do happen—when the past and future fall away and we open to the moment and the people we are with—something shifts. When we feel held in the attentiveness of awareness a kind of <em>completion</em> starts to happen. What we have been holding on to, once witnessed, is ready to be released and energy becomes available for something new. I know this sounds a bit woo woo, but stay with me.</p>

<p>Presence is a precursor to <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/curiosity">curiosity</a>. Presence loosens the constricting grip of control and gives us access to a wide range of information beyond the content of what someone is sharing with us—body language, tone, energy, words left unsaid. When we are present we can receive others more fully, letting go of our own projections and holding patterns in order to build trust and safety in the relationship. We stay anchored and focused, less hooked by distractions and tangents like ruminating on the past or worrying about the future.</p>

<p>Presence welcomes everything, and by welcoming everything coaches become more open to the reality of another without judgement or interpretation. What is the world like for them right now? What has them seeing things in this way? What  might unlock a new way of relating? What core values, unconscious beliefs, and unmet needs are contributing to how they experience themselves?</p>

<p>Most coaching methodologies integrate the idea of presence in one shape or another—it’s actually one of the <a href="https://coachingfederation.org/app/uploads/2021/03/ICF-Core-Competencies-updated.pdf">core competencies of coaching</a> as defined by the International Coaching Federation: #5 - Maintains Presence. The ICF expects coaches to:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Remain focused, observant, empathetic and responsive to the client</li>
  <li>Demonstrate curiosity during the coaching process</li>
  <li>Manage one’s emotions and to stay present with the client</li>
  <li>Demonstrate confidence in working with strong client emotions during the coaching process</li>
  <li>Be comfortable working in a space of not knowing</li>
  <li>Create or allow space for silence, pause or reflection</li>
</ol>

<p>The world of Gestalt outlines the skills and abilities of presence even further. Coaches who effectively embody presence are able to:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Tolerate confusion and ambiguity without rushing to organize it, allowing something to emerge naturally rather than forcing it.</li>
  <li>Separate data from interpretation and emphasize nonjudgmental observations. The closer to actual data, the less distortion of the client's experience.</li>
  <li>State things succinctly, clearly, and directly.</li>
  <li>Attend, observe, and selectively share observations of what is seen, heard, felt, and so forth.</li>
  <li>Attend to one’s own experience of feelings, sensations, and thoughts, and selectively share them.</li>
  <li>Be aware of one’s intentions at any moment; be clear about the priorities of the work.</li>
  <li>Focus on what is most interesting to The Thinker; be aware of the emergence or lack of emergence of themes for which there is excitement</li>
  <li>Make good connections with others and help others do the same; model clear and permeable boundaries, influence dialogue, and let go of being in control.</li>
  <li>State observations in a way that can be heard and considered.</li>
  <li>Use the client's language to heighten the capacity to be heard; using metaphors to paint a verbal picture.</li>
  <li>Stay in the power of the here-and-now and focusing on the ongoing process.</li>
  <li>Appreciate the quality of good breathing and body centering to support self and other.</li>
</ul>

<p>Strong presence has an impact on what we say, how we say it, and how we impact others. I share all of these skills and competencies as a way to illustrate that entire professional bodies of practice dedicated to change and transformation take the capacity for presence very seriously. It is not woo woo at all.</p>

<p>In <a href="https://bookshop.org/p/books/simplifying-coaching-how-to-have-more-transformational-conversations-by-doing-less-claire-pedrick/15769790?ean=9780335249077"><em>Simplifying Coaching</em></a>, Claire Pedrick reports that, “Marianne Woerkom interviewed managers who were coaches in the same organisation. The thinkers ‘attributed the effectiveness of their coaching to a large part to the relationship they had with their coach. Receiving unconditional acceptance and respect from the coach was not only a facilitative condition, but also directly responsible for change.’”</p>

<p><em>Presence facilitates change.</em> And through presence we can inhabit a state of unconditional acceptance and respect. An important nuance here—acceptance is about acknowledging the exact place someone is before supporting any kind of change. As Carl Rogers said, “The curious paradox is that when I accept myself just as I am, then I can change.” When your presence as a coach invites this level acceptance in one of your direct reports, they can see themselves more clearly and mobilize the energy required for true and lasting change. I <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/writing/guides/building-a-relationship-with-change/">wrote an article about this</a> if you are curious to go deeper on the paradoxical theory of change:</p>

<h3 id="cultivating-presence">Cultivating Presence</h3>
<blockquote>
  <p>"Cultivating presence requires a commitment to lifelong learning and development." - Mary Ann Rainey Tolbert and Jonno Hanafin</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Cultivating presence is something we can do for the rest of our lives—there is no end to how present we can become. Given the long term possibilities for presence, I like to reference Tolbert and Hanafin's Six Elements of Cultivating Presence model to stay focused on the primary domains through which we can work with presence.</p>

<p class="caption"><img src="/images/wmw/six-elements-of-presence.png" alt="The Six Elements of Cultivating Presence" />
The Six Elements of Cultivating Presence, created by Mary Ann Rainey Tolbert and Jonno Hanafin</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Continuing to work on unresolved issues and unfinished business.</strong> If we don’t do our own work then we’ll bring our own limiting beliefs, conditioned tendencies, and reactive patterns to coaching conversations. If we want to support others in accessing their full potential, we also have to spend time learning what gets in the way of doing this for ourselves.</li>
  <li><strong>Committing time and energy to active reflection.</strong> Reflection is one of the primary ways we learn from experience. When we take the extra to reflect on our experience we generate new meaning that allows us to take new action.</li>
  <li><strong>Actively seek feedback from colleagues, direct reports, and friends.</strong> To understand the impact our presence has on others, we have to ask them! What do we evoke in others when we work with them?</li>
  <li><strong>Live life fully.</strong> If we only have one type of experience then our learning will be limited. To deepen our capacity for presence it is necessary to have a wide range of experiences to draw from. Personal development is professional development.</li>
  <li><strong>Investing in a broad worldview.</strong> Traveling, building relationships with a wide range of people, exploring new countries and cultures increases our capacity to connect with and understand others.</li>
  <li><strong>Experimenting with new ways of being.</strong> A way of being is about how we think, behave, and approach life cognitively, emotionally, and somatically. Most of us never wake up to our default way of being, but with some reflection and experimentation we can start to see the edges of this way of being, and begin to explore new ones.</li>
</ol>

<p>If it feels in alignment, spend some time reflecting and journaling around your own approach and experience in each of these areas. On a scale of 0-10, where would you rate yourself today? And what would it take to rate yourself one number higher?</p>

<h2 id="the-practice">The Practice</h2>
<p>As you head into your week, identify one conversation  where you will consciously practice being fully present. This could be a 1-on-1 meeting with a direct report, a team meeting, or even a chat with someone at the grocery store.</p>

<p>Before entering the conversation, take a few deep centering breaths and set the intention to be attentive and engaged without multi-tasking or mentally moving ahead to what you’ll say next. Listen with <a href="/writing/essays/soft-eyes">soft eyes</a>, be <a href="/writing/essays/curiosity">curious</a>, <a href="/writing/essays/the-loop-of-awareness">loop your awareness</a>, and let go of stories you've previously told yourself about this person.</p>

<p>Afterward, reflect on how it felt to anchor yourself in presence. Did you gain any new insights that may have been missed otherwise? Did the quality of connection shift at all? See if you can begin incorporating small presence experiments like this into your regular leadership practice. Who knows what unexpected wonders may unfold by simply showing up and giving someone your full attention.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="quotes-i-">Quotes I ❤️</h2>
<blockquote>
  <p>When you coach as a thinking partner instead of an expert, your job is to catch and return what you are given by the client. You don't have to concoct a masterful question. You don't need to figure out if what you want to say is intuition or a blatant projection of your own needs. You don't have to have all the answers. You are a good coach if you share what you hear and see and maybe offer what you sense is happening with no attachment to being right. — Marcia Reynolds</p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Don't get me wrong, staring at the clouds, or a wall, or the ceiling is actually a wonderful activity and I do a fair amount of it myself. And sometimes I recommend it to clients. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Essay] A way of looking with wide open awareness.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/soft-eyes/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/soft-eyes/</guid>
				<pubDate>Mon, 05 Feb 2024 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<p>Beyond methodologies and frameworks, good coaching is fundamentally a shift in how we show up and step into relationship with others—a shift that enables a collaborative and co-creative partnership between the coach and the person being coached.</p>

<p>What do I mean by this? By way of example, my first professional coaching program was the year long <a href="https://www.newventureswest.com/program/professional-coaching-course/">Integral Coaching Certification</a> with New Ventures West. For the first <em>four months</em> of the program students work on developing the body of a coach, which includes daily meditation, reflective practices, and exercise alongside a custom designed year-long development program to deepen each person’s ability to show up in life with more presence, capacity, and awareness. There is no discussion of coaching methodology or what it means to be in a coaching conversation until significant time has been spent on developing these new ways of being.</p>

<p>Kung-fu has a parallel approach (or at least it used to). According to my <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@sifudunng7117">Sifu</a>, back in the day students of Kung Fu were required to spend a full year practicing <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Horse_stance">Sei Ping Ma</a>—the foundational stance of southern-style Kung Fu— before being able to progress to things like hand strikes, blocks, and kicks, let alone forms. In today’s world of instant gratification and participation trophies that business model is no longer viable, but the story emphasizes the importance of all the things that are essential to becoming proficient at an art that at first glance don't look like practicing the art itself.</p>

<p>Hopefully these two examples help paint a clearer picture of what I mean by “a shift in how we show up.” As with learning any new art form, coaching asks us to practice foundational elements that change how we see, understand, and move in the world, to practice in such a way that our body transforms into a unique expression of the art itself. As we integrate these foundational elements into our conversations we more naturally inhabit the posture that coaching requires to build a true co-creative partnership.</p>

<p>When it comes to the non-methodology side of things, we’ve covered this a little in the <a href="/writing/essays/optimism">Curiosity</a>, <a href="/writing/essays/optimism">Optimism</a>, and <a href="/writing/essays/the-loop-of-awareness">Awareness</a> issues, and I plan to spend the next several weeks talking more about all the things that are not “coaching” that make coaching effective.</p>

<p>To that end, today I want to talk about the idea of “soft eyes”. This is one of those techniques that is great not just for coaching but for just about <em>everything</em> in life. I’ve found folks in the fields of horseback riding, journalism, martial arts, detective work, art therapy, and coaching all talking about the powerful practice of soft eyes.</p>

<h2 id="the-idea">The Idea</h2>
<blockquote>
  <p>“If you got soft eyes, you can see the whole thing. If you got hard eyes–you staring at the same tree missing the forest.” - Detective Bunk, The Wire</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Soft eyes is a way of looking at the world with wide open awareness. This awareness is attuned both to the world around us, as well as the world inside of us. An awareness that can simultaneously keep us connected to ourselves as well as others. Soft eyes gives us access to the widest amount of information possible—the act of softening our eyes transforms our entire body into an instrument of receiving. So while soft eyes has a direct link to vision, it is also connected to all the ways in which we sense and understand the world.</p>

<p>Hard eyes, on the other hand, is a narrow and intense awareness. Hard eyes picks out one thing and locks in on it. In societies where we are taught to make eye contact and that its rude to look away, hard eyes tends to be the more dominant way of looking at the world. Years ago I had a coaching supervisor who, after watching one of my sessions, noted that my gaze was <em>very</em> intense. “Well of course it is!” I thought. “I wanted to give my client all of my attention.” But the intense focus of hard eyes puts us at a disadvantage because we lose access to critical information available outside the line of focus, and that “outside” is where the good stuff comes from in coaching conversations.</p>

<p>Interestingly, <a href="https://kahneman.scholar.princeton.edu/sites/g/files/toruqf3831/files/kahneman/files/attention_lo_quality.pdf">when we focus intensely on something</a>—be it another person or a difficult work challenge, our pupils dilate, our breathing becomes more shallow, and the muscles in the face harden. Which is very similar to what happens in the fight/flight response kicks in, releasing hormones and neurotransmitters into the bloodstream to prepare the body for action. The fight/flight response includes some of the same physiological responses as intense concentration—dilated pupils, shallow breathing, and tightened muscles. Studies have shown that in this activated state it is actually harder to see faces, pick-up on facial cues, and empathy also becomes less accessible. So there are very real biological changes that impact what and how we are able to see. The paradox of focused attention is that over-focus leads to disconnection rather than connection!</p>

<p>Soft eyes is kind of an antidote to being at the edge of fight or flight. Soft eyes keeps our nervous system more grounded, which makes it easier to respond from a place of awareness when the unexpected comes into view, both literally and metaphorically. Reg Harris writes, “In an interview with New Dimensions Radio, psychologist Carol Pearson says we need to navigate our journeys with ‘soft eyes.’ According to Pearson, seeing with soft eyes means maintaining the focus needed to pursue our goals while, at the same time, keeping our vision open for other possibilities that may be available to us. Pearson calls this perspective ‘seeing the periphery’ of our lives. It's on the periphery that we might find other, unanticipated options or opportunities that could help us reach our goal more quickly or that might present a different, more fulfilling purpose.”</p>

<h2 id="the-practice">The Practice</h2>
<blockquote>
  <p>With soft eyes, you let your eyes physically relax. Instead of focusing on one thing, you allow that thing to be at the center of your gaze, while simultaneously taking in the largest possible expanse within your full field of vision. This includes peripheral vision both to the left and right, as well as above and below. By using soft eyes you increase your awareness of everything going on around you. - <a href="http://www.bluebirdlane.com/soft-eyes-tap-into-the-power-of-your-gaze.html">Lori Albrough</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>The practice instructions below are a modified version of the technique as described Sally Swift's book, <a href="https://bookshop.org/p/books/centered-riding-sally-swift/12202160?ean=9780312127343">Centered Riding (1985)</a>, who picked up the practice of soft eyes from both Aikido and the Alexander Technique.</p>

<ol>
  <li>While sitting quietly, focus very intently on one thing in your environment. Keep looking intently at the object. Concentrate on its exact outlines, its shape, density, color. Take everything in acutely. This is the practice of looking with hard eyes.</li>
  <li>Now relax your eyes. Let the object be the general center of your gaze, but look at it with your peripheral vision taking in the largest possible expanse, above and below as well as to the left and right. Be aware of the whole wide world. Sit comfortably with open eyes and have the feeling of going within yourself as your eyes encompass everything that comes into your field of vision. Remember that you are still aiming at the central object. This is the practice of looking with soft eyes.</li>
  <li>Try another experiment. While remaining where you are shift back and forth between hard eyes and soft eyes. Which way do you suppose is easier to build a trusting relationship in a coaching conversation? To get all the information you need from yourself, the other person, and the environment? You will quickly find that it is much easier to get this information when using soft eyes. The more area you encompass with your eyes, the more you'll be aware of everything including yourself. Be careful not to glaze or make your eyes fuzzy, just to soften the gaze and take in more of the world.</li>
</ol>

<p>Some useful imagery that can also support your practice of soft eyes is to keep the eyes open looking ahead, not glazed. Allow your eyes to become tools for awareness, and let your body feel like jelly, letting go of any hardness or tension that you may be experiencing.</p>

<p>Hopefully you are beginning to sense that soft eyes is much more than just a way of looking. Sally says that using soft eyes is like a new philosophy. It is a method of becoming acutely aware and sensitive to all life has to offer—both what is directly in your field of vision but also beyond what you can see with your eyes. You become aware of the whole, not just the parts. Soft eyes move the body into a receptive mode that can listen to the world on a very deep level.</p>

<p>Or to put it another way, as a former Reddit user once said, “Soft-eyes is a most elegant ‘life hack’.”</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="quotes-i-">Quotes I ❤️</h2>
<blockquote>
  <p>Whether as individuals, as companies or organizations, or as countries, our authentic power comes from our sense of connection with one another and the world around us. We find that connection when we see with soft eyes – when we engage with life from an open heart and mind, an awareness that everything is in some way connected to everything else, and a willingness to be present and work with whatever feelings arise. - <a href="https://transformationalpresence.org/alan-seale-blog/seeing-with-soft-eyes/">Alan Seale</a></p>
</blockquote>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Essay] The importance of clear endings in coaching conversations.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/ending-well/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/ending-well/</guid>
				<pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<blockquote>
  <p>To maintain a thinking space where transformation is possible, the end needs to be as much in partnership as the beginning. You co-created the space between you and have done the work together. Co-create the end. - Claire Pedrick</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In previous essays I’ve covered the full arc of the coaching conversation, from <a href="/writing/essays/beginning-together">beginning together</a> to <a href="/writing/essays/noticing-and-exploring">raising awareness</a> to <a href="/writing/essays/reflection-and-meaning-making">meaning making</a> to <a href="/writing/essays/taking-action">taking-new-action</a>. While the majority of your time will usually be spent in the “What?” phase of noticing and building awareness, how you start and how you end are critical components of impactful learning and clear commitments.</p>

<p>It can be easy to breeze past beginnings and endings, and in normal conversations we often do. From my work with students in the <a href="/leader-as-coach/">Leader as Coach</a> course, I’ve come to understand that it can feel redundant or awkward to start with intentional structure at the beginning of a conversation—the “flow” isn’t there which can feel unnatural. <em>And yet</em>, starting with clear intentions and a core set of questions that define the boundaries of the coaching container jumpstarts the thinking process for the person being coached. It helps them to identify what really matters and what change they want to see. It sets the parameters and purpose of the conversation. With a clearly defined container the coaching conversation can flow in a focused and supportive way.</p>

<p>The same goes for endings, where again it can feel awkward to bring structure to reflections and learnings. It can be easy to assume that just because both people experienced the same conversation they each have the same understanding and takeaways. <em>And yet</em>, what two people experience in the same conversation can be wildly different. Asking the person being coached to reflect on their experience, learning, insights, and commitments is a chance to create radical clarity and mutual understanding around what happened and what comes next.</p>

<p>The entire process of “What?—So what?—Now what?” takes place inside a container created by a good opening and concluded with a clear ending. A good opening sets the field of play and defines the learning objective, while a clear ending reinforces new insights and ensures the conversation is complete.</p>

<p>Good endings are also important because most of the learning happens outside the coaching conversation, where insights are applied through action. By ending the conversation with intention and structure you set the stage for what comes next, creating small steps to build forward momentum.</p>

<h2 id="the-practice">The Practice</h2>
<p>For endings I like to use Claire Pedrick's CALF framework. As you close out the conversation be sure to ask the following questions:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>C</strong>ontract: Make sure that the agreements you set at the beginning of the conversation have been met and that you have done what you set out to do. You can say something like, “Circling back to where we began, what is different now? How did we do?”</li>
  <li><strong>A</strong>ccountability: Coaching conversations are in service of the person being coached, and the accountability resides with them on what they will do next.  A simple, “Where do you need to be accountable?” may be enough. I also find that in a work environment where the manager needs to stay informed of progress, “What will you do by when, and how will you let me know?” can be effective.</li>
  <li><strong>L</strong>earning: Reflecting on the key learnings helps imprint them in memory and facilitates the active of work of synthesis and integration. “What are you learning?” or “What stands out to you?” are simple ways to bring this out.</li>
  <li><strong>F</strong>inished: Are you actually finished? Is there anything else that might be lingering that wants attention but hasn't been shared yet? “Have we finished?” or “Is that enough for today?” or “Does that feel complete?” are solid closing questions.</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h2 id="quotes-i-">Quotes I ❤️</h2>
<blockquote>
  <p>The best coaches make us recognize we have gaps in our reasoning. The moment we become unsure of what we know, learning happens. This is good coaching. — Marcia Reynolds</p>
</blockquote>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Essay] Moving from insight to application in coaching conversations.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/taking-action/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/taking-action/</guid>
				<pubDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2024 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<blockquote>
  <p>When clients experience a new insight, they feel as if a door has opened to a new way of seeing. They have yet to walk through the door.  - Marcia Reynolds, <a href="https://bookshop.org/p/books/coach-the-person-not-the-problem-a-guide-to-using-reflective-inquiry-marcia-reynolds/13045008?ean=9781523087839">Coach the Person, Not the Problem</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>An technique in coaching conversations is to slow things down so that people can explore and reflect on their experience, a key part of the <a href="/writing/essays/noticing-and-exploring/">noticing and exploring phase</a>. The usefulness of this coaching move is that it asks people to critically assess and make visible what they think is going on and what assumptions, limiting beliefs, biases, and other factors might be at play. It guides them to look under the surface at what is going on in their inner world, wonder about what might be going on in others, and  think about what might be happening systemically that is contributing to the issue or situation they are exploring with you. The net result of raising awareness is an increase in the amount of information you have available for the next phase of the coaching process: <a href="/writing/essays/reflection-and-maining-making">meaning making</a>.</p>

<p>Meaning making is where you look at everything you have uncovered together and ask, “What sense can we make of all of this? What patterns are emerging? What from the past does this bring to mind? What no longer feels true? What new stories are emerging?” Meaning making is an act of knowledge creation—it is the process of developing new understanding and new ways of seeing so that the person being coached begins to experience themselves, their colleagues, and the situation in new ways.</p>

<p>Okay, so you’ve increased awareness, surfaced new information, and made some meaning from what you've discovered. Now what? Precisely! The “Now What?” phase of the cycle brings us to the part of the conversation where new commitments are made towards future actions. Remember, it isn’t a coaching conversation if it doesn't lead to action! The transformative power of coaching is both in the new knowledge it creates and how it asks people to <em>apply</em> that knowledge directly in the real world.</p>

<p>Action might look like:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Role playing or trying something new during the session.</li>
  <li>Engaging in additional reflection after the session</li>
  <li>Conducting self-observation throughout the week in service of ongoing awareness</li>
  <li>Trying something new after the conversation is over</li>
</ul>

<p>Be sure that the person you are working with chooses the action they want to take (within reason-if you are their manager and see them choosing action that will clearly backfire or misses the mark of organizational goals, then put some guardrails in place). This encourages ownership of the learning journey and taps into intrinsic motivation tied to personal and professional goals.</p>

<h2 id="the-practice">The Practice</h2>
<p>You want to move into application questions after the person you are working with has some kind of shift in perspective or ah-ha moment. This is critical to create an opening for <em>new</em> actions and behaviors—without the necessary perspective shift any commitments to action will be a rehash of the same behaviors that created the issue in the first place. Here are some questions that can facilitate commitments to future action in the “Now What?” part of the conversation:</p>

<ul>
  <li>What will you do now?</li>
  <li>How could you make this happen?</li>
  <li>What new ideas do you have on how to get there?</li>
  <li>What feels possible now that wasn't before?</li>
  <li>What might get in the way?</li>
  <li>Given what you have uncovered, what will you do differently?</li>
  <li>How could you improve the situation?</li>
  <li>What are some other approaches to consider?</li>
  <li>What is another option?</li>
  <li>What could you do to bring everything back in alignment?</li>
  <li>Where haven't you looked for a solution yet?</li>
  <li>What’s the solution you've been too scared to try?</li>
  <li>If you were to create an ideal situation, what is your goal? How would it work?</li>
</ul>

<p>You may find that the person you are coaching isn’t sure what to do next. In this case, spend some time brainstorming together around what new actions might be possible. Once you've come up with a list, ask them to select the one or two that feel most applicable and doable.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="quotes-i-">Quotes I ❤️</h2>
<blockquote>
  <p>It may not be quite so obvious in those short, informal, coach-like conversations that a team leader has with a direct report, but the potential is there for valuable and lasting impact. For leaders, this approach accesses a mind-set that includes a focus on both results (action) and on growth (learning). This is, fundamentally, the role of leadership; both lenses are essential. Every initiative and every issue that arises is an opportunity for team members to learn in the process of taking action. At the same time, it is a way for leaders to develop their leadership eyesight: seeing those opportunities. - <a href="https://bookshop.org/p/books/co-active-coaching-the-proven-framework-for-transformative-conversations-at-work-and-in-life-karen-kimsey-house/7897923?ean=9781473674981">Co-Active Coaching, Fourth Edition</a></p>
</blockquote>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Essay] Transforming experience into learning.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/reflection-and-meaning-making/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/reflection-and-meaning-making/</guid>
				<pubDate>Mon, 11 Dec 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<blockquote>
  <p>Reflection, a key aspect of coaching, involves helping the individual stop and remember the action in which they have been engaged, think through the details, consider what worked and what did not work and consider the causes and implications of the same. Reflection seems to be most effective when done in the presence of others.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>A quick summary of where we’re at in the coaching process: you’ve set the focus of the conversation, you’ve done some exploration work to facilitate deeper awareness, and you’ve widened the field of inquiry to invite new perspectives by using open and honest questions. The conversation so far has shed light on the underlying dynamics, assumptions, or perceptions that supports the current behavior of the person you are working with, behavior they may want to change. Essentially what you have done up to this point is to increase the amount of <em>information</em> available to be used as material in the coaching conversation.</p>

<p>What do you do with all of this new information? You facilitate a process of reflection and meaning making, creating space for the person you are working with to make new connections and insights from what they have uncovered. This is the “So What?” part of the process where people conceptually process what they are learning from the experience—both the experience itself and the new awareness that has been created through exploring the experience. Where they can make sense of what has happened and give it meaning. This is a crucial part of the process because meaning making is what transforms experience into learning.</p>

<p>As meaning making takes place, new stories emerge about how the person you are working with understands themselves, their relationships with the people around them, and their own role in creating the opportunities and outcomes they long for. The creation of new stories loosens the grip of the old ones, revealing them for what they are-stories rather than truths. Over time these new stories influence how a person experiences themselves, their colleagues, and their work. They invite new ways of thinking, doing, and being. Stories become recipes for structuring experience and meaning making is foundation on which new possibilities emerge.</p>

<h2 id="the-practice">The Practice</h2>
<p>We covered some questions for the “So What?” phase of the cycle, and I’ll add a few new ones since we are explicitly focusing on reflection and meaning making this issue. The key idea to keep in mind here is that as a coach you are asking questions and creating space for the person you are working with to bring new insight and meaning to the information you have uncovered in the exploration phase.</p>

<ul>
  <li>What sense are you making of this?</li>
  <li>How is your understanding of the situation changing?</li>
  <li>What feels important in all of this?</li>
  <li>What makes this important?</li>
  <li>What does this mean to you?</li>
  <li>What feels different?</li>
  <li>What are you discovering about yourself? Others? - The situation?</li>
  <li>What habitual patterns are you noticing?</li>
  <li>What does this remind you of?</li>
  <li>What would you like to be different?</li>
  <li>What still needs to be considered/included?</li>
  <li>What new meaning is beginning to emerge?</li>
  <li>What is the story you are telling yourself now?</li>
</ul>

<p>Meaning making questions support another person to question their assumptions, reframe their perspective, and see the situation in new ways. They illustrate the ways in which we mistake our <em>interpretation</em> of how things are as truth, and invite a deeper consideration of what else might be happening. Words make worlds, and when we step into meaning making with another person we create the space for new meaning and new worlds to emerge.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="quotes-i-">Quotes I ❤️</h2>
<blockquote>
  <p>Coaching is a way of being, listening, asking, and speaking that draws out and augments characteristics and potential that are already present in a person. An effective coaching relationship creates a safe and challenging environment in which learning can take place. Coaches know that an oak tree already exists within an acorn. They have seen the one grow into the other, over time and under the right conditions, and are committed to providing those conditions to the best of their abilities. Successful coaches continually learn how best to “farm” the potential they are given to nurture.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>— Tim Gallowey, "<a href="https://thesystemsthinker.com/the-inner-game-of-work-building-capability-in-the-workplace/">The Inner Game of Work: Building Capability in the Workplace</a>"</p>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Essay] Building awareness in coaching conversations.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/noticing-and-exploring/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/noticing-and-exploring/</guid>
				<pubDate>Sun, 26 Nov 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<p>In <em><a href="/writing/essays/the-coaching-process">The Coaching Process</a></em> we took a high level overview of the coaching process, introducing the “What? - So What? - Now What?” framework. In the next three issues we’ll be looking at each phase of the process in more detail, starting this week with “What?” And remember, for the coaching conversation to be successful it is important to first take the time to <a href="/writing/essays/beginning-together">begin together</a>.</p>

<p class="caption"><img src="/images/wmw/process-framework.png" alt="the process framework" />
Process Framework for Enabling Action, via Dorothy Strachan</p>

<h2 id="what-aka-noticing-and-exploring">What? Aka Noticing and Exploring</h2>

<p>The majority of work you do in a coaching conversation will be in the “What?” phase of the cycle, which is often referred to as the exploration phase. This is where you work with another person to facilitate a deeper awareness of the issue they have brought to the coaching conversation. To increase their ability to see beyond the edges of their current interpretation, to uncover habitual patterns of thinking and doing that are contributing to what is happening, and to connect with an inner knowing and resourcefulness that enables a different way of relating to the issue at hand.</p>

<p>Increasing awareness is a unique aspect of coaching conversations and one of the reasons they can be so powerful. In normal conversations we are quick to identify problems and leap to action, behavior that is frequently rewarded in organizational settings. But this quickness can reinforce biases and keep us running the same old fixes over and over, leading us to wonder why we keep getting the same results and nothing seems to change.</p>

<p>To get different results you need new ways of thinking and seeing, which is what awareness building is all about—facilitating a deeper understanding that creates a wider range of possibility, leading to new ways of responding and taking action. An important distinction to be aware of is that coaching isn't about problems, it's about <em>solutions</em>.  Problems are about what is wrong, whereas solutions are about what could be better.</p>

<h3 id="stop-helping">Stop Helping</h3>
<p>Now, I'm going to say something really important and counterintuitive: in your role as coach the best way to help the other person is to <em>not help</em>. I actually assign this as homework in Week 1 of the <a href="/leader-as-coach/">Leader as Coach</a> program and people meet the assignment with a bit of incredulity and suspicion, wondering <em>“Isn’t that what we are supposed to do as managers? To help our team, to get them unstuck, to run interference, and make sure they can do what we hired them to do?”</em> Yes, <em>and</em>… if you truly want to support the development and growth of another person, hold them with <a href="/writing/essays/optimism/">unconditional positive regard</a> and trust that with some space to think and open questions to facilitate that thinking, they will come up with their own insights, answers, and next steps.</p>

<p>I always refer to Rachel Remen when discussing the challenge with helping because she <a href="https://www.awakin.org/v2/read/view.php?tid=127">says it so clearly and beautifully</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Helping is based on inequality, it’s not a relationship between equals. When you help, you use your own strength to help someone with less strength. It’s a one up, one down relationship, and people feel this inequality. When we help, we may inadvertently take away more than we give, diminishing the person's sense of self-worth and self-esteem.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So instead of helping, think of serving—in the role of coach you work in service of increasing awareness, insights, possibility, and action in another person, serving their own inner wisdom and knowing. This also requires that you hold back on sharing your experience, opinions, and advice. The shift from helping to serving is often an “ah-ha” moment for leaders who are learning to coach. They realize how much effort they have been putting in to conversations and how exhausting it is to hold more than 100% of the responsibility. Leaning back and taking a serving role, the conversation becomes more equal. Leaders often report that by doing less in these conversations they have more energy <em>and</em> get feedback that the conversation was powerful, facilitating new insights, learnings, and possibilities for the person being coached.</p>

<h3 id="coach-the-person-not-the-issue">Coach the Person, Not the Issue</h3>
<p>Another critical aspect of exploring is to remember that you are coaching the person, not the issue. This is a common maxim in many coaching programs that turns the typical management approach on its head. We are used to stepping into a work conversation and focusing on an issue, working with our direct report or colleague to figure out the best path forward. In coaching conversations the issue is secondary to the <em>person</em> you are working with. As a coach, you are a facilitator of their learning, supporting them to think about the issue in new ways. To do this, your questions need to invoke reflection, awareness, and new understanding <em>for them</em>. If you catch yourself asking questions related to the issue (e.g. going down a path of collecting more information so you can understand the issue better) stop yourself and refocus on the person in front of you.</p>

<p>A side note here: once you make this adjustment, you’ll find that you can often have impactful coaching conversations in a relatively short amount of time. This is because you aren’t wasting time getting all the details about what is going on, who said what, and what happened when. It really doesn’t matter. What does matter is how the person you are coaching is thinking about the issue and what deeper insights are available through <a href="/writing/essays/asking-questions/">open and honest questions</a>.</p>

<h2 id="the-practice">The Practice</h2>
<p>The practice this week is short and sweet, combining several of the skills and approaches we have covered in previous issues. In your conversations over the new couple of weeks, remember practice the following:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Work to increase awareness (see <a href="/writing/essays/the-loop-of-awareness/">The Loop of Awareness</a>, specifically the section on “Noticing” questions).</li>
  <li>Stop helping.</li>
  <li><a href="/writing/essays/curiosity/">Get curious</a>.</li>
  <li>Focus on facilitating learning.</li>
  <li>Coach the person, not the issue.</li>
  <li>Practice asking <a href="/writing/essays/asking-questions">open and honest questions</a>.</li>
</ul>

<p>Keep a journal where you can note what you are learning and the impact the conversations are having on yourself, your team, and the wider organization.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="quotes-i-">Quotes I ❤️</h2>
<blockquote>
  <p>I define coaching broadly as that part of a relationship in which one person is primarily dedicated to serving the long-term development of competence, self-generation, and aliveness in the other. Coaching is a central and critically important activity for any leader in any organization who sees himself or herself as working with and through others.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>— Doug Silsbee, <em>Presence-Based Coaching</em></p>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Essay] A framework for facilitating learning and action.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/the-coaching-process/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/the-coaching-process/</guid>
				<pubDate>Sun, 12 Nov 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<blockquote>
  <p>Knowledge is produced in response to questions. And new knowledge results from the asking of questions… once you have learned how to ask questions - relevant and appropriate and substantial questions - you have learned how to learn and no one can keep you from learning whatever you want or need to know. - Postman and Weingartner</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The thing that distinguishes coaching from normal conversations is its focus on awareness, meaning, and action. Coaching facilitates learning that generates knowledge, uncovers fresh perspectives, and leads to new actions and behaviors. Each of these capacities can be thought of as a step in the coaching process that creates space for people to step into their own innate wisdom and understanding.</p>

<p>So far we’ve talked about how to <a href="/writing/essays/beginning-together">begin a coaching conversation</a> and looked at the specific <a href="/writing/essays/asking-questions/">kinds of questions</a> that are inherent to a coaching approach. Today we’re going to take a step back and look at the process side of things so you have an understanding of how to facilitate learning and can begin to experiment in your conversations at work.</p>

<p>I prefer frameworks that are simple, easy to remember, and flexible enough to be able to respond to the unpredictable nature of human interaction in real-time. I find Dorothy Strachan's “What?— So What?—Now What?” framework fits the bill, providing enough structure to so that you know where you are and where to go, with openings to invite improvisation and creativity.</p>

<p class="caption"><img src="/images/wmw/process-framework.png" alt="the process framework" />
Process Framework for Enabling Action, via Dorothy Strachan</p>

<p>There are three main phases in the process “What?—So What? —Now What?” (hence the name), illustrated in a cyclical relationship that reminds us that human interactions are nonlinear and that you’ll find yourself moving between the phases in various ways throughout a single conversation.</p>

<p>Each phase is associated with a type of question:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Notice questions</strong> open up space to increase understanding and awareness about whatever happens to be the focus of the conversation.</li>
  <li><strong>Meaning questions</strong> invite reflection on what has been uncovered through exploring the notice questions.</li>
  <li><strong>Application questions</strong> create commitments towards future actions, experiments, and next steps given what has emerged from the notice and meaning questions.</li>
</ul>

<p>For the sake of clarity we’ll assume that the questions go in the order listed above—notice, make meaning, and application of the learnings—but in practice you’ll frequently find yourself moving back and forth between a couple of phases until you reach enough clarity to continue on.</p>

<p>Once you have determined the focus of the coaching conversation and figured out what you want to accomplish together, you can move into an exploration of the topic or issue at hand. This part of the process requires stepping into the unknown, which can feel challenging and uncomfortable for the coach. To do this successfully requires letting go of the reins and being willing embrace uncertainty, truly not knowing what the outcome will be. <a href="/writing/essays/curiosity">Curiosity</a> is a great friend in these moments.</p>

<p>The process framework is your map, showing you the lay of the land and the direction of your journey. The first part of your journey begins by creating the space for new understanding through the use of <em>notice</em> questions. This is an invitation to the person you are working with to gain a better understanding of what is both inside and outside of their awareness, asking them to get curious about what lies just beyond the visible horizon. Here you support them to clarify their perspective by articulating the details of what they notice and what makes that noticing so important to them.</p>

<p>Once the issue has been brought into higher resolution through the noticing exploration, you can move into <em>meaning</em> questions that invite reflection and deeper understanding. In this phase you are basically asking, “now that you know what you know, what do you understand that you didn’t before?” Together you start to look for patterns, insights, importance, and significance of what was shared in the <em>noticing</em> phase.</p>

<p>Meaning making can lead to ah-ha moments big and small. When this happens you can shift into the application questions, moving the learning conversation from reflection to commitments for future action. The general gist of this phase is, “with this new understanding, what will you <em>do</em> differently?” Make sure that whatever action plan arises that is doable in a short amount of time—encourage people to take small, immediate steps in order to create quick feedback loops for quick learning and insights to work with in future coaching conversations.</p>

<h2 id="the-practice">The Practice</h2>
<p>This week is less of a practice and more a bank of questions for each phase of the process framework to get you started. The invitation for you is to find a few conversations where you can work with the entire cycle and see what emerges. Be sure to capture your reflections afterwards—what you did that you liked, what you want to learn more about, and what you will try next time.</p>

<h3 id="what-the-notice-questions">What? The Notice Questions</h3>

<ul>
  <li>What is important about the issue? What makes it an issue for you?</li>
  <li>What matters most here? What makes this significant to you?</li>
  <li>What is another way to say this?</li>
  <li>How are you feeling about this?</li>
  <li>What are the most important factors or players in this situation?</li>
  <li>What is at stake? For you? For others?</li>
  <li>How have you contributed to the situation?</li>
  <li>What exactly needs to change here?</li>
  <li>What are you assuming here that is stopping you?</li>
  <li>What fears, doubts, or internal obstacles are keeping you from moving forward? What would it take for these obstacles to be completely gone?</li>
  <li>What do you want to accomplish?</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="so-what-the-meaning-questions">So What? The Meaning Questions</h3>

<ul>
  <li>Based on what we’ve talked about, what’s different for you now?</li>
  <li>What stands out for you?</li>
  <li>What patterns are you starting to notice?</li>
  <li>What does this remind you of?</li>
  <li>What does this all mean to you?</li>
  <li>What concerns do you have?</li>
  <li>What are you learning?</li>
  <li>How does this all fit together?</li>
  <li>What feels more clear? What still feels uncertain?</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="now-what-the-application-questions">Now What? The Application Questions</h3>

<ul>
  <li>What could you do about this?</li>
  <li>What potential courses of action do you see?</li>
  <li>What will you do about this?</li>
  <li>What step could you take this week that would move you towards your goal?</li>
  <li>What actions can you commit to? By when?</li>
  <li>How will you know you've been successful?</li>
  <li>What are you taking away from this conversation?</li>
  <li>What will you begin to do more of? Less of?</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h2 id="quotes-i-">Quotes I ❤️</h2>
<blockquote>
  <p>The idea that managers and employees can share responsibility for learning is a very adaptive one. We make the related assumption that in most organizations, everyone needs to keep learning. Most businesses and not-for-profits confront a range of competitive threats to their survival. These threats include globalization, disruptive technologies, changing societal values, and the rest of the list you've grown accustomed to hearing about. The only way for a firm to survive, let alone prosper, is for enough people in the firm to learn how to adapt to and master these challenges so that the organization can respond appropriately.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>— James Hunt and Joseph Weintraub, <em>The Coaching Manager</em></p>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Essay] The art of open and honest inquiry.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/asking-questions/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/asking-questions/</guid>
				<pubDate>Sun, 29 Oct 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<blockquote>
  <p>"An open question is one that expands rather than restricts your arena of exploration, one that does not push or even nudge you toward a particular way of framing the situation." - Parker Palmer</p>
</blockquote>

<p>One of the primary activities in a coaching conversation is asking questions. But the how and what of your asking will be different than what you might say in day to day conversations. I like to think of coaching conversations as learning conversations, a co-created space where the need to fix or analyze is suspended in favor of exploration and increased awareness. Questions do most of the work in facilitating this experience, and a great question can create clarity, surface insights, and lead us to deeper truths. There is a lot to say about the art of asking questions and we can't possibly get to it all in one issue, so today we’ll start by looking at what makes a good question.</p>

<p>There is no shortage of available material when it comes to the topic of coaching questions. <a href="https://bookshop.org/p/books/the-coaching-habit-say-less-ask-more-change-the-way-you-lead-forever-michael-bungay-stanier/17315881?ean=9780978440749">The Coaching Habit</a>, a popular book by Michael Bungay Steiner, outlines seven specific questions to guide you through a coaching-style conversation, The Co-Active Training Institute has compiled a <a href="https://cocoachingcircles.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/31-Powerful-Questions.pdf">list of powerful questions</a>, and Tony Stoltzfus has written an entire book on the topic of <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Coaching-Questions-Coachs-Powerful-Asking-ebook/dp/B00GR7AX1G/ref=tmm_kin_swatch_0?_encoding=UTF8&amp;qid=1698519710&amp;sr=8-1">Coaching Questions</a>. These kind of resources are useful when it comes to understanding what coaching questions sound like, getting a sense for the patterns in the structure, and seeing how questions can facilitate a learning experience. By all means read books, lists, articles, watch videos and listen to podcasts to help your understanding! But when it comes to asking good coaching questions, the best learning comes from practice and experience.</p>

<p>The best questions, the most powerful questions, come from what is happening in the moment between the coach and the person they are working with. From a place of open and receptive listening the coach attends to not just the issue at hand, but the wholeness of the person they are working with. They notice the words and phrases that are being used, the tone and pace of the voice, gestures, energy levels, and facial expressions. They get curious about what is revealed about how the person sees themselves specifically in relation to the issue they are exploring and how they see themselves in the world more generally. When coaches attune to a conversation in this way they tap into the source of powerful questions: presence and <a href="/writing/essays/curiosity">curiosity</a>.</p>

<p>What can be challenging for people new to this style of asking questions is that to be truly effective you have to let go of the reins. You let go of having an answer, of fixing, of what you think is right, of knowing what to do, of giving advice, and of sharing from your own experiences. You let go of knowing what the outcome will be so that you can facilitate a true learning conversation. In normal conversations we tend to ask questions to help our own understanding of a situation or to lead someone to our own conclusions. In coaching conversations we ask questions to facilitate understanding in the person we are working with. This is an important distinction—the shift from being curious for our own sake to being curious about how the world is occurring for the person in front of us. By asking questions we can support their own discovery to see themselves more clearly, their patterns of thoughts and beliefs, their default way of relating to the challenges and opportunities in front of them.</p>

<p>This kind of exploration and question asking is more akin to the art of dialogue than conversation. Parker Palmer and the <a href="https://couragerenewal.org">Center for Courage &amp; Renewal</a> has some <a href="https://couragerenewal.org/library/honest-and-open-questions-as-a-spiritual-practice/">wonderful guidelines</a> for asking open and honest questions:</p>

<p>An <a href="https://couragerenewal.org/foundations-participant-portfolio-3/wp-content/uploads/sites/11/2022/08/22-08-18-Open-Honest-Questions-.pdf">open and honest question</a>:</p>

<ul>
  <li>is one that the coach could not possibly anticipate the answer</li>
  <li>assists a person to explore their concern rather than satisfying the coach's curiosity</li>
  <li>is brief and to the point</li>
  <li>is not overloaded with background considerations and rationale</li>
  <li>does not paraphrase what has been said, and instead uses the other's words as much as possible</li>
  <li>asks about feelings as well as facts</li>
  <li>can come from intuition</li>
  <li>is not about you, so don't include storytelling or behaviors that draw attention to yourself</li>
  <li>does not have a yes/no right/wrong answer</li>
  <li>often begins with what, when where, who, or how (try avoiding <a href="https://medium.com/method-matter/the-paradox-of-why-77ee8a3b9cc3">why questions</a>)</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-practice">The Practice</h2>
<p>Open and honest questions can seem easy in theory but can be quite hard in practice. The best way to know if you’ve asked a good question is to pay attention to how it impacts the other person. Perceiving impact can be tricky though, especially in conversations where power dynamics are at play that can make revealing the true impact unsafe. This practice is designed to create an open feedback loop so that the coach can understand the full impact of each question.</p>

<p>The exercise requires two people, best done with a trusted practice partner or someone on your team who you have a strong relationship with. The idea is not only to practice asking open and honest questions but to hear first-hand how your questions have impacted the person you are working with.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Speaker, share a bit about a challenge or issue you are currently dealing with. Keep this brief, around 2 - 3 minutes.</li>
  <li>Coach, listen openly and with curiosity. Be careful not to form your questions while the person is speaking, focus on allowing yourself receive both what and how the person is sharing. When the person is done speaking, pause and see what question forms in the empty space. Ask <em>one</em> open and honest question. Don’t ask two or three consecutively! Pause again after you ask the question.</li>
  <li>Speaker, allow the question to land in your mind, heart, and body. Before you answer it, share the impact the question had on you. Does it make you curious, give you energy, invoke a defensive pattern, drain energy, something else? Once you share the impact of the question, answer it in a few brief sentences.</li>
  <li>Coach, listen while the person speaks, pause, and then ask another open and honest question.</li>
  <li>Speaker, again take the the time to feel how the question impacts you. Share what you notice. Then answer the question briefly.</li>
  <li>Repeat this until the conversation feels complete. It is often the case that within 10 minutes of open and honest questions, the speaker is seeing their situation in a new light.</li>
  <li>Switch roles, and repeat the sequence.</li>
</ol>

<p>Debrief together on what you experienced and what you are learning.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="quotes-i-">Quotes I ❤️</h2>
<blockquote>
  <p>Coaching is a way of being, listening, asking, and speaking that draws out and augments characteristics and potential that are already present in a person. An effective coaching relationship creates a safe and challenging environment in which learning can take place. Coaches know that an oak tree already exists within an acorn. They have seen the one grow into the other, over time and under the right conditions, and are committed to providing those conditions to the best of their abilities. Successful coaches continually learn how best to "farm" the potential they are given to nurture.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>— Tim Galloway, <em>The Inner Game of Work: Building Capability in the Workplace</em></p>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Essay] Setting the stage for successful coaching conversations.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/beginning-together/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/beginning-together/</guid>
				<pubDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<p>Beginnings may seem superfluous but they are essential to effective and powerful coaching conversations. There is a lot to be said for taking the time to arrive and settle in together. To slow down and get a sense of each other, allowing our attention to come into the present and to collaboratively look at the work in front of us.</p>

<p>How we begin sets the stage for what follows. In busy organizational environments focused on efficiency and productivity, it can be easy to skip over beginnings in service of getting work done quickly. But when we skip over beginnings, we miss the opportunity to fully connect and we deprive ourselves of the important work of tending to the structure of the conversation. Without connection and structure, no matter how quickly we get to the issue, we are not setting ourselves up for success.</p>

<p>Beginning well is about knowing what the conversation is about, what is most important, what will be different by the end of the conversation, and what will make the conversation useful. If these four things are in place your chances of engaging in a productive and meaningful conversation increase exponentially, simply by tending to beginnings 😊.</p>

<h2 id="the-practice">The Practice</h2>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Arrive.</strong> Give yourself a little time to settle in and get situated.</li>
  <li><strong>Tend to what needs tending.</strong> If you were coming from another meeting and you need to capture a few notes in order not to be distracted, say as much and take a few minutes to write things down. When you are done, allow yourself to stop thinking about where you were and focus on the present.</li>
  <li><strong>Check in.</strong> This can be short, but be genuine.</li>
  <li><strong>Assess.</strong> What is your impression of how they are? What picture do they paint for you of how they are seeing themselves and the world in this moment? This includes things like energy levels, focus, distraction, stress, and ability to be present. We can sense all of these things fairly quickly in the first few moments we are together with someone.</li>
  <li><strong>Set the boundaries of the conversation.</strong> These steps are a slight modification based on Claire Pedricks's wonderful book <a href="https://bookshop.org/p/books/simplifying-coaching-how-to-have-more-transformational-conversations-by-doing-less-claire-pedrick/15769790?ean=9780335249077"><em>Simplifying Coaching</em></a>:
    <ol>
      <li><strong>Subject:</strong> What would you like to explore today? What question or issue?</li>
      <li><strong>Time:</strong> In the amount of time we have, what part of that would be successful to focus on?</li>
      <li><strong>Outcome:</strong> What would you like to be different by the end of this conversation?</li>
      <li><strong>Know:</strong> How will you know that this conversation has been useful?</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Begin.</strong> If you both feel satisfied with the focus and the outcomes, ask them where they would like to start. Let them choose what feels important, and start the conversation with, "Where shall we start?"</li>
</ol>

<p>Once you begin the conversation, ​<a href="/writing/essays/curiosity">curiosity</a>​, <a href="/writing/essays/optimism">optimism</a>​, and ​<a href="/writing/essays/the-loop-of-awareness">using your attention intentionally​</a> will take you through the rest.</p>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Essay] An orientation towards life and not knowing.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/curiosity/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/curiosity/</guid>
				<pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<p>Before we begin, I just want to mention a few essays that can be helpful to reference as you start to get familiar with using curiosity as part of your leadership practice:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Set up a <a href="/writing/essays/the-learning-container">learning container</a>, a set of activities/practices done in the morning and evening to <em>hold</em> the work you are doing as you develop a Coaching Leadership Style. Think of it as scaffolding for learning.</li>
  <li><a href="/writing/essays/working-with-strengths">Work with your strengths.</a>. This is incredibly important for developing your unique Coaching Leadership Style and for being authentic and transparent with others. When people know what is important to you and what your values are, they understand you more deeply and trust increases. Don't be a chaos ball of uncertainty and unpredictability.</li>
  <li>Use the <a href="/writing/essays/the-loop-of-awareness">Loop of Awareness</a> to free your attention. When you learn how to utilize attention intentionally, more of the world opens up in service of noticing, observing, reflecting, learning, and taking choiceful action.</li>
  <li>Approach people with <a href="/writing/essays/optimisim">optimism</a> to support people with change and growth. This is a posture that invites people to plant their feet firmly in reality while taking an optimistic view of what is possible in the future. This is incredibly important when it comes to supporting others in sourcing their own knowledge, creativity, and decision making in service of the person they are becoming.</li>
</ul>

<p>Some of you might be scratching your head and thinking “Andi, where is the coaching in all of this?” Isn’t coaching about asking good questions? If you have been following along and trying out the practices and exercises, I imagine you’ve noticing some subtle shifts in the conversations you are having. That's because you are <em>already</em> coaching. By changing your mindset, using attention wisely, leaning on your strengths, and seeing the inherent resourcefulness in those you work with, your presence itself is having an impact (more on presence in a future edition).</p>

<p>But coaching is <em>also</em> about asking good questions, and we’re going to get into that today from the perspective of Curiosity, an important quality to cultivate in the mindset of a coach.</p>

<h2 id="the-idea">The Idea</h2>
<p>Curiosity isn't necessarily about questions, though they are a part of it. Curiosity is an orientation towards life, a willingness to embrace a state of not knowing, and a genuine interest in uncovering something new. A very useful skill in rapidly changing times. The questions that arise from this place can unlock new ways of seeing, thinking, and acting.</p>

<p>Curiosity in coaching isn’t about gathering information so you can decide what to do. Instead, it acts in service of the learning and growth of the person you are working with. It illuminates areas for exploration so that you can discover what is hidden from view. Questions that come from genuine curiosity can be evocative or provocative, an invitation to pause, reflect, and deepen understanding. Co-Active Coaching recommends paying close attention the impact your questions have—when you ask one, where does it send the other person? Do they remain at the surface giving easy answers, or do they go to new places, quietly listening to the answer that form as new insights and understandings come forward?</p>

<p>Genuine curiosity, sourced from a place of openness and wonder, leaves no room for fear; the excitement of exploration and discovery is too pervasive for anything else to be present. Which is wonderfully liberating for both the coach and the person being coached! Imagine being in a conversation at work—a conversation with your boss no less—where it is truly okay to not know. And to feel fully supported in your exploration to find that knowing, to engage in reflection and discovery until you see yourself and the situation in new ways and new possibilities emerge.</p>

<p>When this happens, people become more generative in their ability to source creative solutions. Curiosity also builds deep connection and trusting relationships, a critical component of high performing teams. Imagine two conversations: one rooted in problem solving, the other rooted in curiosity. In the problem solving conversation, questions are asked to gather information and figure out the source of the issue in order to fix it. Sometimes it can feel like an interrogation, where questions thinly mask judgements, blame, and negative assessments of the people and decisions involved. The conversation rooted in curiosity has no need for any of this because judgements, blame, and negative assessments are <em>conclusions</em>, they close us off to learning, and curiosity cannot exist simultaneously with conclusions. The questions in this conversation put everyone on equal footing, seeking to uncover and understand something new, with genuine interest for what can be learned. The first conversation creates defensiveness, reactivity, and distrust. The second generates curiosity, responsiveness, and trust.</p>

<p>It can be really easy to get hooked by the content of what someone shares with us. The nitty gritty details of who said what, and who did what, and when, and what happened after that. With coaching, you really don’t need all those details because your curiosity is about the <em>person</em>, not the issue. This is a subtle and important difference. When you focus on the person, your curiosity and coaching orients around who they are <em>in relationship to</em> the issue, how they interpret the situation, and what possibilities they see or don't see. What happened in the past doesn't really matter. You want to keep the conversation in the present and oriented towards the future.</p>

<p>And one last thing—get curious beyond the words. Listen to their gestures, tone, energy, posture, pace, and tempo. If something shifts or change, get curious! If someone who usually talks fast and has a lot of energy slows down and gets soft, get curious!</p>

<h2 id="the-practice">The Practice</h2>
<p>This is a collection of micro practices you can try out in the coming weeks:</p>

<ol>
  <li>In your next 1:1, limit your responses to questions and mirroring. Questions should primarily be of the how and what variety, though when and who and where can work too. <a href="https://medium.com/method-matter/the-paradox-of-why-77ee8a3b9cc3">Do your best to avoid why questions.</a> Mirroring helps the conversation feel a little less awkward—by sharing back the words and phrases the other person is using (exactly as they are, no modifications) you serve as a reflection, helping them see and hear themselves more deeply and clearly.</li>
  <li>Keep your questions short. Ask one at a time. Avoid leading questions. Pause and allow space for the other person to reflect and respond.</li>
  <li>If something goes sideways, or you feel the sudden pressure of needing to have an answer, throw your hands up in the air and shout, "How fascinating!" <a href="https://youtu.be/qTKEBygQic0?si=0Ivp2Q4dXGH0TAsD&amp;t=360">in the style of Benjamin Zander</a>. I’m not kidding. I used to do this at work a lot.</li>
  <li>From the Hendricks Institute comes the very useful HMMMMMMMMM. It is very hard to make this sound and <em>not</em> feel more curious. If you need to up the curiosity factor, just let out a good HMMMMMMMMM.</li>
  <li>Before you ask a question, preface it with the words, "I’m curious…"</li>
  <li>When in conversation with someone you are coaching, try standing or sitting side by side looking out a window (if you don't have a window maybe a painting or a nature poster with an inspirational quote). If you can't do this physically, just imagine you are together shoulder to shoulder, equals looking at the same thing and wondering about what is possible.</li>
  <li>When the conversation is over, reflect on what happened and ask yourself, “What is even more mysterious about this person?” This question keeps the curiosity and wonder alive against the very human propensity to label, categorize, interpret, and judge the world around us.</li>
</ol>

<p>Before you step into any of these practices check in with yourself and see if you are truly open to learning or not. If you are, embrace your genuine curiosity and jump into the conversation. If you aren't, pay attention to what is being activated in you and give yourself what you need in the moment. This might be a break from the conversation, a few deep breaths, zooming out from the details, acknowledging and accepting exactly where you are, etc.</p>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Essay] Seeing capacity and potential in others.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/optimism/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/optimism/</guid>
				<pubDate>Sun, 17 Sep 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<p>When I talk with leaders about the idea of optimism as a useful tool for coaching, they usually point out that pretending things are great isn’t going to fix performance problems. Which is true—bypassing reality with magical thinking leads to disappointment, frustration, and resentment. Just ask anyone who has ever delayed having a difficult conversation at work—by the time the talk actually happens considerable damage has been done.</p>

<p>But optimism isn’t about unreasonable hope, it’s about an acceptance of how things are now and a belief that they can be better. It is a perspective, a way of seeing, an orientation towards life that celebrates what an individual or system is doing <em>well</em> , even if what it is doing well happens to be getting in the way of desired outcomes. Optimism is imbued with curiosity and turns its gaze to the future as a place of possibility and action.</p>

<p>Think back to your last year at work. How many times has pointing out what is going wrong—with an individual, project, team, or system—resulted in change? My guess is very few.</p>

<p>Optimism starts with a willingness to accept what is, while simultaneously holding the belief that change is possible and things can get better. Optimism rests in the <a href="/writing/guides/building-a-relationship-with-change">paradox of change</a>, inviting us to understand that <em>change happens just by paying attention to what is</em> . This grounded acceptance of the present is what distinguishes optimism from wishful thinking.</p>

<p>Optimism is the belief that people are doing the best they can with the resources and awareness they have available to them. And <em>awareness</em> is the entry point for coaching. Coaching increases awareness and resourcefulness in others so that new possibilities can emerge, new paths for action can be taken.</p>

<p>On the other side of optimism is pessimism, a perspective we are biologically hard-wired to inhabit because it keeps us alive. It lives in the narrowing band of fear, looking to the past for clues that can protect us from whatever might threaten us in the present. When pessimism clouds our view, we can only see what is going wrong as we spin in reinforcing negative feedback loops fed by fear. In a world of increasing uncertainty, it can feel like we perpetually live in the constricted, protective domain of pessimism.</p>

<p>But optimism, optimism gives us another choice. One that feels increasingly radical in a polarized world. <a href="http://josephmelnickphd.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/Articles/Article_on_Optimism%20with%20Sonia.pdf">Joseph Melnick and Sonia Nevis</a> say of optimism:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Optimism is about having the courage to try things. It is about stepping into something because we hope it will be a good thing, without knowing what will happen. And it is about learning not to stay attached to the negative when things do not turn out in ways we had hoped.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>And this is <em>exactly</em> what coaching is. Raising awareness, taking courageous action, seeing what happens, and reflecting in service of learning from the richness of what we have just experienced. This level of learning isn’t just at a cognitive level, but a level that involves the entirety of our being. Whatever happens, we get curious, accept, learn and grow.</p>

<p>Imagine something is going sideways at work and you <em>know</em> it’s not going well but can’t figure out how to get the results you want. Or maybe you got a negative performance review, or had a big conflict with a colleague at work. And then your boss calls you into a conference room (or Zoom call) and proceeds to tell you all about what a problem this is. What happens as you hear this? You probably make yourself a little smaller (or a little bigger with anger), negative self talk gets louder, you feel sad/mad/frustrated, and you have no idea what to do to make it better. You feel tired and hopeless.</p>

<p>Or, your boss calls you into that Zoom call and you both explore what is going on with non-judgement and acceptance. Your boss listens, asks questions, and then comments on what you are doing really well in the situation. They might say something like, “you are really good at protecting yourself when you feel attacked. Do you know that?” And you might pause for a second and think some kind of trick is afoot, but as your boss encourages you to to examine this piece of feedback and feel the truth of it, your curiosity enters the room. You might say something like, “Yeah, I am really good at that. But it feels like that's the only way I know how to respond and I can see how it gets in the way of collaboration.”</p>

<p>And <em>right there</em> is the seed that unlocks possibility. Because as soon as you accept this statement of what you are doing well, you get curious about it. Curious enough to see the benefit and also <em>the cost</em>, and wonder about other ways you might approach the situation. And that curiosity, fostered by the presence of optimism, is the gateway to expanding your range of responsiveness in similar situations.</p>

<p>For coaches, optimism is less about what you do and more about <em>how you are</em>. This is a mindset based in the ideas of unconditional positive regard, strengths-based change, and positive psychology. It’s not about a set of questions you can ask, but about how you see the world and the inherent capacity you see in others. As you embody optimism, your thinking begins to shift and your actions follow-suit. So this starts with being, percolates into thinking, and finally influences the doing side of leading and coaching.</p>

<h2 id="the-practice">The Practice</h2>

<h3 id="practice-one-resentment-to-appreciation">Practice One: Resentment to Appreciation.</h3>
<p>This an individual practice based on the work of John O. Stevens.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Think of someone at work (or in your life) that you are frustrated with or in some way or another negatively impacted by what they are doing (or not doing).</li>
  <li>Write down a list of your resentments. Begin each sentence with the words “I resent—” and express clearly and exactly what you resent about this person.</li>
  <li>When that feels complete, stop writing and take a minute to move, stretch, wiggle, or shake it out.</li>
  <li>When you are ready, sit down and resume.</li>
  <li>Go through your list of resentments, one by one. For each one, cross out the word <em>resent</em> and replace it with the word <em>appreciate</em>.</li>
  <li>Go slowly, trying each one on for size. How do you feel as you make the shift? Is there something you actually do appreciate in what you thought you resented?</li>
  <li>If you want, add a few more sentences to elaborate on your appreciation.</li>
  <li>Reflect on your experience in this exercise. What did you notice mentally emotionally, and somatically when you engaged in writing down the resentment list? What shifted as you turned resentments into appreciations? What new insights did you make? What will you do with what you have learned?</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="practice-two-filtered-listening">Practice Two: Filtered Listening</h3>

<p>This practice can be done in a 1:1 conversation or team meeting; any situation where you have the opportunity to be an active listener. If you are doing this in a 1:1 scenario, you may want to let the person you are talking with know you are experimenting with different ways of listening and to not be alarmed if they notice your demeanor change.</p>

<ol>
  <li>In this exercise you are going to practice with both the pessimistic and optimistic stance.</li>
  <li>As you begin the conversation or meeting, spend the first 5 - 10 minutes listening from a pessimistic stance. Narrow your focus and look for what is wrong, certain that you are seeing more problems than anyone else and that you those around you do not have the capacity to solve them. If you are in a 1:1 conversation, notice the impact the pessimistic stance has on the person you are listening to.</li>
  <li>After 5 - 10 minutes, let go of the pessimistic stance. Give yourself a moment to let it melt out of your body, dissolve from your thoughts, and abdicate your emotions.</li>
  <li>Now step into the optimistic stance. Consider the person or people in front of you and listen with curiosity. Hold the perspective that everyone is doing the best they can with the awareness and resources available to them, and the conviction you know they have the capacity to create change. If you can generate a genuine sense of warmth and positive regard, even better. But don’t try to fake this-others can detect when we are just putting on a show.</li>
  <li>As you listen, see if you can observe what this person or group knows how to do really well, even if it’s something that frustrates or annoys you. How does this serve the person or group? What do you think it is like for them to engage in the world this way?</li>
  <li>Once you have finished this practice, take a few notes about what you noticed from the experience. If the person you were listening to knows you were trying out listening approaches, debrief and see how the experience was for them. What will you do with what you are learning?</li>
</ol>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Essay] A tool for using attention with intention.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/the-loop-of-awareness/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/the-loop-of-awareness/</guid>
				<pubDate>Sun, 03 Sep 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<p>Our attention is one of the most powerful tools we can use in coaching. What we pay attention to informs how we perceive and interpret the world around us. But most of us, over the course of a lifetime, have developed patterns of perception that freezes us in a narrow band of reality. We learn to pay attention to certain things and discount others, and in doing so reinforce attention loops that are particular to our own individual experience of the world.</p>

<p>If you think about it, this is where a lot of miscommunication and disagreement comes from. People in the same situation experience it in radically different ways because of what they are paying attention to. For example, take the common occurrence of a meeting where disagreement was expressed. For someone whose attention loop is highly focused on emotions, they might feel the meeting was tense and filled with conflict. For another person who focuses on ideas, they might have walked away from the meeting feeling invigorated and challenged. And yet a third person whose attention seeks out the information they need to take action, they might leave the meeting frustrated that progress wasn't made. Same meeting, wildly different experiences and interpretations of what happened.</p>

<p>It takes practice to “unhook” our attention and develop the capacity to take in more of the world, and to do so without adding layers of interpretation and story. To start to see the habitual patterns that have shaped our sense of how the world is, and see that we have constructed a particular version of reality that is specific to our personal way of being.</p>

<p>The Loop of Awareness, developed by <a href="https://hendricks.com">Gay and Katie Hendricks</a>, is a useful tool for freeing our attention and breaking out of habitual patterns of perception. It teaches us how to consciously use our attention, whether we keep it wide to see the big picture or narrow in on something particular to see the details. When we learn how to use our attention in this way we can bring a deeper level of awareness to coaching conversations, giving us more information to work with in support of learning and growth.</p>

<h2 id="the-practice">The Practice</h2>

<p>Begin by directing your attention to yourself.</p>

<p>Notice how you are in this moment—maybe you pick up on your breathing, or a sensation in your body, or your posture. There are so many things you can notice—don't try to notice them all! Just pick up on one or two things. Let your attention rest long enough to note your state.</p>

<p>Now direct your attention to the space around you.</p>

<p>Get curious! Notice something in your environments. Objects nearby, textures, the quality of the light, the temperature, movement, etc.</p>

<p>Direct your focus back to yourself.</p>

<p>And then go back outside yourself again to the space around you.</p>

<p>Keep moving your attention back and forth. Do so in a way that feels natural and comfortable. Consciously shift back and forth, allowing your attention to deepen your awareness of what is happening right now, this very minute, inside and outside yourself. As you do this, feel how powerful your attention can be when used in a conscious and supportive way.</p>

<p>If you want, try oscillating your attention out and in rapidly. Or really slowly. Experiment with different rhythms of moving your attention. <strong>Leave judgement behind and simply notice what you notice</strong>.</p>

<p>You can also do this with a person, instead of the space around you. The process is the same, except when you go outside yourself your focus rests on another person, rather than the space around you, so what you notice might be different.</p>

<h2 id="reflection-prompts">Reflection Prompts</h2>
<p>Notice your own pace and pattern of shifting attention.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Where does your attention sit naturally? Does it rest more on your inward state, or is it more focused on the outer world?</li>
  <li>What is it like to move your awareness with intention? What is easy or hard about the process?</li>
  <li>How do you shift your awareness, what is it that you shift? Your eyes? Your thoughts? Your body?</li>
  <li>What is the rhythm of your oscillation? What cadence feels most comfortable? Most uncomfortable?</li>
  <li>What are you learning about your patterns of focus and awareness? What will you do with this information?</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="things-of-which-we-can-be-aware">Things Of Which We Can Be Aware</h2>
<p>An incomplete list of things to bring your attention to, compiled by <a href="https://www.routledge.com/Organizational-Consulting-A-Gestalt-Approach/Nevis/p/book/9780881632491">Edwin Nevis</a>:</p>

<p><strong>Sensations</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>The outcomes of seeing: sights</li>
  <li>The outcomes of hearing: sounds</li>
  <li>The outcomes of touching: textures, tactility</li>
  <li>The outcomes of gustation: tastes</li>
  <li>The outcomes of olfaction: smells</li>
  <li>The outcomes of proprioception: body tissue/kinesthetic stimulation (tendons, muscles, etc.)</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Internal Verbalizations and Visualizations</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>Thinking, ruminating, internal dialogue</li>
  <li>Planning, wishing, hoping</li>
  <li>Memory, remembering past events, history</li>
  <li>Dreams and fantasies</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Feelings</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>Happiness, pleasure, contentment</li>
  <li>Elation, zest, lust, joy, confidence</li>
  <li>Sadness, depression, helplessness, despair</li>
  <li>Fear, disgust, shame, remorse</li>
  <li>Respect, awe, admiration, wonder, reverence</li>
  <li>Irritation, rage, anger, jealousy, hatred</li>
  <li>Vanity, self-confidence, pride</li>
  <li>Affection, love, warmth, empathy</li>
  <li>Boredom, indifference, scorn</li>
  <li>Tenderness, compassion, pity</li>
  <li>Guilt, anxiety</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Values</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>Predispositions, sets, inclinations, theories</li>
  <li>Judgements and attributions</li>
  <li>Summaries or generalizations of past experience</li>
  <li>Nature of boundaries, prejudices</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Interpersonal and Group Interactions</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>Participation patterns</li>
  <li>Communication styles</li>
  <li>Figural elements: content, energy, differences</li>
  <li>Functional activities</li>
  <li>Norms</li>
  <li>Atmosphere, climate</li>
</ul>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Essay] Building your coaching approach on what you do naturally.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/working-with-strengths/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/working-with-strengths/</guid>
				<pubDate>Sun, 20 Aug 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<p>Each of us has a unique way of engaging with the world that influences what holds our attention, gets us excited, creates meaning, and gives purpose. It shines through in our personality, shapes our leadership style, and can also be a foundation for coaching.</p>

<p>Values and strengths are two ways to describe or encapsulate this uniqueness. Values reflect what we care about and strengths are an expression of what comes naturally. Knowing and living our values is an important part of how we show up in leadership and life, and leaning on our strengths can be an accelerant for development and transformation.</p>

<p>The world of <a href="https://www.health.harvard.edu/topics/positive-psychology">positive psychology</a> and <a href="https://www.naahq.org/sites/default/files/naa-documents/education/Building-A-Strengths-Based-Organization.pdf">strengths-based change</a> suggest that focusing on what is right is more effective than focusing on what is wrong. As <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Qui-Gon_Jinn">Qui-Gon Jinn</a> says, “your focus determines your reality.” If we focus on weaknesses and what is wrong, then our reality is one of scarcity, lack, and fear. If we focus on strengths and what is right, our reality is filled with capacity, competence, and trust.</p>

<p>So on the one hand we have fear, and on the other we have trust. What does this mean for our ability to learn and change? And to coach? Some moods such wonder, ambition, and trust are conducive to learning while others like fear, overwhelm, and resignation prevent learning from happening <sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. When you step into the role of coach, leaning on your strengths can help you feel more confident, present, and open to whatever comes up in conversation. This attitude contributes to an environment of wonder and trust, a place where two people can really explore what is happening with openness and honesty.</p>

<p>Conversely, if you are overly focused on what you might do wrong or what your weaknesses are, the conversation will be palpably different because curiosity and learning are not possible when moods like fear and worry are predominant. If you are unsure of yourself and thinking about what you might do wrong, the environment won't feel supportive for you or the other person.</p>

<p>It is important that you <a href="https://www.want.uji.es/wp-content/uploads/2020/04/2020_Pelaez-Coo-y-Salanova.pdf">apply this same perspective</a> to the person you are working with. Look for and highlight their strengths, reflect their capacities, and communicate the trust you have in their ability to figure things out. Of course, there may be areas to improve, but these can also be approached through a strengths-based lens (more on that in a future article). The main idea to focus on is that by identifying and working with strengths, on what is going right and working well, leaders as coaches build trusting relationships that support learning, creativity, and growth. If you focus on what someone is doing wrong and where they are lacking, the conversation will generate fear and the range of creative action will narrow.</p>

<h2 id="knowing-your-strengths">Knowing Your Strengths</h2>
<p>So, what are your strengths? What kind of coach are you? What unique ways do you facilitate insight, action, and learning through conversation? Answering these questions will help you get clear on how you are showing up as a coach.</p>

<p>There are many ways to uncover your strengths, a few of which we’ll go over together. If you have another method or resource you prefer, then by all means use it!</p>

<h3 id="personal-reflection">Personal Reflection</h3>
<p>Take a moment and reflect on what comes naturally to you, what you do really well without even thinking about it. Maybe there are things you do, or ways that you do them, that people have commented on. What lights you up and gives you energy when you do it? Spend a week or two doing some reflective journaling around the topic and see what comes up.</p>

<h3 id="formal-and-informal-feedback">Formal and Informal Feedback</h3>
<p>Annual reviews, 360 feedback, in the moment appreciations or acknowledgements for something you’ve done well, are all good sources to reference. I’m also a fan of reaching out to people who know you-friends, family, team, colleagues, sangha, whatever-and asking them to share what they see as your strengths.</p>

<h3 id="via-strengths-survey">VIA Strengths Survey</h3>
<p>The <a href="https://www.viacharacter.org">VIA Institute on Character</a> offers a <a href="https://www.viacharacter.org/surveys/takesurvey">free survey</a> to help identify your top “character strengths”-24 scientifically identified strengths that make up what's best about our personality. They also have some useful resources to understand strengths and develop them more fully in service of leadership and coaching.</p>

<h2 id="the-practice">The Practice</h2>
<p>If you’ve set up your learning container already, you just need to make a few modifications. If you haven’t you can probably just follow the instructions below and be fine, but if you want to read more about how to set one up, check out <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/the-learning-container/">Issue #2</a>.</p>

<p>In the morning, continue to spend five quiet minutes with yourself without technology or other distractions. Bring your awareness to hands and arms, feet and legs. Feel your breath in your belly and chest. As you settle in, see if you can sense yourself, your “you-ness”.  What thoughts, emotions, and sensations are you aware of, and how do those contribute to the unique way you sense and respond to the world around you?</p>

<p>In the evening, spend some time journaling and reflecting on your strengths. Here are some questions to get you started:</p>

<ul>
  <li>What are your top strengths?</li>
  <li>What do your strengths mean to you? What do they help you do?</li>
  <li>What happens when you overuse a strength?</li>
  <li>How do your strengths influence how you lead?</li>
  <li>How/when did you <a href="https://www.viacharacter.org/topics/articles/road-map-to-strengths-use">use each of your strengths</a> today?</li>
  <li>How can you use these strengths to support others?</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h5 id="footnotes">FOOTNOTES</h5>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>For more on moods and learning, see "<a href="https://bookshop.org/p/books/learning-to-learn-and-the-navigation-of-moods-the-meta-skill-for-the-acquisition-of-skills-stuart-e-dreyfus-phd/11324350?ean=9780692801796">Learning to Learn and the Navigation of Moods</a>." <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Essay] Structures that hold the work, practices, and commitments of how we lead and live.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/the-learning-container/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/the-learning-container/</guid>
				<pubDate>Sun, 06 Aug 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<p>A learning container is a structure that holds the work, practices, and commitments required to live into a new way of leading or living. For the purpose of this newsletter the work and commitment is to develop a way of being that can facilitate powerful coaching conversations. Coaching is about building awareness, taking new action, and reflecting on the outcomes as a way of learning and growing through experience. It requires keen self-awareness and deep curiosity about others. Embarking on the coaching path can be uncomfortable and challenging, the way forward isn't always clear, and development is a decidedly non-linear path. So when we're learning coaching skills and we want to shift how we're showing up with our teams, we can create a container to remind us of our commitment every day.</p>

<p>Containers can take many forms. Just step outside and take a walk in a forest-you’ll quickly realize <a href="https://onbeing.org/blog/parker-palmer-theres-a-place-for-every-question-in-the-vast-container-of-nature/">​nature is a vast container​</a>. For the purpose of learning new ways of leading and living, the container is more simple, consisting of a morning mindfulness practice and some evening reflections.</p>

<h2 id="the-practice">The Practice</h2>
<p><strong>In the Morning</strong></p>

<p>Spend five minutes each morning connecting with yourself. Preferably before you check your phone, email, or any digital screens. Take a few breaths all the way down to your belly. Feel where your body has contact with another surface (maybe you are lying in bed, sitting in a chair, standing at the window, etc). What are you aware of? What sensations, emotions, and thoughts are you noticing? What do you notice about the environment you are in? Allow yourself to be fully present with whatever is showing up, even if it brings some discomfort.</p>

<p>Starting the day with a small mindfulness checkin builds our capacity to be present and aware in each moment. As this practice becomes a natural part of our daily routine and our awareness muscles grow, we will suddenly find moments at work where we have access to the same level of presence, making it easier to observe our thoughts, emotions, and actions from a more conscious place. Seeing the habitual thoughts and emotional reactions that shape our behavior is the first step in building the capacity to take creative and choiceful action.</p>

<p><strong>In the Evening</strong></p>

<p>Reflect on you day. At the end of each day-either when the work day is done or when you are winding down for the night-reflect back and answer the following questions:</p>

<ul>
  <li>What were my dominate emotions today?</li>
  <li>What thoughts/thought patterns showed up the most?</li>
  <li>What actions did I take? What actions did I avoid?</li>
  <li>How did my thoughts, emotions, and actions contribute to the outcomes I was trying to achieve? How did they get in the way?</li>
</ul>

<p>Paired with the morning mindfulness practice, the reflection questions contribute to building the muscle of self-observation. This is the first step in developing awareness of who you are, and who you are becoming, as a leader-being able to observe ourselves in action and understand what (really) drives our behaviors.</p>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Essay] A high level overview of the Coaching Leadership Style.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/the-coaching-leadership-style/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/the-coaching-leadership-style/</guid>
				<pubDate>Tue, 11 Jul 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<p>The Coaching Leadership Style (CLS) is an approach to leadership that focuses on two tracks: development of self and development of others. By utilizing essential coaching skills and methodologies, work becomes a place for deep transformation, learning, and realizing potential.</p>

<h2 id="what-are-leadership-styles">What are Leadership Styles?</h2>

<p>Leadership Styles are a set of core characteristics that describe how a leader leads. When people step into their first leadership role their style emerges organically from past experiences, current beliefs, personality patterns, and what they value most—accomplishment, collaboration, challenge, being recognized, feeling competent, etc. Sometimes the emergent leadership style is congruent with the organization and environment a leader is working in, but at some point leaders find themselves in a situation where their leadership style suddenly seems to stop working.</p>

<p>When this happens the default style, which had been functioning happily and invisibly in the background, is made visible. Leaders realize they have a choice in how they lead and that it is possible to be more effective in their roles by learning new styles. Over time leadership moves from an unconscious expression of beliefs about what leadership should be, to a conscious commitment to lead uniquely from an aware, responsive, and integrated place. When a leader reaches this point they are able to tailor their leadership style specifically for the needs of any given situation.</p>

<h2 id="types-of-leadership-styles">Types of Leadership Styles</h2>

<p>Kurt Lewin developed one of the earliest leadership styles framework in the 1930s in which he defined <a href="https://www.leadershipahoy.com/kurt-lewin-leadership-styles/">three primary leadership styles</a>: autocratic, democratic, and laissez-faire. Half a century later, Daniel Goleman described <a href="https://hbr.org/2000/03/leadership-that-gets-results">six leadership styles</a> based on his Emotional Intelligence framework: coercive, authoritative, affiliative, democratic, pacesetting, and coaching. Then there is the <a href="https://thinkinsights.net/leadership/hersey-blanchard-situational-leadership/">Hersey-Blanchard Model</a> (also known as Situational Leadership), developed in the 1960s, that says no leadership style is better than any other and that a leader must adapt their style to those they lead. The model relies on four styles to support people based on their abilities and attitudes (called ‘willingness’ in the model): directing, coaching, supporting, and delegating (I believe this is the first instance of coaching being linked to a leadership style).</p>

<p class="essay-image-extend"><img src="/images/essays/leadership-styles.png" alt="smiley" /></p>
<p class="caption">Goleman's six leadership styles based on Emotional Intelligence, via <a href="https://hbr.org/2000/03/leadership-that-gets-results">HBR</a></p>

<p>I use these frameworks as more of a heuristic than an exact science—useful tools for understanding and reflecting on the set of skills experienced leaders should have access to. In practice, leadership styles don’t fit into neat categories—most leaders embody a mix of several—so it is important to be conscious of which is being used and why. The work of a leader, at least some of it, is to notice their style in action and learn what it says about how they view both themselves and others. When this becomes clear leaders respond with increased awareness, utilizing different styles with intention, in order to be truly effective.</p>

<h2 id="what-is-the-coaching-leadership-style">What is the Coaching Leadership Style?</h2>

<p>The Coaching Leadership Style (CLS) is an orientation to leadership that is built on a solid foundation of coaching skills including optimism, reflection, self-efficacy, positive emotions, and learning. Leaders who adopt the CLS exponentially increase their ability to support others to develop their potential and take action that creates results. This style combines leadership, management, coaching, positive psychology, organizational behavior, teaming, and learning.</p>

<p>While Situational Leadership integrates aspects of coaching into its theory of leadership, CLS is more comprehensive in its coaching approach and utilizes coaching not just for skills development, but to support people with attitude misalignments (lack of confidence, limiting beliefs, fear, uncertainty), increased ownership of their own development, and long term excellence and professional goals.</p>

<p>The Coaching Leadership Style is also different in the way it utilizes curiosity and learning as the lens through which development, growth, and action happen. It is solutions-oriented and action-based, embodying a true co-creative partnership with others to improve performance and develop long-term strengths. Of all the leadership styles I’ve come across, the coaching leadership style is the most comprehensive when it comes to integrating care, positive regard, high standards, accountability, and direct conversations that empower both the leader and their team to achieve outcomes, overcome challenges, and embrace possibilities in creative ways. It is also a powerful way to close the <a href="https://www.gsb.stanford.edu/insights/knowing-doing-gap">knowing-doing gap</a> and implement long-lasting, transformational change.</p>

<p>Elements of the Coaching Leadership Style include:</p>

<ul>
  <li>A strengths-based approach to change</li>
  <li>Embodying a growth mindset</li>
  <li>Giving clear and effective feedback</li>
  <li>Presence and self-awareness</li>
  <li>Embracing optimism, self-efficacy, positive emotions, and learning</li>
  <li>Working in mutual and creative partnership with others</li>
</ul>

<p>A Few Benefits of the Coaching Leadership Style:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Increased self-confidence and self-efficacy</li>
  <li>The ability to take actions that create results</li>
  <li>Achievement of desired goals</li>
  <li>Increased trust</li>
  <li>Less stress</li>
  <li>Deeper capacity to be with uncertainty and ambiguity</li>
</ul>

<p>The CLS consists of two tracks—self development and the development of others. For a leader to be effective as a coach they must also engage in their own developmental work bringing self-awareness, reflection, and new actions to their own way of being in the world and relating with others. Because of this, it is also the most self-reflective of the leadership styles.</p>

<h2 id="why-it-matters">Why it matters</h2>

<p>Businesses operate in constantly changing and complex environments that require openness, flexibility, and curiosity to be effectively navigated. Organizations that can access the maximum range of sensing, awareness, and creativity available will be more responsive than the competition, able to take first advantage of new developments. For this to be possible, leaders must let go of the idea they should have all the answers and instead step into an approach to leadership that maximizes ongoing and collective learning. The CLS is well-suited to this task.</p>

<hr />

<p>If you are interested in learning more about the CLS and how to practice it, sign-up for <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds/">Words Make Worlds</a>, a bi-weekly newsletter about the art, science, and craft of the Coaching Leadership Style.</p>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Essay] On the impact of effective coaching conversations at work.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/creating-space-for-others-to-think/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/creating-space-for-others-to-think/</guid>
				<pubDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<p>For a long time the maxim “don’t bring me problems, bring me solutions,” ruled the world of organizational leadership. While a quick search for the phrase reveals it has fallen out of favor in most management circles, within organizations the ethos <a href="https://www.inc.com/jim-schleckser/build-organizational-muscle-encourage-your-team-to-bring-solutions-not-problems.html">seems alive and well</a>. To a degree this makes sense — most executives I know have progressed up the leadership ladder by assessing big picture challenges and opportunities, coming up with solutions, and getting things done. Once you are senior enough this just becomes a part of your job. The thinking that got you there comes along too, creating a positive feedback loop that further entrenches the approach.</p>

<p><a href="https://ecorner.stanford.edu/clips/encourage-a-culture-of-inquiry">According to Adam Grant</a>, asking people to only bring solutions means 1) people will never speak up about the hardest problems, and 2) when they do have a solution they will push for their approach above all others, resulting in a culture of advocacy rather than inquiry. The detriment here is that a lot of organizational energy goes to positioning, optics, and politics as each leader vies to be the one whose solution gets implemented. What if that energy could be funneled to collaboratively understanding the most pressing and complex problems facing an organization, both internally and externally?</p>

<p>Imagine each person in an organization as a node of awareness. A single node cannot comprehend the wholeness of any complex problem or situation, in the same way <a href="https://allpoetry.com/The-Blind-Man-And-The-Elephant">six blind men cannot comprehend the wholeness of an elephant</a>. Which means it is also unlikely that any solution an individual comes up with will be appropriate to the problem at hand, in part because the problem has not been adequately sensed on a larger scale. A manager or executive might have a wider view of the problem, but it is still incomplete in various ways.</p>

<p>I suspect this is why coaching skills are becoming increasingly important for organizations and executives, as a way of increasing awareness in rapidly changing and unpredictable conditions. A coaching approach builds this awareness by creating space for others to think, where deeper questions can be voiced and explored. In this regard, coaching conversations can essentially be thought of as learning conversations, places of pause where new meaning is made. Conversations that support an increased capacity for individuals and teams to sit with uncertainty, to deeply and thoroughly consider an issue, to reflect on their own contributions to the issue, and to use curiosity as a launchpad for innovation.</p>

<p>Coaching conversations are qualitatively different than other types of conversations leaders have and are not meant to be a replacement. When utilizing a coaching-style approach, a leader must learn to let go of the reins and rely on genuine curiosity and not-knowing to guide the work. This isn’t a passive approach by any stretch of the imagination, but the activeness of coaching is focused on the person and the awareness they are bringing to the issue, not on the issue itself (this is a subtle but important shift). By staying firmly rooted in reality with an optimistic view of the future and asking open and honest questions, the leader as coach creates space for the person they are working with to reflect, make meaning, see new possibilities, and take effective action.</p>

<p>And while coaching conversations are solutions-oriented, solutions are undefined at the outset. When two people come together to explore an issue with a commitment to curiosity and learning, they first build the strength of their relational connection. This connection enables deeper ways of seeing and listening that can regulate the nervous system, <a href="https://medium.com/reboot-leadership-resiliency/leading-consciously-staying-relational-with-presence-and-attunement-a6af1d1233f6">create a sense of safety</a>, and increase creativity. The solutions that emerge in this space are of a higher caliber than solutions that come from stress and fear, which is precisely what the “bring me a solution” mindset invokes. <a href="https://hbr.org/2017/09/the-problem-with-saying-dont-bring-me-problems-bring-me-solutions">According to Sabina Nawaz</a>, this approach can “cause employees to shut down in fear, breeds a culture of intimidation, and prevents some problems from surfacing until they’re full-blown crises.”</p>

<p>So hopefully you are on board with the idea that creating space for others to think is a good thing. That something beneficial happens both personally and organizationally when one person is supported by another in building awareness, creating meaning, and finding new ways forward without someone else, like their manager, doing it for them.</p>

<p>And yet! This can feel really uncomfortable for leaders, especially leaders who believe they already know the answer and want to help. Why not alleviate the problem by sharing what we know and have learned through experience?</p>

<p>Because helping, it turns out, isn’t really all that helpful. In <a href="https://www.awakin.org/v2/read/view.php?tid=127">Helping, Fixing, and Serving</a>, Rachel Remen points to the inherent power imbalance in helping:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Helping is based on inequality, it’s not a relationship between equals. When you help, you use your own strength to help someone with less strength. It’s a one up, one down relationship, and people feel this inequality. When we help, we may inadvertently take away more than we give, diminishing the person’s sense of self-worth and self-esteem.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is an important nuance to pull out — the idea that a coaching approach is one that gives, that increases a person’s sense of self-worth and self-esteem. This is the quiet foundation of effective coaching and why it is so important to create space for people to think and find their own path forward. With this seed of change in place, all the other benefits of coaching conversations become magnified.</p>

<p>We each have our own capacity to sense into the challenges in front of us and figure out how to move through them. Sometimes we need another set of eyes and ears to see and listen for patterns that live in our blind spots, but once these patterns are made visible we can utilize our inherent creativity to find novel solutions to problems. And when we are the ones who do the meaning making, when we are the ones generating new possibilities, when we are the ones choosing what actions to take, then our self-worth, self-esteem, and personal power begins to grow. And the next time we face a challenge we have the memory of our innate resourcefulness in finding our way through. This scales to the team and organizational level as well, where collective memories play an outsized role in a system’s ability to support or block its own capacity to navigate challenges and change.</p>

<p>When these kind of conversations are happening across an entire organization, everything loops back to increase resourcefulness and creativity. As we collectively deepen our awareness, calm our nervous systems, and increase our creative capacity, our ability to work with uncertainty and overcome obstacles becomes stronger.</p>

<p>And it all starts with creating space for others to think.</p>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Essay] A story of coming home.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/on-belonging/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/on-belonging/</guid>
				<pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<p class="caption"><img src="/images/essays/belonging.png" alt="smiley" />
Trillium illustration courtesy of Midjourney.</p>

<p>When I was in elementary school we lived on a dirt road in a small, wooded neighborhood. The houses were somewhat far apart, walkable but not dense enough to fill a pillowcase full of candy on Halloween. There weren’t any kids close by so I spent a lot of time in the forest and with our older, friendly neighbors.</p>

<p>The Gregorys, who lived across the street, had vineyards and strawberry patches, the first spiral staircase I had ever seen, and put flowers in their salads. My 10 year old brain marveled at this act of wild creativity. It was on their property that I learned an early and important lesson about electric fences. The Lanes lived down the road past a large patch of trilliums in a shaded midcentury modern and were involved in the world of midwestern architecture (Mr. Lane was the architect of a local high school). And there was Mr. Bateroff in his pick-up truck, speeding too fast along the little dirt road. I mimicked the head shaking and tutting of the adults every time he zipped by, kicking up a cloud of dust. Other than speeding he was a friendly man, hosting neighborhood potlucks and letting us catch tadpoles from the pond in his back yard.</p>

<p>And then one summer two girls, sisters, moved into their grandparents house down the street. The move was temporary while their parents, who had also moved in, navigated a brief hiatus in employment.</p>

<p class="essay-image-extend"><img src="/images/essays/woodland.jpg" alt="smiley" /></p>
<p class="caption">The house looked something like this.</p>

<p>Laura was my age and had a flair for drama (think Sound of Music not Gossip Girl) and mischievousness, of which her older sister was usually the target. She had a way of smiling, followed by a quick wink, that let you know she was up to something. I don’t remember us <em>becoming</em> friends, we just immediately <em>were</em>.</p>

<p>Our imaginations functioned on the same frequency and the connection felt intuitive. There was nothing to negotiate, just endless worlds to explore. The way we played was wildly expressive and lacked any sense of self-consciousness that would have been destabilizing. One day after school we became cats and crawled through her grandparent’s house on all fours meowing at everyone, which drove her sister wild (this put “being cats” in regular play rotation). We filled bowls with Cheerios, set them on the kitchen floor, and ate without using our hands before meowing some more, purring, and taking naps.</p>

<p>I also was building friendships with other girls at school, girls who lived in neighborhoods with paved streets, lots of kids, and a housing density that could fill a pillowcase full of candy faster than you could say, “Ghostbusters!”</p>

<p class="caption"><img src="/images/essays/stickers.jpg" alt="smiley" />
Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@stationery_hoe?utm_source=unsplash&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_content=creditCopyText">Kasturi Roy</a> on Unsplash</p>

<p>I learned a lot from them too—how to be a part of a group, the rituals of girlhood interactions, and how to belong socially. Collecting stickers was popular activity and we’d spend hours flipping through each other’s books commenting on recent additions and occasionally making strategic trades. The glorious puffy, glittery, smelly stickers were all safely behind plastic coversheets of photo album pages. To my recollection we never actually stuck them on anything. Maybe they were a proxy for our budding style and curatorial sensibilities, maybe they were a way of understanding how to negotiate social situations while quietly broadcasting our identity. But deep imagination wasn’t a part of how I interacted with this group of friends. It was more of a tentative foray into the question of “how do we belong together?”</p>

<hr class="section-break" />

<p>As my career took off I found myself spending more and more time in the world of stickers. Learning the rituals of belonging in corporate and start-up environments and learning them pretty dang well. But the cost was high—I lost my connection with intuition and imagination, along with the courage to step into relationships where such things could flourish. Whenever I met someone who lived on that frequency, connected to the flow of life in ways I longed for, I felt shame. Shame for having lost touch with this part of myself and shame that I didn’t know if I could connect with it again.</p>

<p>The world of stickers asks us to sacrifice a part of ourselves for the safety of belonging. Encoded are rituals for how we behave, what we do, and what we acquire so that we can be accepted, successful, and liked. As I examined this aspect of my own life it became clear that in my bid for belonging I routinely abandoned myself.</p>

<p>To rectify this dire situation I figured I needed to get back to connecting with the Lauras of the world. I wondered if I could become a tuning fork, vibrating at a frequency that would invite connections that do not require negotiation but simply the willingness to be, and the courage to follow with openness and curiosity, the currents of creativity.</p>

<p>Recently I was talking to a dear friend, <a href="https://whitneyhess.com/">Whitney Hess</a>, and shared that I was hearing echoes from the world of stickers that softly called to my fear of not belonging. In response she shared that for her, no belonging mattered more than belonging to herself. Well beyond what my ears and brain were processing, her words acted like a soothing balm to existential aches I didn’t know I had.</p>

<p><em>What matters most is belonging to myself.</em></p>

<p>In life, when do we ever truly belong to ourselves? In childhood we belong to our family, in adolescence to our peer group and culture, and in adulthood to society. What gives us the courage to listen and heed the call, after learning to belong in so many ways, that it is time to come home to ourselves? I thought I needed to reclaim my connection to the Lauras of the world, but I am learning that first I must reclaim my connection to myself. As <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6qfbpBzqitA&amp;list=PLSR2TqZCSzFPTE6k34dP-CC8A7NnAPQ1a&amp;index=25&amp;t=318s">Brené Brown</a> says, “our worth and belonging are not negotiated with other people. We carry those inside our hearts.”</p>

<p>What does it mean to belong to ourselves? Here is what I’ve discovered so far: belonging to ourselves requires a radical act of trust. The willingness to connect deeply with the currents of knowing that swirl inside of us and the faith that what we find there is enough to guide who and how we are in the world. A way of settling into our bodies so deeply that a vast stillness opens and we can listen for what wants to come through. And when we hear it we tend to it, stay true to it, and allow it to become a part of our being.</p>

<p>Belonging to ourselves isn’t some kind of “my way or the highway” approach to life, in fact it is quite the opposite. As I’ve cultivated my own belonging I’ve found that I am more open to contact, more connected to the world, more in the flow of life. I am grateful for what I have learned from the world of stickers and from the Lauras, and I can see how they are all part of navigating the world together. But until we can fully belong to ourselves it is just about impossible to find our way without squeezing into uncomfortable contours that were never ours to fill. Belonging to ourselves invites the world to fold itself around our rightful shape and shows us all the ways in which we so beautifully and perfectly belong — to ourselves, to the world, and to life.</p>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Essay] A short treatise on centering.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/working-with-discomfort/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/working-with-discomfort/</guid>
				<pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<p>In life we all face bumpy moments, periods of turbulence and uncertainty, times of just not wanting things to be the way they are. The scenarios are vast: <a href="/writing/essays/receiving-feedback/">receiving feedback</a> that is hard to hear, dealing with a difficult colleague, not getting funding, getting laid off, having our hearts broken — there are so many ways that life can be uncomfortable and intense. The natural inclination is to fix whatever ails us and bring life more in line with our vision of what it should be. And sometimes this is the right approach, when there is a clear solution that is within our control to implement. But more often than not we deceive ourselves about what we can control and spend a lot of time exhausting ourselves pretending otherwise.</p>

<p class="essay-image-extend"><img src="/images/essays/discomfort.jpg" alt="smiley" /></p>
<p class="caption">Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@jbowersphotography?utm_source=medium&amp;utm_medium=referral">Jonathan Bowers</a> on Unsplash</p>

<p>Fittingly, I’m writing this article in the darkness of my home office, a single candle brightening the space but certainly not warming it. The power has gone out on a winter night. We’re in the midst of a bomb cyclone here in California and the wind just blasted off a part of my neighbor’s roof which is now sitting on the power lines as the storm rages. It is cold. I just broke out my subzero sleeping bag.</p>

<p>I do not like this. I have things to do. I hate being cold and have bad circulation. My nose is an icicle.</p>

<p>And so I center.</p>

<p>This is now my current reality. I can try to control (avoid) the reactions the situation brings up in me by tensing and pushing away my frustration, distracting myself online, or pouring a glass of wine. Or I can accept what is, let the frustration move through me, and move into action. I gather lanterns, chargers, blankets, headlamps, and anything else that would be helpful to navigate this night. I call my boyfriend and ask him to pick up something for dinner. I light a candle and sit down to write this article in the dark, at least while the battery is charged.</p>

<p>“But Andi,” you say, “that’s a pretty tame scenario. Of course you were going to get candles and blankets and figure out food.”</p>

<p>Which is true, but if I had moved into action from a place of frustration and reactivity I may not have considered all the things I did. I may not have been open to the way a suddenly new and novel situation was asking me to move in different ways. I probably would have overloaded my nervous system and been grumpy the rest of the evening.</p>

<p>Here’s another one by way of example: recently a part of my brain has decided to raise the possibility that every decision I’ve made in my life was the wrong one. What it lacks in logic it makes up for in emotion. Whenever this idea pops up it grabs me and my body starts to freak out. Tense muscles, shortness of breath, spiraling thoughts. It feels real. I can try and control this by pushing it away and focusing on something else or I can center.</p>

<p>Centering calms my nervous system and gives me the capacity to be with the fear (née terror) that I have followed the wrong path. That I have really messed up somewhere along the way. I allow it all in, and bring compassion to myself and what I am feeling. I can ask myself the question, “what if this is true?” and have the presence, fortitude, and curiosity to explore the fear. It’s not comfortable, but I can hold it all. And when I do this, when I work with the fear rather than try and control it or avoid it, a few things happen. The first is that it doesn’t seem so bad. Even if it were 100% true that doesn’t mean that the next decision I make will be the wrong one. The second is that I now have awareness and choice available to me, there is energy that can be moved into action.</p>

<p>Richard Strozzi-Heckler <a href="https://strozziinstitute.com/centering-the-unity-of-action-and-being/">describes centering</a> as “…the broad and abundant platform from which we launch into a full relationship with the world, and ourselves.” Centering is the practice of bringing the head, heart, and body into alignment and becoming fully present. It’s ridiculously simple to do, and deceptively hard to master. But what centering creates in us is the ability to relax into ourselves so that we can hold more discomfort, be with the intensity, and face reality as it is. Centering is not about being Zenned out, shut down, detached, or peaceful. We center to deepen our ability to feel more, not to feel less. As <a href="https://strozziinstitute.com/staff/alta-starr/">Alta Starr</a> says, “We center so that our aliveness is as full and available to ourselves as possible. We center to be alive.”</p>

<p>The basics of centering go something like this:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Focus on your breathing:</strong> when we are moving from a place of reactivity our breathing tends to be shallow and rapid. Bring attention to your breath and take a few slow, deep inhales. Let the exhale go wherever it goes. Breathing works, just ask the science.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Shift your posture:</strong> notice how your body is shaping itself and shift into a more centered and aligned place. Wiggle your toes and fingers. Feel the length of your spine and reach the top of your head towards the sky.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Bring your attention to the present:</strong> stop time traveling into the past or the future! Focus your attention on what is going on right here, right now in your immediate environment. On what is going on right here, right now, in you. Allow yourself to feel the discomfort of disappointment, anger, hurt, sadness, powerlessness, uncertainty, and fear with deep compassion for yourself. It’s okay to be here. This is where you are. Allow your body to hold everything that is in your awareness.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>As you do this, notice what starts to shift. Discomfort often “grabs” us and pushes our nervous system into overdrive as it executes the motions of avoidance (whether that’s fight, flight, freeze, appease, or some combination therein). What usually happens for me as I sit with discomfort is that my body softens and the weight of the discomfort begins to ease up. As this happens, my field of vision widens and I can start to see possibilities for taking conscious, intentional action.</p>

<p>You can do all of this in about 30 seconds. For an even shorter technique try Wendy Palmer’s instructions:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Inhale up and lengthen your spine, exhale down softening your chest. Think of something that makes you smile.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Interestingly, centering is also a great practice when life is filled with joy, ease, and flow. Centering allows us to deepen our capacity to receive gratitude, success, and positive regard. I have worked with so many people who really struggle to fully let in and feel the fullness of their own competence and the impact they’ve had on others.</p>

<p>So give it a try. Build a simple centering practices into your day. In the morning with a cup of coffee. Before a meeting. In the evening as you wind down your day. Center to unify action and being. Center to feel your aliveness.</p>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Essay] The only constant in life is change. - Heraclitus</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/transitions/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/transitions/</guid>
				<pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<p class="caption"><img src="/images/essays/transitions-texture.jpg" alt="smiley" />
<a href="http://twitter.com/yogidan2012">@yogidan2012</a> on Unsplash</p>

<p>Life is a ceaseless process of transition. The small transitions of daily life slip by unnoticed while the big changes—career, relationship status, geographic location, etc.—are worthy of celebratory social media posts. From the outside these changes seem to happen quickly, a snapshot in time that marks the spot where one thing ceases to be and the next begins. What doesn’t make it into a LinkedIn update is that the snapshot—what we see outwardly as a marker of change—is only a small part of a much longer, invisible, non-linear process.</p>

<p>At the beginning of the pandemic I left my career in tech to become an executive coach. With a coaching certification already in hand and a small roster of clients on the side, I thought the transition would be straightforward. I <em>love</em> coaching and was ecstatic to be able to do this work full time, but wow did I underestimate what the transition would ask of me. Two years in and I’m <em>still</em> in the process of transition.</p>

<h2 id="on-transitions">On transitions</h2>

<p>The simple awareness of a transition is enough to begin the process, whether the transition itself is intentional or not. Faced with a new reality, people look for ways to orient around the change and understand what it means. It’s common to spend time reflecting on personal values to remind us of who we want to be in the world. Transitions can be an opportunity to shake off what felt compromising or intolerable in the past in order to live more congruently in the present.</p>

<p>William and Susan Bridges, some of the best writers on the subject, define transitions as: “the process of letting go of the way things used to be and then taking hold of the way they subsequently become.” In theory this sounds straightforward but in practice we can easily fall into “<a href="https://hbr.org/2022/01/when-a-major-life-change-upends-your-sense-of-self">identity paralysis</a>” — the inability to move on from previous identities and embrace new ones, <em>whether the change itself was positive or negative</em>. Transitions inevitably unravel our understanding of who we are in order to make space for <em>who we are becoming</em>.</p>

<p>Letting go is hard work. What happens to our identity in the midst of transition isn’t an additive process in which a new identity gets layered onto the our current one. It is an undoing, a cleaning out, a shedding. My career as a tech executive was intricately tied to my identity and way of being in the world. It was how I signaled my value to society and how society saw value in me. It defined what occupied my attention and how I structured my days and weeks. Who was I without the complex flow of organizational life to define me? When the daily rhythms of company work disappeared, so did my sense of self.</p>

<h2 id="the-transition-model">The Transition Model</h2>

<p>If you asked me a few years ago how transitions work, I would have said something like this:</p>

<p class="essay-image-extend"><img src="/images/essays/transitions-mine.png" alt="smiley" /></p>
<p class="caption">My faulty model of transitions.</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The Ending:</strong> something happens that precipitates a change. In my case, I realized that something vital came alive as a coach and I wanted this work to be the focus of my days, weeks, and years. I put in notice at work, said tearful goodbyes to my team, and dropped my work computer in the mail.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The New Beginning:</strong> the new beginning begins! I put up a website, opened my doors, and began coaching.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>But it turns out they look more like this:</p>

<p class="essay-image-extend"><img src="/images/essays/transitions-bridges.png" alt="smiley" /></p>
<p class="caption">William &amp; Susan Bridges model of transitions.</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The Ending:</strong> something shifts and alerts us to the closing of a cycle or period in life. At the same time, seeds of the new beginning are present along with a third space—the neutral zone—a liminal place of unbecoming.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The Neutral Zone:</strong> as we move through the stages of letting go, of grief, of understanding ourselves in new light and new context, the liminal space of the neutral zone grows and encompasses most of our awareness. We feel disoriented and uncertain.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The New Beginning:</strong> the new beginning takes shape and builds momentum. We are in conversation with the new situation while simultaneously in contact with the neutral zone and the process of metabolizing the ending.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>Bridges’ model completely shifted my understanding of transitions in two fundamental ways. First, the existence of the neutral zone as a place of necessary disorientation was the key to bringing acceptance and compassion to my experience. And second, the insight that all three stages occur simultaneously over time helped me let go of the need to have it all figured out, let go of trying to control the experience and instead give myself over to the process of transition itself.</p>

<h2 id="the-three-stages-of-transition">The Three Stages of Transition</h2>

<p>Let’s look at the three stages of transition a little more closely.</p>

<h3 id="an-ending">An Ending</h3>

<p>Endings are a kind of symbolic death in which we must let go of the person we’ve been in order to create space for something new to emerge. This is sometimes scary, always uncomfortable, and absolutely necessary to truly take advantage of what transitions can offer in terms of personal and professional transformation.</p>

<p>Endings themselves have different aspects, making them more of a process than a singular event. According to the Bridges’ research, there are 5 key phases to endings:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Disengagement:</strong> the systems that helped support our identity cease to be a part of our environment. Things like calendars, communication channels, coworkers, and responsibilities are no longer a part of our world. It’s okay to let them go.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Dismantling:</strong> once we disengage from these systems, space opens up to unpack our relationship to our previous role and the identity we created in relationship to the organization, system, and team. The separation of dismantling is what needs to happen to move from ‘we’ to ‘I’.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Disidentification:</strong> as we dismantle and disengage, old ways of defining ourselves through roles, responsibilities, and titles begin to fall away. If we are doing this right, we will start to lose a sense of who we are.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Disenchantment:</strong> this is the time to let go of assumptions about reality and accept our own role in creating the specific version we have been inhabiting. We begin to sense that reality has layers and it is time to look below the surface.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Disorientation:</strong> a time of emptiness and disorientation, we no longer know which way is forward, and which way is back. This is the doorway to the neutral zone.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>Endings can open up old wounds, particularly if we have done a good job of compartmentalizing and suppressing the pain of prior experiences. If this happens to you, know that this is very common and you are not alone. Friends, family, therapists, healers, and coaches can be supportive during this time provided the relationship is built on trust and safety. For a quick rundown of what this work entails, “<a href="https://www.thehappinessdoctor.com/blog/7-ways-to-heal-your-old-emotional-wounds">7 Ways to Heal Your Old Emotional Wounds</a>,” is a good place to start.</p>

<h3 id="the-neutral-zone">The Neutral zone</h3>

<p>The neutral zone is a liminal space, an emptiness between ending and beginning. It provides a pause between the old identity and a new one, a pause where the deep work of transitions can unfold. Being in the neutral zone invites us to sit with the discomfort of feeling aimless and undone.</p>

<p>Opening up to this space, to this in-between, gives us access to new ways of perceiving the world. The more we can let go into the aimlessness of the neutral zone, the more we have access to new levels of consciousness. We can tap into other ways of knowing such as deep imagination, intuition, and the dreamtime. When we allow ourselves to see the world differently we expand our sense of reality and connect to a deeper sense of purpose. The neutral zone is necessary in order to metabolize old identities and create the substrate for something new to emerge. Without the neutral zone we wouldn’t have access to this transformational magic.</p>

<p>The neutral zone works in a time outside of time. Personally, I’ve been sitting in the neutral zone for about a year and a half. By this point I’ve become familiar with the visceral process of excavation, sensing where the old identity is filling space that will be needed to support the emergence of a new beginning. It’s not easy though, the letting go.</p>

<p>“Really? This too?” I ask the Neutral Zone.</p>

<p>“Yes, even this too,” is always the reply.</p>

<p>And so I comply, gently, letting another part of my identity dissipate. Resting in the space of not knowing and trusting that this will, at some point, lead somewhere. Bridges calls this experience a kind of emotional wilderness, a place where we can tap into the alternate flow of time needed for internal changes to occur, for internal changes require much more time than external ones.</p>

<h3 id="the-new-beginning">The New beginning</h3>

<blockquote>
  <p>“When we are ready to make a new beginning, we will shortly find an opportunity,” — William and Susan Bridges (p. 158)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The stirrings of a beginning, of a true beginning, happen inwardly. We are changed and transformed by the neutral zone, reconstructed in ways that support the adult we are becoming. And when that becoming has reached a certain point, when we are ready, a beginning beckons. Beginnings are organic, ordinary, and small—heralded without fanfare by hints from inner signals. According to Bridges, these hints can come in many forms: ideas, images, comments, impressions, and dreams to name a few. If we pay close attention to the words and visions that make us feel alive, that have a special kind of resonance, we will find poetic guides to a new beginning.</p>

<p>I thought my new beginning was becoming a coach, but in hindsight I can see it for what it is: an ending. I am still floating in liminal space of the neutral zone letting more of my identity wash away and releasing old ways of orienting myself in the world. The person I am becoming requires yet more space, more letting go, more unraveling. The deeper beginning is still unknown to me, but I can sense it rustling on the periphery, the faintest whispers of something new. I must be still to hear it. Only then will I be able to know what beckons.</p>

<h2 id="the-transition-checklist">The Transition Checklist</h2>

<p>Transitions aren’t just about getting to the other side, they are an invitation to fully surrender to something that cannot be fully known by the cognitive mind. Understanding and accepting this doesn’t make the process any easier, but can be reassuring to know how it works. I encourage you to read <a href="https://bookshop.org/books/transitions-40th-anniversary-edition-making-sense-of-life-s-changes/9780738285405">Transitions: Making Sense of Life’s Changes</a> because it is a stellar companion to have along life’s journey. But if I were to encapsulate what I’ve learned about transitions into a quick list, I’d offer the following:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Take time to reflect and welcome whatever is occurring for you.</li>
  <li>Recognize your thoughts</li>
  <li>Honor your emotions</li>
  <li>Tune into physical sensations</li>
  <li>Create a ritual or event that symbolizes the closing of a chapter in your life. Let yourself experience the ending.</li>
  <li>Create space for emptiness. Find a regular time to be alone.</li>
  <li>Accept resistance, and welcome it in.</li>
  <li>Listen for the new beginning.</li>
  <li><a href="https://hbr.org/2005/01/whats-your-story">Craft a story to tie the past and the present together</a>.</li>
</ol>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Essay] Receiving feedback can be scary, but it doesn’t have to be.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/receiving-feedback/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/receiving-feedback/</guid>
				<pubDate>Sat, 20 Feb 2021 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<p>Good feedback, whether you are on the receiving or giving end, requires an attitude of curiosity and openness. <a href="https://medium.com/method-matter/creating-the-right-space-for-feedback-d54a872019ab">Intentionally creating space for feedback</a> can help, but even with the right space, receiving feedback can be really scary. Many organizations have formal systems of feedback in the style of mid-year and annual reviews. And it’s not uncommon for informal continuous feedback to supplement formal reviews. Formal or informal, the moment feedback is on the table, there’s a good chance <a href="https://www.verywellmind.com/what-happens-during-an-amygdala-hijack-4165944">our amygdala is going to freak out</a>. And when it does, it’s fight, flight, or freeze time. With practice, we can move away from defensiveness and reactivity, and find ways to receive feedback while remaining grounded, open, and curious.</p>

<h2 id="what-happens-when-we-receive-feedback">What happens when we receive feedback?</h2>

<p>The most common thing people do when receiving feedback is internalize it. Immediately. It just comes into our inner landscape and takes up permanent residence. The challenge when feedback is internalized so quickly is that we lose the space and perspective to examine it, understand, and process it. And when we bypass these critical steps, feedback becomes Truth. This is why reactivity and defensiveness are common responses when we experience feedback — it feels like a Truth has just been shared that we weren’t invited to participate in creating.</p>

<h2 id="the-receiving-feedback-checklist">The receiving feedback Checklist</h2>

<h3 id="step-1-check-in-with-yourself-get-grounded-get-curious">Step 1: Check-in with yourself. Get grounded. Get curious.</h3>

<p>I begin everything with a self-checkin, and receiving feedback is no different. As soon as you realize you are in a feedback conversation, take a few deep breaths. Connect to your center. Feel your feet. How are you feeling? What is your energy like? Where is your attention being drawn? What emotions are coming up? Take a few deep breaths, and see if you can find a little more ease in your body.</p>

<h3 id="step-2-listen-from-center">Step 2: Listen from center.</h3>

<p>Listen to what the other person has to say. But not just any kind of listening, centered listening. In her book <a href="https://bookshop.org/a/21645/9781492946694">Leadership Embodiment</a>, Wendy Palmer distinguishes between “listening from personality” and “listening from center”.</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Listening from personality:</strong> a good clue you’re in this mode is a need for control, approval, and safety. If what is being said isn’t what you want to hear, feelings of stress, anxiety, and irritation will come to the fore when listening from personality making it harder to receive, assess, and process information. In this mode, our bodies might physically contract, causing the mind to contract, stress hormones to kick in, and suddenly fight, flight, or freeze responses kick in.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Listening from center:</strong> characteristics of this mode include an awareness of the big picture, feelings of interconnection, and a widening of possibilities. There is a curiosity about the situation, about what is being heard, and what is being understood. Our bodies are open and relaxed. The ability to listen to what is being said and what is not being said is another characteristic of this mode.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>I’d wager that most of us, when we find ourselves in feedback conversations, are listening from personality. And this is when amygdala hijacking kicks in and we internalize feedback instantanesouly. Practicing active listening from a centered place creates space for the conversation and for our own reactions.</p>

<h3 id="step-3-put-the-feedback-on-a-plate">Step 3: Put the feedback on a plate.</h3>

<p>Imagine there is a plate between you and person sharing feedback. As they speak, imagine their words going onto the plate, where you can examine them. This visualization keeps the words external, allows you to see what is being shared, and to look at it more objectively. From this vantage point you can ask clarifying questions, seek to understand what is being shared, and remain grounded and listen from center. Keep the feedback on the plate as the feedback conversation progresses.</p>

<h3 id="step-4-distinguish-between-fact-and-opinion">Step 4: Distinguish between fact and opinion.</h3>

<p>One of the things look for when receiving feedback is opinions masquerading as facts. There is a whole <a href="https://instituteofcoaching.org/blogs/grounding-our-coaching-how-linguistic-coaching-came-be">theory of language</a> around this, but essentially it goes like this: facts are observable and grounded. “It’s 65F degrees outside.” This is a fact. Opinions are interpretations of facts. “It’s warm outside,” and “it’s cold outside,” could both be accurate opinions for the same 65F degree day, depending on a number factors such as where the speaker grew up, body type, quality of circulation, and amount of clothes currently being worn.</p>

<p>In a feedback conversation, this might show up in a comment along the lines of, “you need to speak up more.” Sounds like a fact, doesn’t it? But it’s actually an opinion based on how the speaker interprets the world. With the feedback sitting on the plate in front of you, and having flagged this as an opinion masquerading as a fact, you can now start to ask clarifying questions to understand what the speaker is really trying to say. They probably aren’t asking you to speak just for the sake of hearing yourself talk (although I do know company cultures where this is A Thing), but there is something they think can be solved by sharing their opinion-as-fact. Maybe they spoke to 10 people in other departments and none of them knew what your team was working on. Or maybe they are multi-tasking in meetings and aren’t listening when you speak. Whatever it is, “you need to speak up more,” is not a fact, nor is it very actionable feedback. Once you can see these language constructions in action, it becomes easier to use them as anchors for clarifying conversations.</p>

<h3 id="step-5-step-5-add-a-few-responses-and-gestures-to-your-toolkit">Step 5: Step 5: Add a few responses and gestures to your toolkit.</h3>

<p>It can be useful to have a few go-to phrases and responses at the ready to help create space for processing in the midst of a feedback conversation in order to slow the conversation down, modulate reactivity, and create new possibilities for responding. You might do something like take some really deep breaths while nodding slowly, saying something along the lines of, “This is new information for me and I’m going to need a few moments to process it,” or “I’m really surprised to hear this, can you provide more context?”</p>

<h2 id="sanity-check">Sanity check</h2>

<p>Sometimes we find ourselves receiving feedback from someone who feels very ‘correct’ in their interpretation of the world and gets agitated when you start to ask open and honest questions. This is a tricky situation to be in, and it means that you aren’t going to be in a learning conversation because the other side simply wants to corroborate their opinion of the situation. <em>Do not internalize the feedback they have given you.</em> Leave the feedback on the plate in front of you, thank the person for the feedback, and tell them you will reflect on what they had to share. Find a trusted colleague, a coach, or a peer group to debrief with, and look at the breakdown of facts and opinions. There will likely be a few insights for you, but it might take some work to get at them.</p>

<h2 id="thats-all">That's all!</h2>

<p>It can feel like a lot is at stake when we’re on the receiving end of a feedback conversation. As human beings, we construct interpretations of our world based on our own patterns of observing, acting, reflecting, and understanding. Because we only have access to a small set of facts, we create structures of interpretations that reinforce our personal world view. In a feedback conversation, multiple structures of interpretations are interacting with each other. Great feedback conversations acknowledge this and look for shared outcomes and understanding. Listening from center, keeping feedback on a plate, and paying attention to facts-as-opinions can make the art of receiving feedback much easier, more insightful, and eventually more easeful. So give it a try the next time someone shares feedback with you, and see what happens. Good luck!</p>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Essay] What happens outside the conversation is as important as what happens in it.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/space-for-feedback/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/space-for-feedback/</guid>
				<pubDate>Tue, 12 Jan 2021 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<p>Remember that time someone gave you a gift and you opened it and were like, “oh wow, this person doesn’t know me at all”? Maybe it wasn’t your style (or size), or too flashy, or just totally not anything you’d be into? The type of gift that is more about the person giving it, than about you?</p>

<p class="essay-image-extend"><img src="/images/essays/feedback-gift.jpg" alt="smiley" /></p>
<p class="caption">Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@kadh?utm_source=unsplash&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_content=creditCopyText">Kira auf der Heide</a> on Unsplash</p>

<p>Great feedback, on the other hand, is a gift for both parties. When approached with curiosity, care, and understanding, giving feedback becomes a learning conversation. The first step in doing this skillfully is to drop the idea that feedback is a one way street — that the person giving feedback is “right” and the person receiving feedback is somehow “wrong”. This kind of thinking makes the shittiest of gifts.</p>

<hr class="section-break" />

<h2 id="creating-the-space">Creating the Space</h2>

<p>Okay, so you want to give someone feedback. Maybe someone did something great and you are giving them feedback to celebrate (yay!), but more often than not feedback comes up when something seems to be going off the rails. Before you open your mouth and share whatever happens to be in your head in the moment, pause. Most of the important work giving feedback actually happens before the conversation itself. The following is a check-list I like to run through to make sure I’m creating the right space:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Ground yourself.</strong> Take a few deep breaths and allow yourself to settle into the present moment. What’s happening? Are you feeling reactive or judgmental? Maybe you are feeling anxious? Or perhaps thoughtful and focused? Giving good, clear feedback requires us first to be aware and in control of what’s happening in our inner world. Taking a few moments to ground and connect with ourselves is mandatory for a good feedback conversation.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Get clear on your why.</strong> What’s really driving the desire to provide feedback? Do you want to prove that your own ideas are right, validate your abilities, take someone down a notch? It’s hard to admit, and even harder to do the reflective work to know what we’re really up to, but when we’re feeling reactive or anxious to provide feedback, the underlying motives might be self-serving. If your why is coming from a place of insecurity, go back to step one and ground yourself until you move away from reactivity and can connect to a why that serves a larger purpose.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Embrace curiosity.</strong> You don’t have the full picture. No one has the full picture. It’s just the nature of human perception—we cannot possibly take in all the information and process it, so we select a subset of data to pay attention to that in turn informs our beliefs. Approaching feedback conversations from a posture of learning will help everyone involved understand context, perspectives, and assumptions. Here’s a tip: if you are feeling judgmental, negative, or ready to assign blame, you’re probably not in learning mode.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Understand power dynamics.</strong> In a position of power (especially positional power) being grounded, curious, and open is critical when entering into a feedback conversation. If you are reactive and ready to reinforce your own truth, the person on the receiving end will shut down. At this point, the conversation is no longer about learning and as a leader you’ve just poked yourself in the eye. What could have been a conversation filled with new perspectives and information is now a one-way street and you’re not going to learn anything new. Power dynamics are important to understand even if you aren’t someone’s direct manager. Maybe you’ve been there longer, have a more senior title, are a co-founder, have a lot of influence — whatever it is, be sensitive to power dynamics and if you find yourself reactive or defensive, pause, breathe, and get curious. And if you can’t do that, save the feedback session for another time.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Ask for consent.</strong> Given that we’ve all probably had less-than-wonderful feedback conversations, asking for consent is a kindness that gives the person on the receiving end of the feedback a heads up for what kind of conversation is about to happen. This can be a simple, “Hey, I have some feedback I’d like to share with you. Is that something you can hear right now?” If they are rushing towards a deadline or having a bad day, they may want to reschedule the conversation. Most times people will be open to receiving feedback and can switch into feedback mode, but make sure you ask for consent. The other benefit of asking for consent is that we can clearly signal we are giving feedback. I don’t know how many times I’ve seen people try and give feedback and the other person has no idea they are in a feedback conversation. Be kind, ask for consent. It’s a nice ritual that creates space to shift into a feedback conversation.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Share your feedback.</strong> You are grounded, curious, open. Clear on the purpose of the conversation. Aware of power dynamics. And you’ve asked consent. Now what? There are a number of frameworks that can be used to guide the actual conversation itself. A few I have used over the years: <a href="https://medium.com/@mmeima/life-saving-job-saving-communication-framework-asap-agree-5a458a59cc8">ASAP + Agree</a>, <a href="https://www.ccl.org/articles/leading-effectively-articles/hr-pipeline-a-quick-win-to-improve-your-talent-development-process/">Situation, Behavior, Impact Feedback Model</a>, <a href="https://www.nonviolentcommunication.com/learn-nonviolent-communication/4-part-nvc/">Non-violent Communication</a>, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7qtJ87WTPNY">Issue Clearing</a>. Using a framework might feel awkward at first, but they can be helpful when it comes to keeping the blame game out of the conversation. Until you’ve had a lot of practice with these types of conversations and know how to consistently stay grounded and open, frameworks can be a useful resource to re-orient towards curiosity and learning, even if the conversation gets challenging.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Get clear on what needs to happen moving forward.</strong> You’ve had a great feedback conversation—multiple perspectives and interpretations have been explored, misunderstandings and miscommunications have been clarified, there is a sense of clarity, trust, and understanding that is present—but before you wrap up, be sure you both decide what needs to happen moving forward. This isn’t about detailed action plans and bulleted lists, it’s about knowing you are leaving the conversation with a shared understanding of what’s different and what’s changed. Ideally you’ve both learned something, so what are you going to do with those insights?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Give your sincere thanks.</strong> Share your gratitude for the recipient’s willingness to be open to feedback, and to be willing to explore a learning conversation with you. This sets the tone for future conversations and builds trust. Feedback conversations are so often equated with the feeling of “being in trouble”, so the more we can create a different experience of feedback, the more these types of conversations can happen.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<hr class="section-break" />

<p><em>Good feedback is about curiosity and clear intentions.</em> It doesn’t matter what framework you use (eventually you won’t need to use one!), what matters is that every feedback conversation becomes a learning conversation. If you are willing to engage in a mutual exploration of what is happening, and if you are willing to honor the experiences of others, you’ll find these conversations can become a foundation for trust, growth, and possibility. Best of luck on your feedback journey!</p>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Essay] A closer look at management, leadership, and why it’s important to understand the differences between the two.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/management-and-leadership/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/management-and-leadership/</guid>
				<pubDate>Thu, 03 Sep 2020 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<p>If you’re stepping into a leadership role, chances are you’re also going to be doing a lot of managing. And while it’s true the two overlap quite a bit, understanding the differences can help you be more effective manager, a more inspirational leader, and more successful overall.</p>

<h2 id="on-management">On Management</h2>

<p>Managers are a specific breed of leader, created by the business world to <a href="https://hbr.org/2004/01/managers-and-leaders-are-they-different">guide the destinies</a> of corporate enterprises. They are responsible and accountable for running and <em>managing</em> a part of the business. This might be a division, a department, or a team with a specific mandate. Their power in the organization is bestowed upon them by their position, which is why it’s called positional power. If they weren’t in the position, they wouldn’t have power. When combined with great leadership skills, managers rarely need to rely on <strong>positional power</strong>. Bereft of leadership skills, however, managers with positional power become the thing of nightmares (or New Yorker cartoons).</p>

<p>A few things managers do:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Literally manages a part of the business</li>
  <li>Aligns work with strategy</li>
  <li>Green-lights projects</li>
  <li>In charge of hiring, firing, and promotions</li>
  <li>Responsible for career development</li>
  <li>Writes annual and mid-year reviews</li>
  <li>Manages P&amp;L</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="on-leadership">On Leadership</h2>

<p>Leaders, in organizations or otherwise, have the ability to bring people together; to align, inspire, and empower them towards a common vision. Leaders honor both the work to be done, and the people doing it. Their power doesn’t come from a title, but instead from the relationships they’ve built. <strong>Personal power</strong> is given to leaders by individuals who believe they are worth following and looking to for direction.</p>

<p>Historically, managers weren’t necessarily expected to have great leadership skills or experience. Positional power was enough to get the job done. These days, teams expect their managers to also be great leaders. After all, people don’t leave jobs, they leave managers.</p>

<p>A few things leaders do:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Articulates and embodies vision, values, and purpose</li>
  <li>Creates a sense of inclusion and belonging</li>
  <li>Shows up fully present</li>
  <li>Exhibits emotional and social intelligence</li>
  <li>Actively listens and invites others to the conversation</li>
  <li>Builds meaningful relationships and fosters trust</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="management--leadership-a-continuum">Management &amp; Leadership: A Continuum</h2>

<p>Management and leadership are two sides of the same coin, and it can be helpful to look at them as a continuum.</p>

<p class="essay-image-extend"><img src="/images/essays/management-leadership.png" alt="smiley" /></p>
<p class="caption">American Journal of Pharmaceutical Education 2017; 81(6) Article 102.</p>

<p>The trick is in knowing when to show up as a leader, as a manager, or as both (spoiler alert: it’s usually both). I think this is one of the most challenging things for new managers to learn, especially if they haven’t developed (or aren’t sure of) their leadership style. If you rely too much on positional power, you’ll alienate your team and come across as an autocratic leader. If you rely too much on personal power, you won’t learn how to make authoritative decisions (or build trust in your ability to make those decisions), which will significantly dampen your ability to have an impact on the business.</p>

<p>If you’ve been at this game for a while, you’ve probably developed a pretty nuanced sense for when to lead and when to manage. Even then, it can still be hard to get right!</p>

<h2 id="putting-it-into-practice">Putting It Into Practice</h2>

<p>There are three lenses that can be helpful in trying to triangulate when to lead, and when to manage: <strong>context, possibility, and action</strong>. I’m sure there are hundreds of ways to approach this and would love to learn how other folks think about it. If you are someone who spends cycles on this and are willing to share, PLEASE do (like, right here in the comments, or on Twitter, or in an email, or whatever).</p>

<p><strong>Context:</strong> Context is critical; nothing happens in a vacuum! How much do you know about the context surrounding the situation? Is there a problem?A lack of clarity? Is this within your team or across teams? What will it take to resolve it, who is involved, who is impacted, and what is the urgency? Conversely, is there excitement or a desire to do something new or different? Who do you need to convince? What is at stake?</p>

<p><strong>Possibility:</strong> What solutions or paths are available? What do you already know, what do you need to learn? Who has that information, and who might also have ideas about new possibilities? Is there appetite at the organization for multiple possibilities, or is there pressure to collapse everything into a singular possibility?</p>

<p><strong>Action:</strong> What actions can be taken to bring clarity to the situation or to a resolution/decision? What is within your mandate to do? What needs to be done by others? Do you have the time to remain open to possibilities, or is urgency requiring you to narrow things down? Who is needed to make a decision?</p>

<h2 id="an-example-scenario">An Example Scenario</h2>

<p>A new project has been green-lit for research and development. A cross-functional team has been assigned, including two members from your team who are expected to commit about 60% of their time to early exploration, alongside their day to day responsibilities. The project lead is excited (maybe a little too excited) about the potential of this new project and considers themselves a mini-CEO of the initiative. They (the project lead) begin to assign your team tasks well outside what is in scope for the project, they create silos which leads to a lack of transparency and communication, and they make promises to early clients with time frames and schedules that haven’t been backed up by other members of the team. Your team is frustrated, losing morale, and unsure of what to do.</p>

<p><em><strong>Context, possibility, action:</strong></em></p>

<p><strong>Context:</strong> A project is starting to go off the rails, your team is being impacted, and while you aren’t part of the day to day operations of this project, a big part of its early success relies on your team, and therefor you. Your team is obviously feeling the pain of this, but so is the larger project team, and the organization who is relying on this project to grow the business.</p>

<p><strong>Possibility:</strong> There are a number of possibilities in front of you: finding a way to get the cross-functional team to work together, doing some issue clearing, continuing with the status quo, creating more boundaries and silos and just stitching together the output of each person on the team (in order to avoid confrontation), or just letting the project go off the tracks entirely.</p>

<p><strong>Action:</strong> The situation demands urgency because of the importance of the project, and how people are being impacted. You have the mandate to determine what your team works on, but you don’t have mandate over the entire project. You don’t want to lose anyone, the project is important to the company, and there are a lot of complicating factors to consider.</p>

<p><em><strong>Where do you lead, and where do you manage?</strong></em></p>

<p><strong>Lead:</strong> Work with your team, teaching them frameworks and tactics for having difficult conversations. Help them process their experiences, understand their own contribution to the situation, and generate new approaches and behaviors that will open up new possibilities and ways of working. Also use leadership to foster your relationship with the project lead — spend some time with them to understand their perspective, the purpose behind their actions, and what’s blocking the team.</p>

<p><strong>Manage:</strong> This is where you exercise positional power with the project lead (though they don’t report to you, their behavior is directly impacting your team) — you need to approve what your team works on and all requests for work must run though you (make sure your team understands this as well). This removes the burden of unnecessary work being assigned and gives your team breathing room to focus on the work that needs to be done. But remember! Positional power without a side of leadership often comes off as autocratic, and you could risk impacting your relationship with the project lead. Tread carefully.</p>

<h2 id="okay-got-it-now-what">Okay, Got It. Now What?</h2>

<h3 id="keep-a-journal">Keep a Journal</h3>

<p>The best way to start to understand your own ways of leading and managing, uncover blind spots, and get a sense of your leadership style, is to keep a journal. For example, at the end of each day quickly reflect on where you lead, where you managed, and what you learned. Did you face a particularly complex and challenging situation? Jot down the context, possibilities, and actions. Which ones call for leadership, and which ones for management? After a few weeks, you’ll start to see patterns that can be great learning material for further personal and professional development.</p>

<h3 id="and-remember-its-a-balance">And Remember, It’s a Balance</h3>

<p>Day to day, the role of leadership and management blur together. As we move between tasks, meetings, and conversations we sit somewhere in the middle of the leadership &lt;-&gt; management continuum, instinctually moving across it based on our own combination of experience, training, and self-awareness. But every so often it can be beneficial to pause and reflect on the differences between the two, examining our own ways of showing up as managers and leaders. Maintaining the right balance of personal and positional power can make all the difference.</p>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

			<item>
        <title>[Essay] On the overlap between experiential learning and designing.</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/learning-through-worldmaking/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com/writing/essays/learning-through-worldmaking/</guid>
				<pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2019 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


				<description>
					<![CDATA[
						<blockquote>
  <p>“There is no better way to gain an understanding of something than by designing it.” — Russell Ackoff</p>
</blockquote>

<p>A while back, I casually dropped an <a href="https://medium.com/@pnts/reflections-on-business-design-and-value-bb398cada721">alternative framing of design</a> as a way of learning. My intent was to articulate the activities of design, decoupled from the technics of craft, to explore how we can bring our understanding of design to business. In the intervening months, I’ve gone deeper with this framing, pulling from several theories and connecting a few more dots to help articulate the why of design as a way of learning, and to examine what makes it different.</p>

<p>As design evolves beyond a consideration of objects to answer the challenges of the 21st century, it is essential to understand what design brings to the table well beyond the current framing of design as problem solving. When we look at design as a way of learning, we expand the possibilities of where design can go and what design can do. What is unique to the designerly way of learning is that it involves making, crafting in conversation with the world in order to understand and shape it. This article serves as a snapshot of my current thinking, weaving theories and explorations into a sense of what design is and why it matters.</p>

<hr class="section-break" />

<h2 id="designing-as-reflection-in-action">Designing as Reflection-in-action</h2>

<p>Donald Schön’s work in professional education gives us insight into how learning happens in the process of working with the materials of a situation. While observing architecture students working in the studio tradition, Schön conceptualized the practice of design as a specific kind of inquiry that he called reflection-in-action; a “reflective conversation with the materials of the design situation (<a href="https://www.colorado.edu/ftep/sites/default/files/attached-files/ftep_memo_to_faculty_2.pdf">The Architectural Studio as an Exemplar of Education for Reflection in Action</a>, p. 5)”. In this configuration, knowing and making are intricately linked, as in the example of a studio master simultaneously drawing and talking in order to help a student explore some of the challenges she is facing with her own work.</p>

<p>Familiar yet abstract, this is the more tangible side of design that we experience through artifact creation and making things. In <a href="https://mitpress.mit.edu/books/design-unbound-designing-emergence-white-water-world-volume-1">Design Unbound</a>, Ann Pendleton-Julian and John Seely Brown outline this idea in a discussion of rapid iteration, stating “what is unique to design… is the capacity to think and act fluidly, not just as a repetition of sequences of thinking, acting, and prototyping but as a complex web of interaction between cognitive activity as both reasoning and imagination, and acts of making/doing to create meaningful things and context that have agency in and on a white water world. (p. 88)” Reflection-in-action invites practitioners to change the situation at hand and reshape what they are doing while they are doing it. Making is an essential part of action, usually taking the form of an artifact with its own meaning and coherence.</p>

<p class="essay-image-extend"><img src="/images/essays/reflection-in-action.png" alt="smiley" /></p>

<p>The artifacts a designer crafts in the ongoing process of reflection-in-action can be abstract or concrete; concept maps, prototypes, conversations, sketches, models, etc. Historically more attention has been given to material products and goods, but abstract artifacts are often employed in the composition of a process or system. In creating artifacts and placing them in the world—an act of transforming experiences—the designer engages in an ongoing process of reflection-in-action, manipulating the artifact and experiencing the outcomes of those changes. Herold Nelson and Erik Stolterman have a wonderful passage in <a href="https://mitpress.mit.edu/books/design-way-second-edition">The Design Way</a> that illuminates this process:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“The way design ideas are brought into the world, as crafted material, is a critical part of the design process. Producing good designs requires building successful interrelationships and interconnections with the material of the real world. As the world speaks back, joining the designer in a dialogue, we move out of a polarity between objectivity and the subjectivity into a holistic interrelationship. That which is being innovated is part of the material process itself. When a design is brought into the world, there is no longer a distinction between that-which-is and the not-yet-existing. In this conjunction, we see the real nature of our designs and how they become a part of the world. (p. 176)”</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="design-as-sensemaking">Design as Sensemaking</h2>

<p>While Schön’s theories of reflective practices illuminate how designers move from indeterminate situations to determinate ones, they are less clear on how <em>understanding</em> happens. If design studio practice is centered around “the relationship between changing things and understanding”, how does that understanding unfold?</p>

<p>Humans are meaning-makers by design. To get a sense of how understanding happens, I looked to Brenda Dervin’s <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/19970710233153/http://communication.sbs.ohio-state.edu/sense-making/lit/1983_4.html">theory of sense-making</a>. Coming from the field of communication studies, sense-making describes a process of continuous dialogue with a situation through which we arrive at stable, although limited and tentative, observations or facts. Sense-making’s core assumption is that “reality is neither complete nor constant but rather filled with fundamental and pervasive discontinuities or gaps (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/19970710233153/http://communication.sbs.ohio-state.edu/sense-making/lit/1983_4.html">p.4</a>).” It is the process of dealing with those gaps, the “constructing” activities of information seeking, that we come to some sense of understanding (this works at both individual and collective levels). Said another way, sense-making highlights our ability as humans to “circle phenomena from various perspectives… [providing] the means for us to arrive at a more comprehensive, more fully informed, potentially more useful understanding of the situation (<a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/sense-making-methodology-reader-selected-writings-of-brenda-dervin/oclc/51871729">p. 7</a>).”</p>

<p class="essay-image-extend"><img src="/images/essays/sense-making.png" alt="smiley" /></p>

<p>What’s important about sense-making, especially in understanding the meta-activities of design, is that it cedes the idea of an objective reality and assumes there is no “neutral” observing. When we design, we are in the situation we seek to understand, becoming the “maker of ideas of situations (<a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/sense-making-methodology-reader-selected-writings-of-brenda-dervin/oclc/51871729">p.67</a>).” The gap-bridging process involves both in-the-head and physical activities of making ideas, using strategies, connecting, sources, choosing words, etc. While Dervin doesn’t use the language of ‘thinking’ and ‘feeling’ in her own work, she does look at the interplay of situational and psychological experiences, the interconnectedness of inner and outer worlds of human existence, which I used to inform the mapping above. In sense-making humans are seen in through their experience-in-the-world, “as a body-mind-heart-spirit moving through time and space, with a past history, present reality, and future dreams or ambitions ( <a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/sense-making-methodology-reader-selected-writings-of-brenda-dervin/oclc/51871729">p.7</a>).” Embodied thinking and feeling captures the essence of the human in the sense-making process, bridging gaps to create meaning and understanding.</p>

<h2 id="sense-making--reflection-in-action">Sense-making + Reflection-in-action</h2>

<p class="essay-image-extend"><img src="/images/essays/learning-cycle.png" alt="smiley" /></p>

<p>If you combine Schön’s reflection-in-action with Dervin’s sense-making along two different axes, you get what looks like the Experiential Learning Cycle—a process of transforming experience into knowledge. This transformation takes place in cycles that involve two dialectics:</p>

<ol>
  <li>concrete experience (<em>feeling</em>) and abstract conceptualization (<em>thinking</em>)</li>
  <li>reflective observation (<em>reflecting</em>) and active experimentation (<em>acting</em>)</li>
</ol>

<p>Feeling and thinking are grouped together in a dialectic of “grasping experience”, while reflecting and acting comprise the “transforming experience” dialectic. Everyone goes through these cycles in the process of learning, but how you resolve the dialectics is indicative of your learning style. In Kolb’s words, “Integrated learning is a process involving a <em>creative tension</em> among the four learning modes that is responsive to contextual demands [emphasis added].”</p>

<p>If you couldn’t tell from my added emphasis, there is something very interesting in the creative tensions that exist within the learning cycle because it starts to point to <em>tension</em> as a locus of creativity, rather than design itself. It’s a subtle nuance, but useful in that we can see the tensions design methods utilize—constraints, ambiguity, sense-making, divergence, convergence, etc. foster creativity, but we can also see where those tensions exist in other fields. The history of humanity is bursting with creativity well outside the realm of design.</p>

<p>There is something unique about design as a way of learning, however, in that design is interested in what could be, rather than what is. Herbert Simon (1969) and Richard Buchanan’s (1992) assertion that the difference between science and design is that “design thinking deals primarily with what <em>does not yet exist</em>,” while science “seeks to explain <em>what is</em>.” Science discovers, design invents. Where science works to uncover an objective world, design brings forth multiple worlds simultaneously.</p>

<h2 id="worldmaking">Worldmaking</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Worldmaking as we know it always starts from worlds already on hand; the making is a remaking.” — Nelson Goodman</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Worldmaking refers to the ways we collectively make the spaces we inhabit through symbolic practices. The human drive towards meaning-making leads us to unconsciously build our world from social conditioning, scientific rationality, artistic traditions, and our own struggle for survival. In this context, worldmaking is an acknowledgment of the interpretive frames and practices that we create our worlds through rather than an assessment of the fundamental nature of physical reality. Damian Cox makes sense of this in the following way:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Goodman’s worldmaking is a disciplined business. We do not always make worlds when we manipulate symbols. Worldmaking is constrained by coherence, consistency, the fit with intuitive judgement and intelligible purpose and these virtues add up to what Goodman calls the “rightness” of a version. Right versions make worlds, and are produced by many different kinds of people. Scientists create worlds; philosophers create worlds; artists create worlds; an advertising agency might create a world. World’s are the product of any ambitious, successful attempt to create an order of things (“<a href="https://www.academia.edu/6111032/Goodman_and_Putnam_on_the_Making_of_Worlds">Goodman and Putnam on the Making of Worlds</a> p. 36”).</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Design makes worldmaking visible, transforming it into a conscious act through intentionality, awareness, and an interest in the ways in which the world could be. In the process of articulating these worlds, the things that we make—the nouns—are expressions and references to the underlying logic of the world in creation. Worldmaking in some ways could be considered the essence of design experimentation, something Schön pointed to in his discussion of virtual worlds. For the designer, the ability to “construct and manipulate virtual worlds is a crucial component to his ability not only to perform artistically but to experiment rigorously (<a href="https://www.thriftbooks.com/w/educating-the-reflective-practitioner-toward-a-new-design-for-teaching-and-learning-in-the-professions-higher-education-series_donald-a-schn/272745/?mkwid=s0GErMpGO%7Cdc&amp;pcrid=70112878392&amp;pkw=&amp;pmt=&amp;plc=&amp;pgrid=21323665512&amp;ptaid=pla-292616666626&amp;gclid=EAIaIQobChMI0sf2qNnV4wIVg56fCh0K7ggXEAQYAyABEgK0o_D_BwE#isbn=1555420257&amp;idiq=8790061">p. 75</a>).”</p>

<p>Going back to the idea of materials, Nelson Goodman offers a subset of methods that contribute to worldmaking: composition and decomposition, weighting, ordering, deletion &amp; supplementation, and deformation. Pairing this with H. Nelson and Stolterman’s articulation that “materials are what a designer brings together using structural connections or compositional relationships (p. 174),” and keeping in mind that materials are not limited to the physical, we start to get a curious inclination of how broad the meta-activities of design can go.</p>

<p>Design is a dynamic and unending cycle of grasping and transforming experience through the process of worldmaking. When coupled with the technics of design as craft, we can see worlds emerge through our experience of a brand, a service, or a product tied together through the logic of business in an invitation to a certain way of being. But we can move into other areas with different materials—business, organizations, governments, policy—and begin to use design to bring forth new worlds and possibilities.</p>

<hr class="section-break" />

<p>In the 20th century design, tightly coupled with craft, combined intentionality and human-centered practices to create things that people valued. The challenges of the 21st century invite us to move beyond things and to design for complexity and emergence. In order to do this we must move our work to higher levels of perception, applying the fluidity of thinking, acting, and understanding to our conversations with indeterminate situations. My specific interest is in how the activities of design can inform the practice of worldmaking in organizations, exploring new ways of working that facilitate flourishing at the individual, company, and societal levels. Beyond business, the importance of design as learning through worldmaking configures design as a meta-cognitive activity through which we explore and bring forth new possibilities in any domain. Attuned to ideas of what could be, design is the way by which we consciously move through reflection-in-action and sense-making in order to bring forth new worlds.</p>

					]]>
				</description>
			</item>

  </channel>
</rss>
