<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"

	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	>

  <channel>
  	<title>Words Make Worlds</title>
    <atom:link href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <link>https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <generator>Middleman (Ruby)</generator>
    <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>
		<description>A publication about the art, science, and craft of the Coaching Leadership Style. Sent bi-weekly, Words Make Worlds delivers insight and practices to increase leadership impact.</description>
		<meta property="og:image" content="https://methodandmatter.com/images/mm-round.png" />
    <image>
      <url>https://methodandmatter.com/images/mm-round.png</url>
      <title>method &#038; matter</title>
      <link>https://methodandmatter.com</link>
    </image>



      <item>
        <title>Ending Well</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com//words-make-worlds/013/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com//words-make-worlds/013/</guid>
        <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


        <description>
          <![CDATA[
            <p>Welcome to 🪐 <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds">Words Make Worlds</a>, a newsletter dedicated to the art, science, and craft of the Coaching Leadership Style. In this issue we come to the final stage of the coaching process: ending well.  If you are just joining us (hi!) you can catch up previous issues in the series here:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds/009/">Issue 9: The Coaching Process</a>. Provides an overview of the coaching process and introduces the “What? — So what? — Now what?” framework.</li>
  <li><a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds/010/">Issue 10: Noticing and Exploring</a>. A deeper dive into the “What?” part of the cycle and what it takes to facilitate deeper thinking and awareness in others.</li>
  <li><a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds/011/">Issue 11: Reflection and Meaning Making</a>. An exploration of the “So What?” part of the cycle and the importance of making new meaning from what was uncovered in the noticing and exploring phase.</li>
  <li><a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds/012/">Issue 12: Taking Action</a>. Coaching is effective because it combines self-awareness with taking action. Without action there is no coaching conversation. This is what the “Now What?” phase is all about.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-idea">The Idea</h2>
<blockquote>
  <p>To maintain a thinking space where transformation is possible, the end needs to be as much in partnership as the beginning. You co-created the space between you and have done the work together. Co-create the end. - Claire Pedrick</p>
</blockquote>

<p>We’ve now covered the entire arc of the coaching conversation, from raising awareness to making meaning to taking new action. While the majority of your time will usually be spent in the “What?” phase of noticing and building awareness, how you start and how you end are critical compontents of impactful learning and clear commitments.</p>

<p>It can be easy to breeze past beginnings and endings, and in normal conversations we often do. From my work with students in the <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/leader-as-coach/">Leader as Coach</a> course I’ve come to understand that it can feel redundant or awkward to start with intentional structure <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds/007/">at the beginning of a conversation</a> — the “flow” isn’t there which can feel unnatural. <em>And yet</em>, starting with clear intentions and a core set of questions that define the boundaries of the coaching container jumpstarts the thinking process for the person being coached. It helps them to identify what really matters and what change they want to see. It sets the parameters and purpose of the conversation. With a clearly defined container the coaching conversation can flow in a focused and supportive way.</p>

<p>The same goes for endings, where again it can feel awkward to bring structure to reflections and learnings. It can be easy to assume that just because both people experienced the same conversation they each have the same understanding and takeaways. <em>And yet</em>, what two people experience in the same conversation can be wildly different. Asking the person being coached to reflect on their experience, learning, insights, and commitments is a chance to create radical clarity and mutual understanding around what happened and what comes next.</p>

<p>The entire process of “What? — So what? — Now what?” takes place inside a container created by a good opening and concluded with a clear ending. A good opening sets the field of play and defines the learning objective, while a clear ending reinforces new insights and ensures the conversation is complete.</p>

<p>Good endings are also important because most of the learning happens outside the coaching conversation, where insights are applied through action. By ending the conversation with intention and structure you set the stage for what comes next, creating small steps to build forward momentum.</p>

<h2 id="the-practice">The Practice</h2>
<p>For endings I like to use Claire Pedrick’s CALF framework.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>C</strong>ontract: Make sure that the agreements you set at the beginning of the conversation have been met and that you have done what you set out to do. You can say something like, “Circling back to where we began, what is different now? How did we do?”</li>
  <li><strong>A</strong>ccountability: Coaching conversations are in service of the person being coached, and the accountability resides with them on what they will do next.  A simple, “Where do you need to be accountable?” may be enough. I also find that in a work environment where the manager needs to stay informed of progress, “What will you do by when, and how will you let me know?” can be effective.</li>
  <li><strong>L</strong>earning: Reflecting on the key learnings helps imprint them in memory and facilitates the active of work of synthesis and integration. “What are you learning?” or “What stands out to you?” are simple ways to bring this out.</li>
  <li><strong>F</strong>inished: Are you actually finished? Is there anything else that might be lingering that wants attention but hasn’t been shared yet? “Have we finished?” or “Is that enough for today?” or “Does that feel complete?” are solid closing questions.</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h2 id="quotes-i-3">Quotes I &lt;3</h2>
<blockquote>
  <p>The best coaches make us recognize we have gaps in our reasoning. The moment we become unsure of what we know, learning happens. This is good coaching. — Marcia Reynolds</p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<p>Thank you for being here and for bringing coaching into your leadership practice.</p>

<p>Until next time,</p>

<p>Andi</p>

          ]]>
        </description>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Taking Action</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com//words-make-worlds/012/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com//words-make-worlds/012/</guid>
        <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2024 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


        <description>
          <![CDATA[
            <p>🎊 Happy New Year 🎊, and welcome to <strong>Issue 12</strong> of <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds/">Words Make Worlds</a>, where we continue our journey through the coaching process framework with a look at what happens in the “Now What?” part of the cycle. If you are new here (welcome!) you can quickly catch up by checking out <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds/009/">Issue 9: The Coaching Process</a>, <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds/010/">Issue 10: Noticing and Exploring</a>, and <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds/011/">Issue 11: Reflection and Meaning Making</a>.</p>

<p>If you don’t have time to make it to the end of the newsletter I have two announcements I don’t want you to miss: 1) I am hosting a <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/feedback/">free webinar on January 9th</a> on giving better feedback and 2) Leader as Coach has a <a href="https://maven.com/andrea-mignolo/leader-as-coach">new cohort launching on January 15th</a> - come join us!</p>

<p>And with that, let's get on with the issue.</p>

<h2 id="the-idea">The Idea</h2>
<blockquote>
  <p>“When clients experience a new insight, they feel as if a door has opened to a new way of seeing. They have yet to walk through the door.”  - Marcia Reynolds, <a href="https://bookshop.org/p/books/coach-the-person-not-the-problem-a-guide-to-using-reflective-inquiry-marcia-reynolds/13045008?ean=9781523087839">Coach the Person, Not the Problem</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>By now you’ve gotten a sense of how coaching conversations slow things down so that people can explore and reflect on their experience, a key part of the <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds/010/">noticing and exploring phase</a>. The usefulness of this coaching move is that it asks people to critically assess and make visible what they think is going on and what assumptions, limiting beliefs, biases, and other factors might be at play. It guides them to look under the surface at what is going on in their inner world, wonder about what might be going on in others, and  think about what might be happening systemically that is contributing to the issue or situation they are exploring with you. The net result of raising awareness is an increase in the amount of information you have available for the next phase of the coaching process: <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds/011/">meaning making</a>.</p>

<p>Meaning making is where you look at everything you have uncovered together and ask, “What sense can we make of all of this? What patterns are emerging? What from the past does this bring to mind? What no longer feels true? What new stories are emerging?” Meaning making is an act of knowledge creation — it is the process of developing new understanding and new ways of seeing so that the person being coached begins to experience themselves, their colleagues, and the situation in new ways.</p>

<p>Okay, so you’ve increased awareness, surfaced new information, and made some meaning from what you’ve discovered. Now what? Precisely! The “Now What?” phase of the cycle brings us to the part of the conversation where new commitments are made towards future actions. Remember, it isn’t a coaching conversation if it doesn’t lead to action! The transformative power of coaching is both in the new knowledge it creates and how it asks people to <em>apply</em> that knowledge directly in the real world.</p>

<p>Action might look like:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Role playing or trying something new during the session.</li>
  <li>Engaging in additional reflection after the session</li>
  <li>Conducting self-observation throughout the week in service of ongoing awareness</li>
  <li>Trying something new after the conversation is over</li>
</ul>

<p>Be sure that the person you are working with chooses the action they want to take (within reason - if you are their manager and see them choosing action that will clearly backfire or misses the mark of organizational goals, then put some guardrails in place). This encourages ownership of the learning journey and taps into intrinsic motivation tied to personal and professional goals.</p>

<h2 id="the-practice">The Practice</h2>
<p>You want to move into application questions after the person you are working with has some kind of shift in perspective or ah-ha moment. This is critical to create an opening for <em>new</em> actions and behaviors — without the necessary perspective shift any commitments to action will be a rehash of the same behaviors that created the issue in the first place. Here are some questions that can facilitate commitments to future action in the “Now What?” part of the conversation:</p>

<ul>
  <li>What will you do now?</li>
  <li>How could you make this happen?</li>
  <li>What new ideas do you have on how to get there?</li>
  <li>What feels possible now that wasn’t before?</li>
  <li>What might get in the way?</li>
  <li>Given what you have uncovered, what will you do differently?</li>
  <li>How could you improve the situation?</li>
  <li>What are some other approaches to consider?</li>
  <li>What is another option?</li>
  <li>What could you do to bring everything back in alignment?</li>
  <li>Where haven’t you looked for a solution yet?</li>
  <li>What’s the solution you’ve been too scared to try?</li>
  <li>If you were to create an ideal situation, what is your goal? How would it work?</li>
</ul>

<p>You may find that the person you are coaching isn’t sure what to do next. In this case, spend some time brainstorming together around what new actions might be possible. Once you’ve come up with a list, ask them to select the one or two that feel most applicable and doable.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="webinar-from-conflict-to-connection">Webinar: From Conflict to Connection</h2>
<p>On January 9th at 11:30am Pacific Time I’ll be hosting a free webinar on using feedback to deepen trust, strengthen relationships, and build a culture of learning. Interested? <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/feedback/">Learn more and sign up here</a>!</p>

<p><img src="/images/zoom-announcement-feedback.png" alt="image announcement for webinar From Conflict to Connection" /></p>

<hr />

<h2 id="leader-as-coach">Leader as Coach</h2>
<p>A new cohort is launching on January 15th and there are still a few spaces open! If you are looking to kick of 2024 with a new/expanded approach to your leadership practice, this is the course for you! You can learn more about the course, including a peek at the syllabus, <a href="https://maven.com/andrea-mignolo/leader-as-coach">over on Maven</a>.</p>

<p><img src="/images/og/leader-as-coach-2.png" alt="image announcement for Leader as Coach" /></p>

<hr />

<h2 id="quotes-i-">Quotes I ❤️</h2>
<blockquote>
  <p>It may not be quite so obvious in those short, informal, coach-like conversations that a team leader has with a direct report, but the potential is there for valuable and lasting impact. For leaders, this approach accesses a mind-set that includes a focus on both results (action) and on growth (learning). This is, fundamentally, the role of leadership; both lenses are essential. Every initiative and every issue that arises is an opportunity for team members to learn in the process of taking action. At the same time, it is a way for leaders to develop their leadership eyesight: seeing those opportunities. - <a href="https://bookshop.org/p/books/co-active-coaching-the-proven-framework-for-transformative-conversations-at-work-and-in-life-karen-kimsey-house/7897923?ean=9781473674981">Co-Active Coaching, Fourth Edition</a></p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<p>That’s all for this issue! I hope the new year is starting off brightly with focus, hope, and purpose. If you are looking for an exercise to facilitate reflection on the past year and commitments for the year ahead, checkout “<a href="https://methodandmatter.com/essays/end-of-a-cycle/">At the End of a Cycle,</a>” the process I use for my own yearly (and quarterly) reflections.</p>

<p>Until next time,</p>

<p>Andi</p>

          ]]>
        </description>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Reflection and Meaning Making</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com//words-make-worlds/011/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com//words-make-worlds/011/</guid>
        <pubDate>Mon, 11 Dec 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


        <description>
          <![CDATA[
            <p>Welcome to 🌍 <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds">Words Make Worlds</a>, Issue 11! I’m <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/about">Andi</a>, and this week we continue our journey through the stages of the coaching process, taking a look at the role of reflection and meaning making in a coaching conversation (the “So What?” part of the process model). If you are just joining us you might want to start with <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds/009/">Issue 9 - The Coaching Process</a> and then check out <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds/010/">Issue 10 - Noticing and Exploring</a>.</p>

<h2 id="the-idea">The Idea</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Reflection, a key aspect of coaching, involves helping the individual stop and remember the action in which they have been engaged, think through the details, consider what worked and what did not work and consider the causes and implications of the same. Reflection seems to be most effective when done in the presence of others.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>A quick summary of where we’re at in the coaching process: you’ve set the focus of the conversation, you’ve done some exploration work to facilitate deeper awareness, and you’ve widened the field of inquiry to invite new perspectives by using open and honest questions. The conversation so far has shed light on the underlying dynamics, assumptions, or perceptions that supports the current behavior of the person you are working with, behavior they may want to change. Essentially what you have done up to this point is to increase the amount of <em>information</em> available to be used as material in the coaching conversation.</p>

<p>What do you do with all of this new information? You facilitate a process of reflection and meaning making, creating space for the person you are working with to make new connections and insights from what they have uncovered. This is the “So What?” part of the process where people conceptually process what they are learning from the experience - both the experience itself and the new awareness that has been created through exploring the experience. Where they can make sense of what has happened and give it meaning. This is a crucial part of the process because meaning making is what transforms experience into learning.</p>

<p>As meaning making takes place, new stories emerge about how the person you are working with understands themselves, their relationships with the people around them, and their own role in creating the opportunities and outcomes they long for. The creation of new stories loosens the grip of the old ones, revealing them for what they are - stories rather than truths. Over time these new stories influence how a person experiences themselves, their colleagues, and their work. They invite new ways of thinking, doing, and being. Stories become recipes for structuring experience and meaning making is foundation on which new possibilities emerge.</p>

<h2 id="the-practice">The Practice</h2>
<p>We covered some questions for the “So What?” phase of the cycle, and I’ll add a few new ones since we are explicitly focusing on reflection and meaning making this issue. The key idea to keep in mind here is that as a coach you are asking questions and creating space for the person you are working with to bring new insight and meaning to the information you have uncovered in the exploration phase.</p>

<ul>
  <li>What sense are you making of this?</li>
  <li>How is your understanding of the situation changing?</li>
  <li>What feels important in all of this?</li>
  <li>What makes this important?</li>
  <li>What does this mean to you?</li>
  <li>What feels different?</li>
  <li>What are you discovering about yourself? Others? - The situation?</li>
  <li>What habitual patterns are you noticing?</li>
  <li>What does this remind you of?</li>
  <li>What would you like to be different?</li>
  <li>What still needs to be considered/included?</li>
  <li>What new meaning is beginning to emerge?</li>
  <li>What is the story you are telling yourself now?</li>
</ul>

<p>Meaning making questions support another person to question their assumptions, reframe their perspective, and see the situation in new ways. They illustrate the ways in which we mistake our <em>interpretation</em> of how things are as truth, and invite a deeper consideration of what else might be happening. Words make worlds, and when we step into meaning making with another person we create the space for new meaning and new worlds to emerge.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="quotes-i-3">Quotes I &lt;3</h2>
<blockquote>
  <p>“Coaching is a way of being, listening, asking, and speaking that draws out and augments characteristics and potential that are already present in a person. An effective coaching relationship creates a safe and challenging environment in which learning can take place. Coaches know that an oak tree already exists within an acorn. They have seen the one grow into the other, over time and under the right conditions, and are committed to providing those conditions to the best of their abilities. Successful coaches continually learn how best to “farm” the potential they are given to nurture.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>— Tim Gallowey, “<a href="https://thesystemsthinker.com/the-inner-game-of-work-building-capability-in-the-workplace/">The Inner Game of Work: Building Capability in the Workplace</a>”</p>

<hr />

<p>As always, thank you for being here. If you have a moment hit reply ↩️ - I’d love to hear how you are integrating coaching into your leadership practice at work or what you’d love to have me cover in future issues. See you in a few weeks!</p>

          ]]>
        </description>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Noticing and Exploring</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com//words-make-worlds/010/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com//words-make-worlds/010/</guid>
        <pubDate>Sun, 26 Nov 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


        <description>
          <![CDATA[
            <p>Welcome to <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds/">Words Make Worlds</a>, a newsletter dedicated to the art, science, and craft of the Coaching Leadership Style. Coaching is a leadership skill that works beautifully alongside two other necessary and critical executive capacities: leading and managing. Used intentionally, coaching acts as a leadership multiplier that deepens trust, increases accountability, and unleashes potential, resulting in high performing cultures and teams.</p>

<p>Last issue we took a high level overview of <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds/009/">The Coaching Process</a>, introducing the “What? - So What? - Now What?” framework. In the next three issues we’ll be looking at each phase of the process in more detail, starting this week with “What?” And remember, for the coaching conversation to be successful it is important to first take the time to <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds/007/">begin together</a>.</p>

<p class="caption"><img src="/images/wmw/process-framework.png" alt="the process framework" />
Process Framework for Enabling Action, via Dorothy Strachan</p>

<h2 id="what-aka-noticing-and-exploring">What? Aka Noticing and Exploring</h2>

<p>The majority of work you do in a coaching conversation will be in the “What?” phase of the cycle, which is often referred to as the exploration phase. This is where you work with another person to facilitate a deeper awareness of the issue they have brought to the coaching conversation. To increase their ability to see beyond the edges of their current interpretation, to uncover habitual patterns of thinking and doing that are contributing to what is happening, and to connect with an inner knowing and resourcefulness that enables a different way of relating to the issue at hand.</p>

<p>Increasing awareness is a unique aspect of coaching conversations and one of the reasons they can be so powerful. In normal conversations we are quick to identify problems and leap to action, behavior that is frequently rewarded in organizational settings. But this quickness can reinforce biases and keep us running the same old fixes over and over, leading us to wonder why we keep getting the same results and nothing seems to change.</p>

<p>To get different results you need new ways of thinking and seeing, which is what awareness building is all about — facilitating a deeper understanding that creates a wider range of possibility, leading to new ways of responding and taking action. An important distinction to be aware of is that coaching isn’t about problems, it’s about <em>solutions</em>.  Problems are about what is wrong, whereas solutions are about what could be better.</p>

<h3 id="stop-helping">Stop Helping</h3>
<p>Now, I’m going to say something really important and counterintuitive: in your role as coach the best way to help the other person is to <em>not help</em>. I actually assign this as homework in Week 1 of the <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/leader-as-coach/">Leader as Coach</a> program and people meet the assignment with a bit of incredulity and suspicion, wondering <em>“Isn’t that what we are supposed to do as managers? To help our team, to get them unstuck, to run interference, and make sure they can do what we hired them to do?</em> Yes, <em>and</em>… if you truly want to support the development and growth of another person, hold them with <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds/005/">unconditional positive regard</a> and trust that with some space to think and open questions to facilitate that thinking, they will come up with their own insights, answers, and next steps.</p>

<p>I always refer to Rachel Remen when discussing the challenge with helping because she <a href="https://www.awakin.org/v2/read/view.php?tid=127">says it so clearly and beautifully</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Helping is based on inequality, it's not a relationship between equals. When you help, you use your own strength to help someone with less strength. It's a one up, one down relationship, and people feel this inequality. When we help, we may inadvertently take away more than we give, diminishing the person's sense of self-worth and self-esteem.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So instead of helping, think of serving — in the role of coach you work in service of increasing awareness, insights, possibility, and action in another person, serving their own inner wisdom and knowing. This also requires that you hold back on sharing your experience, opinions, and advice. The shift from helping to serving is often an “ah-ha” moment for leaders who are learning to coach. They realize how much effort they have been putting in to conversations and how exhausting it is to hold more than 100% of the responsibility. Leaning back and taking a serving role, the conversation becomes more equal. Leaders often report that by doing less in these conversations they have more energy <em>and</em> get feedback that the conversation was powerful, facilitating new insights, learnings, and possibilities for the person being coached.</p>

<h3 id="coach-the-person-not-the-issue">Coach the Person, Not the Issue</h3>
<p>Another critical aspect of exploring is to remember that you are coaching the person, not the issue. This is a common maxim in many coaching programs that turns the typical management approach on its head. We are used to stepping into a work conversation and focusing on an issue, working with our direct report or colleague to figure out the best path forward. In coaching conversations the issue is secondary to the <em>person</em> you are working with. As a coach, you are a facilitator of their learning, supporting them to think about the issue in new ways. To do this, your questions need to invoke reflection, awareness, and new understanding <em>for them</em>. If you catch yourself asking questions related to the issue (e.g. going down a path of collecting more information so you can understand the issue better) stop yourself and refocus on the person in front of you.</p>

<p>A side note here: once you make this adjustment, you’ll find that you can often have impactful coaching conversations in a relatively short amount of time. This is because you aren’t wasting time getting all the details about what is going on, who said what, and what happened when. It really doesn’t matter. What does matter is how the person you are coaching is thinking about the issue and what deeper insights are available through <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds/008/">open and honest questions</a>.</p>

<h2 id="the-practice">The Practice</h2>
<p>The practice this week is short and sweet, combining several of the skills and approaches we have covered in previous issues. In your conversations over the new couple of weeks, remember practice the following:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Work to increase awareness (see <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds/009/">Issue 9</a>, specifically the section on “Noticing" questions).</li>
  <li>Stop helping.</li>
  <li><a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds/006/">Get curious</a>.</li>
  <li>Focus on facilitating learning.</li>
  <li>Coach the person, not the issue.</li>
  <li>Practice asking <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds/008/">open and honest questions</a>.</li>
</ul>

<p>Keep a journal where you can note what you are learning and the impact the conversations are having on yourself, your team, and the wider organization.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="leader-as-coach">Leader as Coach</h2>

<p>If you are interested in taking your coaching to the next level, check out <a href="https://maven.com/andrea-mignolo/leader-as-coach">Leader as Coach</a> — a 6 week intensive for leaders who want to integrate coaching skills into their leadership practice. Think of this as a learning lab where you get hands-on practice coaching in a safe and supportive container. Through carefully designed experiential learning exercises, participants deepen their coaching capacity cognitively, emotionally, and somatically. Two cohorts are launching early 2024 and can be a great way to kick off the year.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="quotes-i-3">Quotes I &lt;3</h2>
<blockquote>
  <p>“I define coaching broadly as that part of a relationship in which one person is primarily dedicated to serving the long-term development of competence, self-generation, and aliveness in the other. Coaching is a central and critically important activity for any leader in any organization who sees himself or herself as working with and through others.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>— Doug Silsbee, <em>Presence-Based Coaching</em></p>

<hr />

<p>Thank you for being here, I deeply appreciate your time and attention. Happy exploring, and see you in two weeks!</p>

          ]]>
        </description>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>The Coaching Process</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com//words-make-worlds/009/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com//words-make-worlds/009/</guid>
        <pubDate>Sun, 12 Nov 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


        <description>
          <![CDATA[
            <p>This is Issue 9 of 🌎 <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds">Words Make Worlds</a>, a newsletter about the art, science, and craft of the Coaching Leadership Style. I’m your guide, <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/about/">Andi</a>, and I believe that coaching skills are a leadership multiplier leading to happier teams, more authentic work relationships, and stronger accountability (among other things). Let’s get into this week’s topic: the coaching process.</p>

<h2 id="the-idea">The Idea</h2>
<blockquote>
  <p>Knowledge is produced in response to questions. And new knowledge results from the asking of questions… once you have learned how to ask questions - relevant and appropriate and substantial questions - you have learned how to learn and no one can keep you from learning whatever you want or need to know. - Postman and Weingartner</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The thing that distinguishes coaching from normal conversations is its focus on awareness, meaning, and action. Coaching facilitates learning that generates knowledge, uncovers fresh perspectives, and leads to new actions and behaviors. Each of these capacities can be thought of as a step in the coaching process that creates space for people to step into their own innate wisdom and understanding.</p>

<p>So far we’ve talked about how to <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds/007/">begin a coaching conversation</a> and looked at the specific <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds/008/">kinds of questions</a> that are inherent to a coaching approach. Today we’re going to take a step back and look at the process side of things so you have an understanding of how to facilitate learning and can begin to experiment in your conversations at work.</p>

<p>I prefer frameworks that are simple, easy to remember, and flexible enough to be able to respond to the unpredictable nature of human interaction in real-time. I find Dorothy Strachan’s “What? — So What? — Now What?” framework fits the bill, providing enough structure to so that you know where you are and where to go, with openings to invite improvisation and creativity.</p>

<p class="caption"><img src="/images/wmw/process-framework.png" alt="the process framework" />
Process Framework for Enabling Action, via Dorothy Strachan</p>

<p>There are three main phases in the process “What? — So What? — Now What?” (hence the name), illustrated in a cyclical relationship that reminds us that human interactions are nonlinear and that you’ll find yourself moving between the phases in various ways throughout a single conversation.</p>

<p>Each phase is associated with a type of question:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Notice questions</strong> open up space to increase understanding and awareness about whatever happens to be the focus of the conversation.</li>
  <li><strong>Meaning questions</strong> invite reflection on what has been uncovered through exploring the notice questions.</li>
  <li><strong>Application questions</strong> create commitments towards future actions, experiments, and next steps given what has emerged from the notice and meaning questions.</li>
</ul>

<p>For the sake of clarity we’ll assume that the questions go in the order listed above — notice, make meaning, and application of the learnings — but in practice you’ll frequently find yourself moving back and forth between a couple of phases until you reach enough clarity to continue on.</p>

<p>Once you have determined the focus of the coaching conversation and figured out what you want to accomplish together, you can move into an exploration of the topic or issue at hand. As we discussed in <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds/008/">Issue 8</a> this part of the process requires stepping into the unknown, which can feel challenging and uncomfortable for the coach. To do this successfully  requires letting go of the reins and being willing embrace uncertainty, truly not knowing what the outcome will be. <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds/006/">Curiosity</a> is a great friend in these moments.</p>

<p>The process framework is your map, showing you the lay of the land and the direction of your journey. The first part of your journey begins by creating the space for new understanding through the use of <em>notice</em> questions. This is an invitation to the person you are working with to gain a better understanding of what is both inside and outside of their awareness, asking them to get curious about what lies just beyond the visible horizon. Here you support them to clarify their perspective by articulating the details of what they notice and what makes that noticing so important to them.</p>

<p>Once the issue has been brought into higher resolution through the noticing exploration, you can move into <em>meaning</em> questions that invite reflection and deeper understanding. In this phase you are basically asking, “now that you know what you know, what do you understand that you didn’t before?” Together you start to look for patterns, insights, importance, and significance of what was shared in the <em>noticing</em> phase.</p>

<p>Meaning making can lead to ah-ha moments big and small. When this happens you can shift into the application questions, moving the learning conversation from reflection to commitments for future action. The general gist of this phase is, “with this new understanding, what will you <em>do</em> differently?” Make sure that whatever action plan arises that is doable in a short amount of time — encourage people to take small, immediate steps in order to create quick feedback loops for quick learning and insights to work with in future coaching conversations.</p>

<h2 id="the-practice">The Practice</h2>
<p>This week is less of a practice and more a bank of questions for each phase of the process framework to get you started. The invitation for you is to find a few conversations where you can work with the entire cycle and see what emerges. Be sure to capture your reflections afterwards — what you did that you liked, what you want to learn more about, and what you will try next time.</p>

<h3 id="what-the-notice-questions">What? The Notice Questions</h3>

<ul>
  <li>What is important about the issue? What makes it an issue for you?</li>
  <li>What matters most here? What makes this significant to you?</li>
  <li>What is another way to say this?</li>
  <li>How are you feeling about this?</li>
  <li>What are the most important factors or players in this situation?</li>
  <li>What is at stake? For you? For others?</li>
  <li>How have you contributed to the situation?</li>
  <li>What exactly needs to change here?</li>
  <li>What are you assuming here that is stopping you?</li>
  <li>What fears, doubts, or internal obstacles are keeping you from moving forward? What would it take for these obstacles to be completely gone?</li>
  <li>What do you want to accomplish?</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="so-what-the-meaning-questions">So What? The Meaning Questions</h3>

<ul>
  <li>Based on what we’ve talked about, what’s different for you now?</li>
  <li>What stands out for you?</li>
  <li>What patterns are you starting to notice?</li>
  <li>What does this remind you of?</li>
  <li>What does this all mean to you?</li>
  <li>What concerns do you have?</li>
  <li>What are you learning?</li>
  <li>How does this all fit together?</li>
  <li>What feels more clear? What still feels uncertain?</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="now-what-the-application-questions">Now What? The Application Questions</h3>

<ul>
  <li>What could you do about this?</li>
  <li>What potential courses of action do you see?</li>
  <li>What will you do about this?</li>
  <li>What step could you take this week that would move you towards your goal?</li>
  <li>What actions can you commit to? By when?</li>
  <li>How will you know you’ve been successful?</li>
  <li>What are you taking away from this conversation?</li>
  <li>What will you begin to do more of? Less of?</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h2 id="quotes-i-3">Quotes I &lt;3</h2>
<blockquote>
  <p>The idea that managers and employees can share responsibility for learning is a very adaptive one. We make the related assumption that in most organizations, everyone needs to keep learning. Most businesses and not-for-profits confront a range of competitive threats to their survival. These threats include globalization, disruptive technologies, changing societal values, and the rest of the list you’ve grown accustomed to hearing about. The only way for a firm to survive, let alone prosper, is for enough people in the firm to learn how to adapt to and master these challenges so that the organization can respond appropriately.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>— James Hunt and Joseph Weintraub, <em>The Coaching Manager</em></p>

<hr />

<p>If you enjoyed this issue and found value in it, please share it with other leaders you know. My mission is to bring coaching insights and practices to as many leaders as possible in service of more humane, purposeful, creative, and calmer organizations.</p>

<p>Thank you. ❤️</p>

<p>Andi</p>

          ]]>
        </description>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Asking Questions</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com//words-make-worlds/008/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com//words-make-worlds/008/</guid>
        <pubDate>Sun, 29 Oct 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


        <description>
          <![CDATA[
            <p>Welcome to <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds/">Words Make Worlds</a>, a newsletter dedicated to the art, science, and craft of the Coaching Leadership Style. If you are a new subscriber, welcome! To get you up to speed, last issue we talked about <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds/007/">Beginning Together</a> and this week we’ll be talking about what comes after a good beginning — the exploration phase.</p>

<h2 id="the-idea">The Idea</h2>
<blockquote>
  <p>“An open question is one that expands rather than restricts your arena of exploration, one that does not push or even nudge you toward a particular way of framing the situation.” - Parker Palmer</p>
</blockquote>

<p>One of the primary activities in a coaching conversation is asking questions. But the how and what of your asking will be different than what you might say in day to day conversations. I like to think of coaching conversations as learning conversations, a co-created space where the need to fix or analyze is suspended in favor of exploration and increased awareness. Questions do most of the work in facilitating this experience, and a great question can create clarity, surface insights, and lead us to deeper truths. There is a lot to say about the art of asking questions and we can’t possibly get to it all in one issue, so today we’ll start by looking at what makes a good question.</p>

<p>There is no shortage of available material when it comes to the topic of coaching questions. <a href="https://bookshop.org/p/books/the-coaching-habit-say-less-ask-more-change-the-way-you-lead-forever-michael-bungay-stanier/17315881?ean=9780978440749">The Coaching Habit</a>, a popular book by Michael Bungay Steiner, outlines seven specific questions to guide you through a coaching-style conversation, The Co-Active Training Institute has compiled a <a href="https://cocoachingcircles.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/31-Powerful-Questions.pdf">list of powerful questions</a>, and Tony Stoltzfus has written an entire book on the topic of <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Coaching-Questions-Coachs-Powerful-Asking-ebook/dp/B00GR7AX1G/ref=tmm_kin_swatch_0?_encoding=UTF8&amp;qid=1698519710&amp;sr=8-1">Coaching Questions</a>. These kind of resources are useful when it comes to understanding what coaching questions sound like, getting a sense for the patterns in the structure, and seeing how questions can facilitate a learning experience. By all means read books, lists, articles, watch videos and listen to podcasts to help your understanding! But when it comes to asking good coaching questions, the best learning comes from practice and experience.</p>

<p>The best questions, the most powerful questions, come from what is happening in the moment between the coach and the person they are working with. From a place of open and receptive listening the coach attends to not just the issue at hand, but the wholeness of the person they are working with. They notice the words and phrases that are being used, the tone and pace of the voice, gestures, energy levels, and facial expressions. They get curious about what is revealed about how the person sees themselves specifically in relation to the issue they are exploring and how they see themselves in the world more generally. When coaches attune to a conversation in this way they tap into the source of powerful questions: presence and <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds/006/">curiosity</a>.</p>

<p>What can be challenging for people new to this style of asking questions is that to be truly effective you have to let go of the reins. You let go of having an answer, of fixing, of what you think is right, of knowing what to do, of giving advice, and of sharing from your own experiences. You let go of knowing what the outcome will be so that you can facilitate a true learning conversation. In normal conversations we tend to ask questions to help our own understanding of a situation or to lead someone to our own conclusions. In coaching conversations we ask questions to facilitate understanding in the person we are working with. This is an important distinction — the shift from being curious for our own sake to being curious about how the world is occurring for the person in front of us. By asking questions we can support their own discovery to see themselves more clearly, their patterns of thoughts and beliefs, their default way of relating to the challenges and opportunities in front of them.</p>

<p>This kind of exploration and question asking is more akin to the art of dialogue than conversation. Parker Palmer and the <a href="https://couragerenewal.org">Center for Courage &amp; Renewal</a> has some <a href="https://couragerenewal.org/library/honest-and-open-questions-as-a-spiritual-practice/">wonderful guidelines</a> for asking open and honest questions:</p>

<p>An <a href="https://couragerenewal.org/foundations-participant-portfolio-3/wp-content/uploads/sites/11/2022/08/22-08-18-Open-Honest-Questions-.pdf">open and honest question</a>:</p>

<ul>
  <li>is one that the coach could not possibly anticipate the answer</li>
  <li>assists a person to explore their concern rather than satisfying the coach’s curiosity</li>
  <li>is brief and to the point</li>
  <li>is not overloaded with background considerations and rationale</li>
  <li>does not paraphrase what has been said, and instead uses the other’s words as much as possible</li>
  <li>asks about feelings as well as facts</li>
  <li>can come from intuition</li>
  <li>is not about you, so don’t include storytelling or behaviors that draw attention to yourself</li>
  <li>does not have a yes/no right/wrong answer</li>
  <li>often begins with what, when where, who, or how (try avoiding <a href="https://medium.com/method-matter/the-paradox-of-why-77ee8a3b9cc3">why questions</a>)</li>
</ul>

<p>I'm going to pause for now on the topic of questions (we'll revisit this many more times in the coming months) and move on to the practice.</p>

<h2 id="the-practice">The Practice</h2>
<p>Open and honest questions can seem easy in theory but can be quite hard in practice. The best way to know if you’ve asked a good question is to pay attention to how it impacts the other person. Perceiving impact can be tricky though, especially in conversations where power dynamics are at play that can make revealing the true impact unsafe. This practice is designed to create an open feedback loop so that the coach can understand the full impact of each question.</p>

<p>The exercise requires two people, best done with a trusted practice partner or someone on your team who you have a strong relationship with. The idea is not only to practice asking open and honest questions but to hear first-hand how your questions have impacted the person you are working with.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Speaker, share a bit about a challenge or issue you are currently dealing with. Keep this brief, around 2 - 3 minutes.</li>
  <li>Coach, listen openly and with curiosity. Be careful not to form your questions while the person is speaking, focus on allowing yourself receive both what and how the person is sharing. When the person is done speaking, pause and see what question forms in the empty space. Ask <em>one</em> open and honest question. Don’t ask two or three consecutively! Pause again after you ask the question.</li>
  <li>Speaker, allow the question to land in your mind, heart, and body. Before you answer it, share the impact the question had on you. Does it make you curious, give you energy, invoke a defensive pattern, drain energy, something else? Once you share the impact of the question, answer it in a few brief sentences.</li>
  <li>Coach, listen while the person speaks, pause, and then ask another open and honest question.</li>
  <li>Speaker, again take the the time to feel how the question impacts you. Share what you notice. Then answer the question briefly.</li>
  <li>Repeat this until the conversation feels complete. It is often the case that within 10 minutes of open and honest questions, the speaker is seeing their situation in a new light.</li>
  <li>Switch roles, and repeat the sequence.</li>
</ol>

<p>Debrief together on what you experienced and what you are learning.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="leader-as-coach">Leader as Coach</h2>
<p><a href="https://methodandmatter.com/leader-as-coach/">Leader as Coach</a> is back in 2024! If you are interested getting more hands on practice with coaching in a safe and confidential space with other leaders, this course is for you! Two cohorts are kicking off in Q1 of 2024 making this a great way to start the year with some powerful skills to maximize your leadership impact.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="quotes-i-3">Quotes I &lt;3</h2>
<blockquote>
  <p>Coaching is a way of being, listening, asking, and speaking that draws out and augments characteristics and potential that are already present in a person. An effective coaching relationship creates a safe and challenging environment in which learning can take place. Coaches know that an oak tree already exists within an acorn. They have seen the one grow into the other, over time and under the right conditions, and are committed to providing those conditions to the best of their abilities. Successful coaches continually learn how best to “farm” the potential they are given to nurture.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>— Tim Galloway, <em>The Inner Game of Work: Building Capability in the Workplace</em></p>

<hr />

<p>Have fun exploring coaching questions and see you in two weeks 🙌!</p>

          ]]>
        </description>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Beginning Together</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com//words-make-worlds/007/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com//words-make-worlds/007/</guid>
        <pubDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


        <description>
          <![CDATA[
            <p>Welcome to <em>Words Make Worlds</em> 🌎! I’m <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/about">Andi</a> and this week we’ll be looking at how to begin a coaching conversation. How you begin is critical to your level of success, and the attention you give to beginnings will determine everything that comes afterwards.</p>

<h2 id="the-idea">The Idea</h2>
<p>Beginnings may seem superfluous but they are essential to effective and powerful coaching conversations. There is a lot to be said for taking the time to arrive and settle in together. To slow down and get a sense of each other, allowing our attention to come into the present and to collaboratively look at the work in front of us.</p>

<p>How we begin sets the stage for what follows. In busy organizational environments focused on efficiency and productivity, it can be easy to skip over beginnings in service of getting work done quickly. But when we skip over beginnings, we miss the opportunity to fully connect and we deprive ourselves of the important work of tending to the structure of the conversation. Without connection and structure, no matter how quickly we get to the issue, we are not setting ourselves up for success.</p>

<p>Beginning well is about knowing what the conversation is about, what is most important, what will be different by the end of the conversation, and what will make the conversation useful. If these four things are in place your chances of engaging in a productive and meaningful conversation increase exponentially, simply by tending to beginnings 😊.</p>

<h2 id="the-practice">The Practice</h2>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Arrive.</strong> Give yourself a little time to settle in and get situated.</li>
  <li><strong>Tend to what needs tending.</strong> If you were coming from another meeting and you need to capture a few notes in order not to be distracted, say as much and take a few minutes to write things down. When you are done, allow yourself to stop thinking about where you were and focus on the present.</li>
  <li><strong>Check in.</strong> This can be short, but be genuine.</li>
  <li><strong>Assess.</strong> What is your impression of how they are? What picture do they paint for you of how they are seeing themselves and the world in this moment? This includes things like energy levels, focus, distraction, stress, and ability to be present. We can sense all of these things fairly quickly in the first few moments we are together with someone.</li>
  <li><strong>Set the boundaries of the conversation.</strong> These steps are a slight modification based on Claire Pedricks’s wonderful book <a href="https://bookshop.org/p/books/simplifying-coaching-how-to-have-more-transformational-conversations-by-doing-less-claire-pedrick/15769790?ean=9780335249077"><em>Simplifying Coaching</em></a>:
    <ol>
      <li><strong>Subject:</strong> What would you like to explore today? What question or issue?</li>
      <li><strong>Time:</strong> In the amount of time we have, what part of that would be successful to focus on?</li>
      <li><strong>Outcome:</strong> What would you like to be different by the end of this conversation?</li>
      <li><strong>Know:</strong> How will you know that this conversation has been useful?</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Begin.</strong> If you both feel satisfied with the focus and the outcomes, ask them where they would like to start. Let them choose what feels important, and start the conversation with, “Where shall we start?”</li>
</ol>

<p>Once you begin the conversation, ​<a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds/006/">curiosity</a>​, <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds/005/">optimism</a>​, and ​<a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds/004/">using your attention intentionally​</a> will take you through the rest.</p>

<hr />

<p>I wish you clear, focused, and easeful beginnings. Thank you for being here, see you in two weeks! 🙌</p>

          ]]>
        </description>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Curiosity</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com//words-make-worlds/006/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com//words-make-worlds/006/</guid>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


        <description>
          <![CDATA[
            <p>Hello, and welcome to the Curiosity Edition of <em>Words Make Worlds</em>! I’m <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/about">Andi</a>, an executive and team coach who believes that coaching skills are essential for leaders in the increasingly complex, uncertain, and relentlessly changing world we find ourselves in. The siren song of technological solutionism is strong, but for now organizations are still made of people and as long they are, knowing how to build strong, trusting, collaborative relationships is crucial to individual and organizational success. And coaching is a skill that can deliver exactly that.</p>

<p>Before we jump into today’s theme of curiosity, let’s cover where we are at so far:</p>

<ul>
  <li>We started by setting up a <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds/002/">learning container</a>, a set of activities/ done in the morning and evening to <em>hold</em> the work you are doing as you develop a Coaching Leadership Style. Think of it as scaffolding for learning.</li>
  <li>Then we talked about <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds/003/">working with strengths (and values)</a>. This is incredibly important for developing your unique Coaching Leadership Style and for being authentic and transparent with others. When people know what is important to you and what your values are, they understand you more deeply and trust increases. Don’t be a chaos ball of uncertainty and unpredictability.</li>
  <li>Throw in the <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds/004/">Loop of Awareness</a>, a useful tool for freeing your attention. When you learn how to utilize attention intentionally, more of the world opens up in service of noticing, observing, reflecting, learning, and taking choiceful action.</li>
  <li>And then we talked about <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds/005/">optimism</a> and the role it plays in supporting change and growth. This is a posture that invites participants to plant their feet firmly in reality while taking an optimistic view of what is possible in the future. This is incredibly important when it comes to supporting others in sourcing their own knowledge, creativity, and decision making in service of the person they are becoming.</li>
</ul>

<p>Some of you might be scratching your head and thinking “Andi, where is the coaching in all of this?” Isn’t coaching about asking good questions? If you have been following along and trying out the practices and exercises, I imagine you’ve noticing some subtle shifts in the conversations you are having. That’s because you are <em>already</em> coaching. By changing your mindset, using attention wisely, leaning on your strengths, and seeing the inherent resourcefulness in those you work with, your presence itself is having an impact (more on presence in a future edition).</p>

<p>But coaching is <em>also</em> about asking good questions, and we’re going to get into that today from the perspective of Curiosity, an important quality to cultivate in the mindset of a coach.</p>

<h2 id="the-idea">The Idea</h2>
<p>Curiosity isn’t necessarily about questions, though they are a part of it. Curiosity is an orientation towards life, a willingness to embrace a state of not knowing, and a genuine interest in uncovering something new. A very useful skill in rapidly changing times. The questions that arise from this place can unlock new ways of seeing, thinking, and acting.</p>

<p>Curiosity in coaching isn’t about gathering information so you can decide what to do. Instead, it acts in service of the learning and growth of the person you are working with. It illuminates areas for exploration so that you can discover what is hidden from view. Questions that come from genuine curiosity can be evocative or provocative, an invitation to pause, reflect, and deepen understanding. Co-Active Coaching recommends paying close attention the impact your questions have - when you ask one, where does it send the other person? Do they remain at the surface giving easy answers, or do they go to new places, quietly listening to the answer that form as new insights and understandings come forward?</p>

<p>Genuine curiosity, sourced from a place of openness and wonder, leaves no room for fear; the excitement of exploration and discovery is too pervasive for anything else to be present. Which is wonderfully liberating for both the coach and the person being coached! Imagine being in a conversation at work - a conversation with your boss no less - where it is truly okay to not know. And to feel fully supported in your exploration to find that knowing, to engage in reflection and discovery until you see yourself and the situation in new ways and new possibilities emerge.</p>

<p>When this happens, people become more generative in their ability to source creative solutions. Curiosity also builds deep connection and trusting relationships, a critical component of high performing teams. Imagine two conversations: one rooted in problem solving, the other rooted in curiosity. In the problem solving conversation, questions are asked to gather information and figure out the source of the issue in order to fix it. Sometimes it can feel like an interrogation, where questions thinly mask judgements, blame, and negative assessments of the people and decisions involved. The conversation rooted in curiosity has no need for any of this because judgements, blame, and negative assessments are <em>conclusions</em>, they close us off to learning, and curiosity cannot exist simultaneously with conclusions. The questions in this conversation put everyone on equal footing, seeking to uncover and understand something new, with genuine interest for what can be learned. The first conversation creates defensiveness, reactivity, and distrust. The second generates curiosity, responsiveness, and trust.</p>

<p>It can be really easy to get hooked by the content of what someone shares with us. The nitty gritty details of who said what, and who did what, and when, and what happened after that. With coaching, you really don’t need all those details because your curiosity is about the <em>person</em>, not the issue. This is a subtle and important difference. When you focus on the person, your curiosity and coaching orients around who they are <em>in relationship to</em> the issue, how they interpret the situation, and what possibilities they see or don’t see. What happened in the past doesn’t really matter. You want to keep the conversation in the present and oriented towards the future.</p>

<p>And one last thing - get curious beyond the words. Listen to their gestures, tone, energy, posture, pace, and tempo. If something shifts or change, get curious! If someone who usually talks fast and has a lot of energy slows down and gets soft, get curious!</p>

<h2 id="the-practice">The Practice</h2>
<p>This is a collection of micro practices you can try out in the coming weeks:</p>

<ol>
  <li>In your next 1:1, limit your responses to questions and mirroring. Questions should primarily be of the how and what variety, though when and who and where can work too. <a href="https://medium.com/method-matter/the-paradox-of-why-77ee8a3b9cc3">Do your best to avoid why questions.</a> Mirroring helps the conversation feel a little less awkward - by sharing back the words and phrases the other person is using (exactly as they are, no modifications) you serve as a reflection, helping them see and hear themselves more deeply and clearly.</li>
  <li>Keep your questions short. Ask one at a time. Avoid leading questions. Pause and allow space for the other person to reflect and respond.</li>
  <li>If something goes sideways, or you feel the sudden pressure of needing to have an answer, throw your hands up in the air and shout, “How fascinating!” <a href="https://youtu.be/qTKEBygQic0?si=0Ivp2Q4dXGH0TAsD&amp;t=360">in the style of Benjamin Zander</a>. I’m not kidding. I used to do this at work a lot.</li>
  <li>From the Hendricks Institute comes the very useful HMMMMMMMMM. It is very hard to make this sound and <em>not</em> feel more curious. If you need to up the curiosity factor, just let out a good HMMMMMMMMM.</li>
  <li>Before you ask a question, preface it with the words, “I’m curious…”</li>
  <li>When in conversation with someone you are coaching, try standing or sitting side by side looking out a window (if you don’t have a window maybe a painting or a nature poster with an inspirational quote). If you can’t do this physically, just imagine you are together shoulder to shoulder, equals looking at the same thing and wondering about what is possible.</li>
  <li>When the conversation is over, reflect on what happened and ask yourself, “What is even more mysterious about this person?” This question keeps the curiosity and wonder alive against the very human propensity to label, categorize, interpret, and judge the world around us.</li>
</ol>

<p>Before you step into any of these practices check in with yourself and see if you are truly open to learning or not. If you are, embrace your genuine curiosity and jump into the conversation. If you aren’t, pay attention to what is being activated in you and give yourself what you need in the moment. This might be a break from the conversation, a few deep breaths, zooming out from the details, acknowledging and accepting exactly where you are, etc.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="leader-as-coach-starts-tomorrow">Leader as Coach Starts Tomorrow</h2>
<p>The next cohort of <a href="https://maven.com/andrea-mignolo/leader-as-coach">Leader as Coach</a> kicks off on Monday, October 2nd! If you want hands on practice learning essential coaching skills to maximize your leadership impact, come join us! This six week cohort-based course will give you the skills to have better conversations, increase accountability, unlock potential, and increase team performance.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="leader-as-coach-library">Leader as Coach Library</h2>
<p>Also! If you are looking for more resources to support you in your coaching journey, check out the Leader as Coach Library, an evolving collection of <a href="https://airtable.com/appoaIkTducQK5fHH/shrRXr1zvaPl1XANL/tblfZ7HUjXLTJaXGI">books</a> and <a href="https://airtable.com/appoaIkTducQK5fHH/shrRKnQFXVG0LbbTJ/tblfZ7HUjXLTJaXGI?backgroundColor=red">articles</a> for leaders like you.</p>

<hr />

<p>I hope you enjoyed this exploration of curiosity. I am VERY CURIOUS to know how these practices are going for you, what you are learning, and questions you are holding. If you feel like sharing, just reply to this email.</p>

<p>See you in two weeks!</p>

          ]]>
        </description>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Optimism</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com//words-make-worlds/005/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com//words-make-worlds/005/</guid>
        <pubDate>Sun, 17 Sep 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


        <description>
          <![CDATA[
            <p>Welcome to the fifth issue of <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds"><em>Words Make Worlds</em></a>, a newsletter dedicated to the art, science, and craft of the Coaching Leadership Style. Today we’re getting into one of my favorite parts of coaching: optimism.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-idea">The Idea</h2>
<p>When I talk with leaders about the idea of optimism as a useful tool for coaching, they usually point out that pretending things are great isn’t going to fix performance problems. Which is true — bypassing reality with magical thinking leads to disappointment, frustration, and resentment. Just ask anyone who has ever delayed having a difficult conversation at work — by the time the talk actually happens considerable damage has been done.</p>

<p>But optimism isn’t about unreasonable hope, it’s about an acceptance of how things are now and a belief that they can be better. It is a perspective, a way of seeing, an orientation towards life that celebrates what an individual or system is doing <em>well</em> ,  even if what it is doing well happens to be getting in the way of desired outcomes. Optimism is imbued with curiosity and turns its gaze to the future as a place of possibility and action.</p>

<p>Think back to your last year at work. How many times has pointing out what is going wrong — with an individual, project, team, or system — resulted in change? My guess is very few.</p>

<p>Optimism starts with a willingness to accept what is, while simultaneously holding the belief that change is possible and things can get better. Optimism rests in the <a href="https://medium.com/method-matter/building-a-relationship-with-change-3602cf6e7890">paradox of change</a>, inviting us to understand that <em>change happens just by paying attention to what is</em> . This grounded acceptance of the present is what distinguishes optimism from wishful thinking.</p>

<p>Optimism is the belief that people are doing the best they can with the resources and awareness they have available to them. And <em>awareness</em> is the entry point for coaching. Coaching increases awareness and resourcefulness in others so that new possibilities can emerge, new paths for action can be taken.</p>

<p>On the other side of optimism is pessimism, a perspective we are biologically hard-wired to inhabit because it keeps us alive. It lives in the narrowing band of fear, looking to the past for clues that can protect us from whatever might threaten us in the present. When pessimism clouds our view, we can only see what is going wrong as we spin in reinforcing negative feedback loops fed by fear. In a world of increasing uncertainty, it can feel like we perpetually live in the constricted, protective domain of pessimism.</p>

<p>But optimism, optimism gives us another choice. One that feels increasingly radical in a polarized world. <a href="http://josephmelnickphd.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/Articles/Article_on_Optimism%20with%20Sonia.pdf">Joseph Melnick and Sonia Nevis</a> say of optimism:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Optimism is about having the courage to try things. It is about stepping into something because we hope it will be a good thing, without knowing what will happen. And it is about learning not to stay attached to the negative when things do not turn out in ways we had hoped.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>And this is <em>exactly</em> what coaching is. Raising awareness, taking courageous action, seeing what happens, and reflecting in service of learning from the richness of what we have just experienced. This level of learning isn’t just at a cognitive level, but a level that involves the entirety of our being. Whatever happens, we get curious, accept, learn and grow.</p>

<p>Imagine something is going sideways at work and you <em>know</em> it’s not going well but can’t figure out how to get the results you want. Or maybe you got a negative performance review, or had a big conflict with a colleague at work. And then your boss calls you into a conference room (or Zoom call) and proceeds to tell you all about what a problem this is. What happens as you hear this? You probably make yourself a little smaller (or a little bigger with anger), negative self talk gets louder, you feel sad/mad/frustrated, and you have no idea what to do to make it better. You feel tired and hopeless.</p>

<p>Or, your boss calls you into that Zoom call and you both explore what is going on with non-judgement and acceptance. Your boss listens, asks questions, and then comments on what you are doing really well in the situation. They might say something like, “you are really good at protecting yourself when you feel attacked. Do you know that?” And you might pause for a second and think some kind of trick is afoot, but as your boss encourages you to to examine this piece of feedback and feel the truth of it, your curiosity enters the room. You might say something like, “Yeah, I am really good at that. But it feels like that’s the only way I know how to respond and I can see how it gets in the way of collaboration.”</p>

<p>And <em>right there</em> is the seed that unlocks possibility. Because as soon as you accept this statement of what you are doing well, you get curious about it. Curious enough to see the benefit and also <em>the cost</em>, and wonder about other ways you might approach the situation. And that curiosity, fostered by the presence of optimism, is the gateway to expanding your range of responsiveness in similar situations.</p>

<p>For coaches, optimism is less about what you do and more about <em>how you are</em>. This is a mindset based in the ideas of unconditional positive regard, strengths-based change, and positive psychology. It's not about a set of questions you can ask, but about how you see the world and the inherent capacity you see in others. As you embody optimism, your thinking begins to shift and your actions follow-suit. So this starts with being, percolates into thinking, and finally influences the doing side of leading and coaching.</p>

<h2 id="the-practice">The Practice</h2>

<h3 id="practice-one-resentment-to-appreciation">Practice One: Resentment to Appreciation.</h3>
<p>This an individual practice based on the work of John O. Stevens.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Think of someone at work (or in your life) that you are frustrated with or in some way or another negatively impacted by what they are doing (or not doing).</li>
  <li>Write down a list of your resentments. Begin each sentence with the words “I resent —“ and express clearly and exactly what you resent about this person.</li>
  <li>When that feels complete, stop writing and take a minute to move, stretch, wiggle, or shake it out.</li>
  <li>When you are ready, sit down and resume.</li>
  <li>Go through your list of resentments, one by one. For each one, cross out the word <em>resent</em> and replace it with the word <em>appreciate</em>.</li>
  <li>Go slowly, trying each one on for size. How do you feel as you make the shift? Is there something you actually do appreciate in what you thought you resented?</li>
  <li>If you want, add a few more sentences to elaborate on your appreciation.</li>
  <li>Reflect on your experience in this exercise. What did you notice mentally emotionally, and somatically when you engaged in writing down the resentment list? What shifted as you turned resentments into appreciations? What new insights did you make? What will you do with what you have learned?</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="practice-two-filtered-listening">Practice Two: Filtered Listening</h3>

<p>This practice can be done in a 1:1 conversation or team meeting; any situation where you have the opportunity to be an active listener. If you are doing this in a 1:1 scenario, you may want to let the person you are talking with know you are experimenting with different ways of listening and to not be alarmed if they notice your demeanor change.</p>

<ol>
  <li>In this exercise you are going to practice with both the pessimistic and optimistic stance.</li>
  <li>As you begin the conversation or meeting, spend the first 5 - 10 minutes listening from a pessimistic stance. Narrow your focus and look for what is wrong, certain that you are seeing more problems than anyone else and that you those around you do not have the capacity to solve them. If you are in a 1:1 conversation, notice the impact the pessimistic stance has on the person you are listening to.</li>
  <li>After 5 - 10 minutes, let go of the pessimistic stance. Give yourself a moment to let it melt out of your body, dissolve from your thoughts, and abdicate your emotions.</li>
  <li>Now step into the optimistic stance. Consider the person or people in front of you and listen with curiosity. Hold the perspective that everyone is doing the best they can with the awareness and resources available to them, and the conviction you know they have the capacity to create change. If you can generate a genuine sense of warmth and positive regard, even better. But don’t try to fake this - others can detect when we are just putting on a show.</li>
  <li>As you listen, see if you can observe what this person or group knows how to do really well, even if it’s something that frustrates or annoys you. How does this serve the person or group? What do you think it is like for them to engage in the world this way?</li>
  <li>Once you have finished this practice, take a few notes about what you noticed from the experience. If the person you were listening to knows you were trying out listening approaches, debrief and see how the experience was for them. What will you do with what you are learning?</li>
</ol>

<hr />

<h2 id="leader-as-coach">Leader as Coach</h2>

<p>A quick reminder that <a href="https://maven.com/andrea-mignolo/leader-as-coach">Leader as Coach kicks off its fourth cohort on October 2nd</a>! This is a great opportunity for leaders to deepen their coaching skills by putting them into practice in safe learning environment, because the best way to learn to coach is to <em>start coaching</em>.</p>

<hr />

<p>🫶 Happy practicing, and see you in two weeks! 🫶</p>

          ]]>
        </description>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>The Loop of Awareness</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com//words-make-worlds/004/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com//words-make-worlds/004/</guid>
        <pubDate>Sun, 03 Sep 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


        <description>
          <![CDATA[
            <p>Hello, happy September, and welcome to another issue of <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds"><em>Words Make Worlds</em></a>! I’m Andi, and today we’re going to be learning a tool for increasing awareness and using attention with intention.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-idea">The Idea</h2>
<p>Our attention is one of the most powerful tools we can use in coaching. What we pay attention to informs how we perceive and interpret the world around us. But most of us, over the course of a lifetime, have developed patterns of perception that freezes us in a narrow band of reality. We learn to pay attention to certain things and discount others, and in doing so reinforce attention loops that are particular to our own individual experience of the world.</p>

<p>If you think about it, this is where a lot of miscommunication and disagreement comes from. People in the same situation experience it in radically different ways because of what they are paying  attention to. For example, take the common occurrence of a meeting where disagreement was expressed. For someone whose attention loop is highly focused on emotions, they might feel the meeting was tense and filled with conflict. For another person who focuses on ideas, they might have walked away from the meeting feeling invigorated and challenged. And yet a third person whose attention seeks out the information they need to take action, they might leave the meeting frustrated that progress wasn’t made. Same meeting, wildly different experiences and interpretations of what happened.</p>

<p>It takes practice to “unhook” our attention and develop the capacity to take in more of the world, and to do so without adding layers of interpretation and story. To start to see the habitual patterns that have shaped our sense of how the world is, and see that we have constructed a particular version of reality that is specific to our personal way of being.</p>

<p>The Loop of Awareness, developed by <a href="https://hendricks.com">Gay and Katie Hendricks</a>, is a useful tool for freeing our attention and breaking out of habitual patterns of perception. It teaches us how to consciously use our attention, whether we keep it wide to see the big picture or narrow in on something particular to see the details. When we learn how to use our attention in this way we can bring a deeper level of awareness to coaching conversations, giving us more information to work with in support of learning and growth.</p>

<h2 id="the-practice">The Practice</h2>

<p>Begin by directing your attention to yourself.</p>

<p>Notice how you are in this moment — maybe you pick up on your breathing, or a sensation in your body, or your posture. There are so many things you can notice — don’t try to notice them all! Just pick up on one or two things. Let your attention rest long enough to note your state.</p>

<p>Now direct your attention to the space around you.</p>

<p>Get curious! Notice something in your environments. Objects nearby, textures, the quality of the light, the temperature, movement, etc.</p>

<p>Direct your focus back to yourself.</p>

<p>And then go back outside yourself again to the space around you.</p>

<p>Keep moving your attention back and forth. Do so in a way that feels natural and comfortable. Consciously shift back and forth, allowing your attention to deepen your awareness of what is happening right now, this very minute, inside and outside yourself. As you do this, feel how powerful your attention can be when used in a conscious and supportive way.</p>

<p>If you want, try oscillating your attention out and in rapidly. Or really slowly. Experiment with different rhythms of moving your attention. <strong>Leave judgement behind and simply notice what you notice</strong>.</p>

<p>You can also do this with a person, instead of the space around you. The process is the same, except when you go outside yourself your focus rests on another person, rather than the space around you, so what you notice might be different.</p>

<h2 id="reflection-prompts">Reflection Prompts</h2>
<p>Notice your own pace and pattern of shifting attention.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Where does your attention sit naturally? Does it rest more on your inward state, or is it more focused on the outer world?</li>
  <li>What is it like to move your awareness with intention? What is easy or hard about the process?</li>
  <li>How do you shift your awareness, what is it that you shift? Your eyes? Your thoughts? Your body?</li>
  <li>What is the rhythm of your oscillation? What cadence feels most comfortable? Most uncomfortable?</li>
  <li>What are you learning about your patterns of focus and awareness? What will you do with this information?</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="things-of-which-we-can-be-aware">Things Of Which We Can Be Aware</h2>
<p>An incomplete list of things to bring your attention to, compiled by <a href="https://www.routledge.com/Organizational-Consulting-A-Gestalt-Approach/Nevis/p/book/9780881632491">Edwin Nevis</a>:</p>

<p><strong>Sensations</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>The outcomes of seeing: sights</li>
  <li>The outcomes of hearing: sounds</li>
  <li>The outcomes of touching: textures, tactility</li>
  <li>The outcomes of gustation: tastes</li>
  <li>The outcomes of olfaction: smells</li>
  <li>The outcomes of proprioception: body tissue/kinesthetic stimulation (tendons, muscles, etc.)</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Internal Verbalizations and Visualizations</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>Thinking, ruminating, internal dialogue</li>
  <li>Planning, wishing, hoping</li>
  <li>Memory, remembering past events, history</li>
  <li>Dreams and fantasies</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Feelings</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>Happiness, pleasure, contentment</li>
  <li>Elation, zest, lust, joy, confidence</li>
  <li>Sadness, depression, helplessness, despair</li>
  <li>Fear, disgust, shame, remorse</li>
  <li>Respect, awe, admiration, wonder, reverence</li>
  <li>Irritation, rage, anger, jealousy, hatred</li>
  <li>Vanity, self-confidence, pride</li>
  <li>Affection, love, warmth, empathy</li>
  <li>Boredom, indifference, scorn</li>
  <li>Tenderness, compassion, pity</li>
  <li>Guilt, anxiety</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Values</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>Predispositions, sets, inclinations, theories</li>
  <li>Judgements and attributions</li>
  <li>Summaries or generalizations of past experience</li>
  <li>Nature of boundaries, prejudices</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Interpersonal and Group Interactions</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>Participation patterns</li>
  <li>Communication styles</li>
  <li>Figural elements: content, energy, differences</li>
  <li>Functional activities</li>
  <li>Norms</li>
  <li>Atmosphere, climate</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h2 id="what-are-you-learning">What Are You Learning?</h2>
<p>I’d love to know how your practices are going and what you are learning. If this feels in alignment for you, just reply to this email!</p>

<p>Until next time,</p>

<p>Andi</p>

          ]]>
        </description>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Working With Strengths</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com//words-make-worlds/003/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com//words-make-worlds/003/</guid>
        <pubDate>Sun, 20 Aug 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


        <description>
          <![CDATA[
            <p>Hello! This is <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds"><em>Words Make Worlds</em></a> Issue 3. You are receiving this newsletter because somewhere along the way you decided to learn more about the Coaching Leadership Style. If you’ve changed your mind and are no longer interested, you can easily unsubscribe at the bottom of this email. If you are still here then keep reading because this week we are learning about the importance of a strengths-based approach to developing your coaching skills.</p>

<h2 id="the-idea">The Idea</h2>

<p>Each of us has a unique way of engaging with the world that influences what holds our attention, gets us excited, creates meaning, and gives purpose. It shines through in our personality, shapes our leadership style, and can also be a foundation for coaching.</p>

<p>Values and strengths are two ways to describe or encapsulate this uniqueness. Values reflect what we care about and strengths are an expression of what comes naturally. Knowing and living our values is an important part of how we show up in leadership and life, and leaning on our strengths can be an accelerant for development and transformation.</p>

<p>The world of <a href="https://www.health.harvard.edu/topics/positive-psychology">positive psychology</a> and <a href="https://www.naahq.org/sites/default/files/naa-documents/education/Building-A-Strengths-Based-Organization.pdf">strengths-based change</a> suggest that focusing on what is right is more effective than focusing on what is wrong. As <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Qui-Gon_Jinn">Qui-Gon Jinn</a> says, “your focus determines your reality.” If we focus on weaknesses and what is wrong, then our reality is one of scarcity, lack, and fear. If we focus on strengths and what is right, our reality is filled with capacity, competence, and trust.</p>

<p>So on the one hand we have fear, and on the other we have trust. What does this mean for our ability to learn and change? And to coach? Some moods such wonder, ambition, and trust are conducive to learning while others like fear, overwhelm, and resignation prevent learning from happening <sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. When you step into the role of coach, leaning on your strengths can help you feel more confident, present, and open to whatever comes up in conversation. This attitude contributes to an environment of wonder and trust, a place where two people can really explore what is happening with openness and honesty.</p>

<p>Conversely, if you are overly focused on what you might do wrong or what your weaknesses are, the conversation will be palpably different because curiosity and learning are not possible when moods like fear and worry are predominant. If you are unsure of yourself and thinking about what you might do wrong, the environment won’t feel supportive for you or the other person.</p>

<p>It’s important that you <a href="https://www.want.uji.es/wp-content/uploads/2020/04/2020_Pelaez-Coo-y-Salanova.pdf">apply this same perspective</a> to the person you are working with. Look for and highlight their strengths, reflect their capacities, and communicate the trust you have in their ability to figure things out. Of course, there may be areas to improve, but these can also be approached through a strengths-based lens (more on that in a future issue). The main idea to focus on is that by identifying and working with strengths, on what is going right and working well, leaders as coaches build trusting relationships that support learning, creativity, and growth. If you focus on what someone is doing wrong and where they are lacking, the conversation will generate fear and the range of creative action will narrow.</p>

<h2 id="knowing-your-strengths">Knowing Your Strengths</h2>
<p>So, what are your strengths? What kind of coach are you? What unique ways do you facilitate insight, action, and learning through conversation? Answering these questions will help you get clear on how you are showing up as a coach.</p>

<p>There are many ways to uncover your strengths, a few of which we’ll go over together. If you have another method or resource you prefer, then by all means use it!</p>

<h3 id="personal-reflection">Personal Reflection</h3>
<p>Take a moment and reflect on what comes naturally to you, what you do really well without even thinking about it. Maybe there are things you do, or ways that you do them, that people have commented on. What lights you up and gives you energy when you do it? Spend a week or two doing some reflective journaling around the topic and see what comes up.</p>

<h3 id="formal-and-informal-feedback">Formal and Informal Feedback</h3>
<p>Annual reviews, 360 feedback, in the moment appreciations or acknowledgements for something you’ve done well, are all good sources to reference. I’m also a fan of reaching out to people who know you - friends, family, team, colleagues, sangha, whatever - and asking them to share what they see as your strengths.</p>

<h3 id="via-strengths-survey">VIA Strengths Survey</h3>
<p>The <a href="https://www.viacharacter.org">VIA Institute on Character</a> offers a <a href="https://www.viacharacter.org/surveys/takesurvey">free survey</a> to help identify your top “character strengths” - 24 scientifically identified strengths that make up what’s best about our personality. They also have some useful resources to understand strengths and develop them more fully in service of leadership and coaching.</p>

<h2 id="the-practice">The Practice</h2>
<p>If you’ve set up your learning container already, you just need to make a few modifications. If you haven’t you can probably just follow the instructions below and be fine, but if you want to read more about how to set one up, check out <a href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds/002/">Issue #2</a>.</p>

<p>In the morning, continue to spend five quiet minutes with yourself without technology or other distractions. Bring your awareness to hands and arms, feet and legs. Feel your breath in your belly and chest. As you settle in, see if you can sense yourself, your “you-ness”.  What thoughts, emotions, and sensations are you aware of, and how do those contribute to the unique way you sense and respond to the world around you?</p>

<p>In the evening, spend some time journaling and reflecting on your strengths. Here are some questions to get you started:</p>

<ul>
  <li>What are your top strengths?</li>
  <li>What do your strengths mean to you? What do they help you do?</li>
  <li>What happens when you overuse a strength?</li>
  <li>How do your strengths influence how you lead?</li>
  <li>How/when did you <a href="https://www.viacharacter.org/topics/articles/road-map-to-strengths-use">use each of your strengths</a> today?</li>
  <li>How can you use these strengths to support others?</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="until-next-time">Until Next Time</h2>
<p>The Coaching Leadership Style has two tracks - development of self and development of others. You may be curious why we haven't gotten into the actual coaching conversation yet, but in many ways we have. By first focusing on ourselves, who we are as leaders, what our strengths are, and increasing our awareness of how we show up, interactions with our teams and colleagues will begin to shift. What we are working on right now is one of the most fundamental and critical tools of coaching - presence. As we’ll begin to uncover, coaching conversations are 20% what you say, 80% how you show up.</p>

<p>See you in a few weeks,</p>

<p>Andi</p>

<hr />

<h5 id="footnotes">FOOTNOTES</h5>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>For more on moods and learning, see “<a href="https://bookshop.org/p/books/learning-to-learn-and-the-navigation-of-moods-the-meta-skill-for-the-acquisition-of-skills-stuart-e-dreyfus-phd/11324350?ean=9780692801796">Learning to Learn and the Navigation of Moods</a>.” <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>

          ]]>
        </description>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>The Learning Container</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com//words-make-worlds/002/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com//words-make-worlds/002/</guid>
        <pubDate>Sun, 06 Aug 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


        <description>
          <![CDATA[
            <p>Welcome to Issue 2 of <em>Words Make Worlds</em>, a newsletter dedicated to the art, science, and craft of the Coaching Leadership Style. This week we take a look at learning containers, why they are important for developing a Coaching Leadership Style, and how to set one up for yourself.</p>

<h2 id="the-idea">The Idea</h2>
<p>A learning container is a structure that holds the work, practices, and commitments required to live into a new way of leading or living. For the purpose of this newsletter the work and commitment is to develop a way of being that can facilitate powerful coaching conversations. Coaching is about building awareness, taking new action, and reflecting on the outcomes as a way of learning and growing through experience. It requires keen self-awareness and deep curiosity about others. Embarking on the coaching path can be uncomfortable and challenging, the way forward isn’t always clear, and development is a decidedly non-linear path. So when we’re learning coaching skills and we want to shift how we’re showing up with our teams, we can create a container to remind us of our commitment every day.</p>

<p>Containers can take many forms. Just step outside and take a walk in a forest - you’ll quickly realize <a href="https://onbeing.org/blog/parker-palmer-theres-a-place-for-every-question-in-the-vast-container-of-nature/">​nature is a vast container​</a>. For the purpose of learning the Coaching Leadership Style the container is much more simple, consisting of a morning mindfulness practice and some evening reflections.</p>

<h2 id="the-practice">The Practice</h2>
<p><strong>In the Morning</strong></p>

<p>Spend five minutes each morning connecting with yourself. Preferably before you check your phone, email, or any digital screens. Take a few breaths all the way down to your belly. Feel where your body has contact with another surface (maybe you are lying in bed, sitting in a chair, standing at the window, etc). What are you aware of? What sensations, emotions, and thoughts are you noticing? What do you notice about the environment you are in? Allow yourself to be fully present with whatever is showing up, even if it brings some discomfort.</p>

<p>Starting the day with a small mindfulness checkin builds our capacity to be present and aware in each moment. As this practice becomes a natural part of our daily routine and our awareness muscles grow, we will suddenly find moments at work where we have access to the same level of presence, making it easier to observe our thoughts, emotions, and actions from a more conscious place. Seeing the habitual thoughts and emotional reactions that shape our behavior is the first step in building the capacity to take creative and choiceful action.</p>

<p><strong>In the Evening</strong></p>

<p>Reflect on you day. At the end of each day - either when the work day is done or when you are winding down for the night -  reflect back and answer the following questions:</p>

<ul>
  <li>What were my dominate emotions today?</li>
  <li>What thoughts/thought patterns showed up the most?</li>
  <li>What actions did I take? What actions did I avoid?</li>
  <li>How did my thoughts, emotions, and actions contribute to the outcomes I was trying to achieve? How did they get in the way?</li>
</ul>

<p>Paired with the morning mindfulness practice, the reflection questions contribute to building the muscle of self-observation. This is the first step in developing a Coaching Leadership Style - being able to observe ourselves in action and understand what (really) drives our behaviors.</p>

<h2 id="experiment">Experiment!</h2>
<p>As we delve deeper into the skills of the Coaching Leadership Style I will offer modifications to the learning container in order to support your learning and development. But for now, over the next two weeks, experiment with creating a learning container in your life and see what emerges. And if you feel so inclined, reply to this email and let me know how its going!</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="elsewhere">Elsewhere</h2>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://medium.com/wordsmakeworlds/the-coaching-leadership-style-developing-self-and-developing-others-2f3fd665ba6d">Getting Started with the Coaching Leadership Style​</a>. Last week I spoke with Russ Unger of Chicago Camps about getting start with CLS, including a discussion of containers (link includes audio, captions, and transcript).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The cohort-based course <a href="https://maven.com/andrea-mignolo/leader-as-coach">Leader as Coach</a> returns in the fall! Starting September 18th, this 6 week course provides experiential learning and hands on practice for folks who want to get started with the Coaching Leadership Style.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<hr />

<p>Thanks for being here, happy learning, and see you in two weeks!</p>

          ]]>
        </description>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Welcome to Words Make Worlds!</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com//words-make-worlds/001/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com//words-make-worlds/001/</guid>
        <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jul 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


        <description>
          <![CDATA[
            <p>Hello! I am glad you are here.</p>

<p>To kick things off, I want to share my intention behind this newsletter and what you can expect, with the caveat that things will evolve with time and feedback.</p>

<p><em>Words Make Worlds</em> will (usually) arrive in your inbox every other Sunday. Each issue will contain an idea or model relevant to the Coaching Leadership Style, an experiment for putting it into practice, and journaling prompts to facilitate reflection and learning.</p>

<p>My intention is to share practical, grounded, actionable teachings that, over time, will support you to integrate coaching skills into your leadership practice. I'll also share links to longer form articles and videos for those of you who like to go deeper with methods, theories, and frameworks.</p>

<p>The Coaching Leadership Style consists of two tracks — developing self and developing others. You can expect as much of this work to be about <em>you</em> as it is about your team, because powerful coaching is about presence, attention, and curiosity. This means it is important to be aware of the role your unconscious thoughts, feelings and behaviors play in creating the conditions you find yourself in as a leader.</p>

<p>I am more convinced than ever that a coaching approach to leadership brings clarity to how we see each other, presence to how we receive each other, and the courage to hold each other accountable with care and directness. There is always more we can do to deepen our ability to be present, to ask open and honest questions, and to build trusting and collaborative partnerships that honor our humanity and unlock worlds of possibility.</p>

<h2 id="getting-started">Getting Started</h2>

<p>The next issue of Words Make Worlds will introduce the idea of a “container” — a structure that can facilitate your learning journey as you practice the skills of coaching. Until then, here are a few articles to get you more familiar with the Coaching Leadership Style.</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://medium.com/wordsmakeworlds/the-coaching-leadership-style-developing-self-and-developing-others-2f3fd665ba6d">The Coaching Leadership Style: Developing Self and Developing Others​</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://medium.com/wordsmakeworlds/the-mindset-qualities-and-posture-of-a-coach-28ff82c21a21">The Mindset, Qualities, and Posture of a Coach</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://medium.com/wordsmakeworlds/12-essential-books-for-leaders-who-coach-a7620fce706a">12 Essential Books for Leaders Who Coach</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://medium.com/wordsmakeworlds/creating-space-for-others-to-think-30a6e8b418e1">Creating Space for Others to Think</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="thank-you">Thank you!</h2>
<p>Thanks for joining me on this journey, and see you in two weeks.</p>

<p>With infinite gratitude,</p>

<p>Andi</p>

          ]]>
        </description>
      </item>

  </channel>

</rss>
