<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"

	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	>

  <channel>
  	<title>Words Make Worlds</title>
    <atom:link href="https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <link>https://methodandmatter.com/words-make-worlds</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <generator>Middleman (Ruby)</generator>
    <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>
		<description>A publication about the art, science, and craft of the Coaching Leadership Style. Sent bi-weekly, Words Make Worlds delivers insight and practices to increase leadership impact.</description>
		<meta property="og:image" content="https://methodandmatter.com/images/mm-round.png" />
    <image>
      <url>https://methodandmatter.com/images/mm-round.png</url>
      <title>method &#038; matter</title>
      <link>https://methodandmatter.com</link>
    </image>



      <item>
        <title>Being Green in a World on Fire</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com//words-make-worlds/being-green-in-a-world-on-fire/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com//words-make-worlds/being-green-in-a-world-on-fire/</guid>
        <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


        <description>
          <![CDATA[
            <p>There is a simple check-in I like to use when I’m facilitating groups and coaching teams. Some of you may know it—it’s referred to as the Traffic Light Check-in. I picked the practice up from a <a href="https://reboot.io">Reboot</a> Circle I was in many years ago, and they in turn learned it from one of their former colleagues. Beyond that, I am unsure of its origin.</p>

<p>The practice is simple. Authentically answer the question, “How are you?” Use one of the colors of the traffic light (red, yellow, green/blue) to express your state, along with any other context you care to share.</p>

<p>Here is how Ali Schultz describes <a href="https://www.reboot.io/murmuration/">each of the colors</a>:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Green means you feel safe, copasetic, or perhaps are in flow. You’re able to have eye-contact, creativity, play, humor. In a sense, all systems are go.</li>
  <li>Yellow is reactionary, meaning that the fight or flight impulse is present, as is perhaps some defensiveness.</li>
  <li>Red means your rational brain is offline, nervous system is shutting down such that you may or may not be present at all, or there may be a loss of trust.</li>
</ul>

<p>So a check-in might go something like, “I’m pretty green. I slept well and feel excited about the day, but there is quite a lot to get done.” Or maybe you are yellow, and you share the color and say something like, “I’m concerned about some of the upcoming deadlines around the new product launch and feeling stretched thin.”</p>

<p>When running these check-ins with designers, I get Pantone colors, gradients, patterns, you name it. People get pretty creative with expressing how they are doing through color.</p>

<p>What I’ve always liked about the method is that it’s quick, it offers people a chance to check-in with themselves and bring awareness to how they are feeling, and provides psychological safety because they don’t have to share any additional details that may feel uncomfortable or unsafe.</p>

<p>It also gives people a chance to support each other. For the yellow check-in above, a few people might offer their time after the meeting to run through the concerns and see if anything needs to be adjusted or addressed. I once reported red in a meeting due to some stuff going on in my personal life, and the team rallied around me, volunteering to take on extra work so that I could take care of myself. And I didn’t have to share all the messy details, only that I was showing up as red.</p>

<p>The colors apparently map to the nervous system in the style of Polyvagal theory—green meaning you are in the rest and digest mode of the parasympathetic nervous system, yellow indicates sympathetic activation of the fight/flight response, and red is freeze, aka dorsal collapse.</p>

<h3 id="is-it-okay-to-be-green">Is it okay to be green?</h3>
<p>I introduced this check-in to a group of deeply caring folks who work in a high-stress, high-stakes environment and who are feeling the impact of federal funding cuts for at-risk communities.</p>

<p>They picked up the color language immediately and pointed to a challenge inherent in their work—they were always yellow, all the time, by the very nature of what they did. Could they even be green?</p>

<p>As the conversation unfolded, something even more fundamental came to light. Many of these kind and capable people held a core belief that is not okay to be green in a world that is on fire (both literally and metaphorically for this Los Angeles based team).</p>

<p>I will note that when I teach the traffic light check-in, I describe green as being present and able to tend to what is needed in the moment. I do not talk about being copasetic or creativity, play, and humor. Yes, these things are all totally part of what can happen in green states, but they aren’t all that can happen.</p>

<h3 id="what-being-green-really-means">What being green really means</h3>
<p>Being green means that we have the capacity to be with whatever is showing up without getting so activated we can’t respond.  It doesn’t necessarily mean we are in a great mood, joyful, and full of creative energy, though that is absolutely possible. It does mean that we are relaxed and open, responsive and present, and able to fully feel the feels.</p>

<p>Being green means being attuned to our emotions. The ones that lift us up into connected and creative states, and the ones that show up when we encounter a world that doesn’t align with our values.</p>

<p>The key to being green is being present and feeling what shows up, rather than fusing with emotions or suppressing them to the point they eat away at us from the inside. It is not the presence of a “negative” emotion that indicates yellow or red, but how we <em>are</em> with that emotion.</p>

<p>It is entirely possible to be green and sad. Or red and joyful.</p>

<h3 id="embodied-self-awareness">Embodied Self-Awareness</h3>
<p>To understand this, I want to briefly remap the definitions of the colors based on Alan Fogel’s research on Embodied Self-Awareness (ESA).</p>

<p>The basic idea (and I am over simplifying for the sake of brevity) behind ESA is that it is the ability <em>feel</em> ourselves as living, sensing beings that invokes the parasympathetic rest-and-digest response. When we <em>think</em> about ourselves conceptually we are invoking various neural networks in the brain that rely on the sympathetic nervous system. It is only when we can drop fully into the experiencing self that we can access the restorative qualities of emotions.</p>

<p>In this model, green is a restorative state in which we are able to fully embrace any felt experience—pleasure or pain, happiness or grief—that arises in the present moment without judgmental or censoring thoughts. This state involves complete presence with whatever we’re feeling, sustained long enough to create a lasting sense of relief, deeper breathing, or spreading warmth and relaxation.</p>

<p>Yellow is a modulated state where we have the capacity to alternate between focused activity and brief moments of reconnecting with our felt experience. In this state, we can stay engaged with tasks and challenges while maintaining enough body awareness to know when we need to pause, breathe, or tend to what our body is telling us. Most of us live primarily in this state.</p>

<p>Red means we feel stuck and cannot modulate our felt experience, thoughts, or nervous system activation. There’s no space to breathe, no rest, no relief. We feel trapped in painful emotions, ruminative thoughts, or overwhelming sensations without the ability to shift or find perspective.</p>

<h3 id="on-sadness-and-joy">On sadness and joy</h3>
<p>Let’s run through red, yellow, and green for sadness and joy, to get a sense of how this works.</p>

<p><strong>Red sadness:</strong> In red states, it is common for feelings to be suppressed. Sadness often comes with the physiological counterpart of crying, which has a number of health benefits. When people suppress crying, the sadness is internalized and can fuel ongoing rumination about negative experiences, which leads to feelings of exhaustion and burnout. When crying does happen in a red state, it is the sympathetic nervous system that stays activated so the tears don’t have the soothing effect they would if sadness was experienced in a yellow or green state. This type of crying tends to be needy, self-centered, and manipulative.</p>

<p><strong>Yellow sadness:</strong> Sadness in a yellow state frequently allows the tears to flow with the understanding that crying contains the possibility of alleviating some of the distress.</p>

<p><strong>Green sadness:</strong> Sadness in a green state has a different quality. Crying brings relief and surrender. The tears that come contain certain proteins and stress hormones that flush stress-related chemicals and shift the body into a relaxation response. It is in this state that crying activates the parasympathetic nervous system and can bring in a sense of relief and restoration.</p>

<p><strong>Red joy:</strong> In a red state, joy is usually found in things that can temporarily numb the pain. This can look like addiction, risk taking, lashing out, or being manic. These actions, while they do bring relief for short periods of time, do not activate the soothing side of the parasympathetic nervous system, often keeping someone in dorsal freeze or sympathetic activation.</p>

<p><strong>Yellow joy:</strong> Joy in yellow states tends to center around high energy excitement that brings a sense of intensity, focus, and engagement. This is very typical of “flow” states experiences in sports, creative work, musical performances, etc. These states work in conjunction with sympathetic activation in the form of eustress, the positive kind of stress that stretches and challenges us. As opposed to distress which can push us into overwhelm and closer to red states.</p>

<p><strong>Green joy:</strong> Joy in this state comes with a sense of deep okayness. The body relaxes and lets go of protective tension, there may be a sense of warmth and release, or the possibility for restoration and healing. People often feel qualities of presence like contentment, peace, and aliveness. Others share they experience total surrender, compassion, love, and receptivity. The face softens and people often appear younger and with bright, smiling eyes.</p>

<h3 id="seconds">90 seconds</h3>
<p>It is true that emotions generally take around 90 seconds to run their course. But that is ONLY if we are in a green state of presence. When we have the capacity to be with the emotion and fully feel it, without needing to analyze, control, or act it out, the emotion can find a path to show up, share its message with us, and then subside. But if we mess with it in any way, then that emotion is going to hang around for a lot longer.</p>

<p>I’ve spoken about my Kung Fu training in previous issues, and once again there are useful lessons that can be applied here. Being green is about being open, present, and relaxed. Aware and responsive to whatever might show up.</p>

<p>If I have my fist out in front of me and my arm tense, just waiting like for something to show that I can fight, by the time a real threat shows up my arm is going to be stiff, tired, and exhausted. I’ve wasted all my energy staying tense and waiting.</p>

<p>Instead, I practice staying relaxed, open, and present. If something shows up that needs attention, I am ready to respond with the right amount of energy and effort. I use timing and physics to keep myself safe and contain my opponent.</p>

<p>The same goes for being green.</p>

<h3 id="on-being-green">On being green</h3>
<p>So I want to say, to all those caring leaders out there, it is absolutely okay to be green.</p>

<p>We <em>need</em> you to be green. Be present and open. Feel the emotions that come through and let them flow. Not just the ones that alert you to what isn’t right in the world, but the ones that remind you of what is <em>already</em> right. The wonder of being alive, the love you have for special people in your life, the joy of connection and doing something meaningful.</p>

<p>Strong emotions, the ones typically classified as “negative” don’t have to keep you tense to the point of exhaustion—they have a restorative quality when felt in a state of being green. For example, restorative anger reminds us of what really matters and gives us the energy to take a stand for what we care about. It is entirely possible to wake up everyday and say “NO” without overwhelming your body with stress to the point of exhaustion.</p>

<p>If we stay tense and reactive, then we are easily knocked over. Our resources are always depleted and we don’t have enough to meet the moments that matter.</p>

<p>Green helps us connect to our emotions, we allow them all but we do this skillfully so that we can fully utilize the gifts of these emotions. If we do this unskillfully then we explode, collapse, or become lost in dogma. Such reactions aren’t in service of life and justice, and often they wind up perpetuating the status quo.</p>

<p>Being green is <em>exactly</em> how you show up in a world on fire.</p>

          ]]>
        </description>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Are You Really on the Same Page?</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com//words-make-worlds/expectations-to-agreements/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com//words-make-worlds/expectations-to-agreements/</guid>
        <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


        <description>
          <![CDATA[
            <p>One of the biggest challenges of leadership is shared knowledge.</p>

<p>Usually we think this covers business-related knowledge: mission and vision, customer behavior, quarterly and yearly goals, jobs to be done, market dynamics, and organizational context. Which is not wrong, but <em>is</em> incomplete.</p>

<p>It’s not just knowledge about the business that needs to be shared, but ways of working, behaving, communicating, and responding, which can be a particular blind spot of leadership. Leaders do what is obvious to them, and assume that same thing must be obvious to others.</p>

<p>And because this is a blind spot, leaders can get pretty worked up when people fail to do the very things that seem obvious to them. They get frustrated, make up stories, and blame the team, rather than just, you know, tell people about those obvious and common sense things they expect them to do.</p>

<p>This gets even more tricky when you consider the foibles of human communication. What I say is often not what people hear, even though <em>I</em> think I’ve perfectly said what I mean. And I usually won’t find out until after the fact, when what I thought I communicated fails to manifest (in which case I am probably going to blame the other party and not myself!).</p>

<p>Thankfully, there are a few things you can do to  keep these misses from happening and get everyone on the same page.</p>

<h3 id="getting-clear-together">Getting Clear Together</h3>

<p>First, say out loud, and as clearly as you can, what your expectations are.</p>

<p>Here is an expectation I have: “I expect that people will arrive to meetings on time and prepared, and if they can’t make it or will be late, will let me know at least 24 hours prior.”</p>

<p>Second, figure out if what you said has been understood the way you intended it. “Is this clear? What questions do you have?”</p>

<p>In the case above, one question might be, “How should we let you know?” Another might be, “What if the meeting is on Monday morning?” Someone else might wonder about what being prepared for a meeting looks like or what counts as “late”.</p>

<p>See what I mean? What seems clear to you actually isn’t all that clear when tested against the perspective, experience, and work history of others.</p>

<p>Once you've gotten clear together, the next step is to find out if folks agree with what you shared. Just because you expect people to behave a certain way doesn’t mean it will resonate or be acceptable to them. They might have some other ideas around meeting protocols.</p>

<p>Whether they agree immediately or you spend some time workshopping it together, the finally step is to write down what you agreed to in a place everyone can easily refer to it when needed.</p>

<h3 id="from-expectations-to-shared-agreements">From Expectations to Shared Agreements</h3>

<p>The process just described is what is commonly referred to in the coaching world as “expectations and agreements”. Expectations exist in your head, and if you don’t share them you set yourself up for continuous disappointment because <em>people can’t read your mind</em>.</p>

<p>The alternative is to create a set of shared agreements—expectations that are shared out loud, agreed to or modified, and then written down for reference. Shared agreements usually exist as “living documents” that can be updated or modified at anytime, to keep the system responsive and flexible.</p>

<p>A good sign you are holding an expectation that would be better as a shared agreement is frustration and negative judgements that people just don’t “get it.” What is it they don’t get? Surface that expectation and share it! If you have ever thought to yourself, “Well, I do X, so why aren’t they doing X?” that is a great sign of an unshared expectation! Put it out into the open!</p>

<p>Here are some of the shared agreements I use with each cohort of Leader as Coach:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Everything is welcome: Whatever shows up in class is welcome. We bring compassion, appreciation and non-judgement to each other and to this work.</li>
  <li>We take care of ourselves: We don’t need to ask permission to do what we need to tend to ourselves. We will let people know when we need to step away.</li>
  <li>Commitment: We are committed to each other and this learning container throughout our time together. This means active participation in sessions, completing weekly experiments, sharing reflections, and communicating proactively if challenges arise.</li>
  <li>Psychological Safety: We are here to learn and support each other in that learning. We commit to supporting, listening, and giving space without judgement for people to share openly. We hold positive intent and give people the benefit of the doubt, and do our best to hold back from fixing, directing, and giving advice without consent.</li>
</ul>

<p>Creating a set of shared agreements with your team can be transformative. Not only are your expectations clear and out in the open, but because they are created collaboratively, everyone feels invested. People aren’t being told what to do, they are collectively shaping team behavior.</p>

<p>This also means you waste a lot less energy feeling frustrated and ruminating about why people aren’t doing or responding in ways you think they should. It’s a big world. We’ve all been shaped by different upbringings, education, cultures, and work experiences. Do yourself and your team a favor and say as clearly as you can what you want, and then explore that together.</p>

<h3 id="you-expectations---agreements-checklist">You expectations -&gt; agreements checklist:</h3>
<ul>
  <li>Have I said it out loud?</li>
  <li>Have people understood it?</li>
  <li>Do they agree with it?</li>
  <li>If not, what can we come up with as an alternative?</li>
  <li>Have we written it down where everyone can find it?</li>
</ul>

          ]]>
        </description>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>The Surprising Power of Awe</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com//words-make-worlds/the-surprising-power-of-awe/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com//words-make-worlds/the-surprising-power-of-awe/</guid>
        <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


        <description>
          <![CDATA[
            <p>I must have been around 10 or 11 years old the winter I realized how vast the universe was.</p>

<p>A storm tumbled through our town leaving eight inches of snow in its wake. The next day the temperature warmed enough to rain and then rapidly dropped below zero, transforming the top inches of snow into a thick layer of ice—a hardy crust that you could walk on top of and not break through. For adults this was probably a pain in the butt, but for us kids it was a magical playground.</p>

<p>It only took one stupidly fast and uncontrollable run down the hill in our back yard for my brother and I to realize how treacherous the situation was. Normally we could maneuver our sleds into a controlled landing by dragging one or both arms in the snow, like a rudder, and easily avoid crashing into the pine trees lining the bottom. But with the ice there was no dragging, only careening, our tiny faces slapped with pine needles before an unceremonious and sudden encounter with a tree trunk.</p>

<p>We also realized we couldn’t make it back up the hill, everything was so slippery. We had to chip hand holes into the ice with sticks to create anchors so we wouldn't slide to the bottom and have to start the climb all over.</p>

<p>Eventually we ditched our sleds and created a new game. We covered the ice in a grid of hand holds. Starting at the top of the hill, snowsuit stomach down, we launched ourselves. There was enough momentum that you could grab onto a hole and change your direction, spinning around a few times before catching another. Kind of like if Plinko were etched into the side of a hill, with kids bonking around instead of a giant coin.</p>

<p>It was such fun we stayed out well past dinner time. My brother was the first to get tired and go inside. I stayed out to do a few more runs.</p>

<p>By this point it was dark, the night crisp. Halfway down the hill I flipped over and looked up. The spiral arm of the Milky Way slashed across the inky sky, stars twinkling in every direction.</p>

<p>The warm light from the living room spilled down the hill, its meniscus stopping just short of where I lay sprawled. We had been learning about space at school (Jupiter was my favorite planet) and I knew that each point of light dotting the sky was incredibly far away.</p>

<p>So far away that what I was looking at might not be there any longer, the distance between us like a time machine turning the clock back a millennia. I had the sudden realization I was looking into the past.</p>

<p>Everything inverted.</p>

<p>I understood how small I was, and how alive. I felt the cold of the icy snow and the familiarity of the backyard I knew so well—the oak to my right and maple to my left, the pine trees lining the bottom of the hill, and the little nook behind them where we buried beloved pets. All of us there under the vast canopy of time and space, the night quiet and perfect. I could see my breath as I gazed into the vastness of space, completely mesmerized.</p>

<p>I was in awe.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="a-brief-detour-into-the-body">A Brief Detour into the Body</h2>

<p>For the last few months I’ve been designing an offsite for leaders around somatic resilience practices. The central theme is that the body is essential to our well-being, but in order for it to serve in its full function, we have to be able to <em>feel</em> it (not just think about it) and understand what it is saying.</p>

<p>The body is the first to sense when we are moving into unhealthy behaviors (to name a few: working too much, being in activated states for too long, pushing through, “leaning in”, you know the drill…) and sending signals to slow down. But when we have been in prolonged states of “grinding” our biology works against us.</p>

<p>In order to grind we have to push our body into “survival mode”, at least neurochemically. Prolonged states of stress pump cortisol into the bloodstream so we can keep going, which reinforces activation of the nervous system. This process necessarily numbs our ability to feel what is happening in our body so that we can keep going, and also happens to be a recipe for burnout.</p>

<p>When we’ve been pushing for so long, disconnected from the felt-sense of what the body needs and wants, it can be hard to find real rest, the kind that actually begins to restore a baseline of normal functioning.</p>

<h2 id="the-awe-shortcut">The Awe Shortcut</h2>

<p>In my research I’ve come to learn that awe is rather unique when it comes to human emotion. It can act as a short cut for dropping the body into a restorative, expansive state. When awe is activated our thinking mind gets quiet, creating space to reconnect to something much greater than ourselves (which happens to be really good for us).</p>

<p>Let's be clear, I'm not saying awe is a panacea that will fix everything, but it deserves some attention for at least cutting through the bullshit of our ego for a short bit of time.</p>

<p>No other emotion can do this. Most emotions can be experienced in any state our nervous system is in—restorative where we feel the fullness of an emotion without editorializing, modulated where we both feel and analyze, or dysregulated where the emotion takes over and pushes us into fight or flight mode.</p>

<p>But not awe! Awe generates a state of relaxation, an absence of thinking, and the feeling of being completely in the present moment. You cannot experience dysregulation and awe at the same time.</p>

<p>This matters because these days we’re all pretty activated by the uncertainty of the world. Our nervous systems seem perilously and persistently close to the edge, making it damn hard to find enough restoration to feel truly nourished and resourced (infinite scrolling and social media are decidedly <em>not</em> restorative activities).</p>

<p>So you can meditate a bunch, go on wellness retreats, drop yourself into a sensory deprivation tank or… just experience awe. You don’t have to go far—opening up to wonder and listening to your favorite music, spending some time in nature, or getting down with amazing art are all ways to connect with awe.</p>

<h2 id="try-it-out">Try it Out</h2>

<p>Here’s an easy one you can start doing right now: every day, for the next two weeks, commit to taking a 15 minute walk. Focus on being completely present and seeing everything “new” as if from a child’s perspective. As Kai Sky recommends, “Imagine something that gives you joy. Got it? Now go and be like that all day long. (Yes, it is that simple…).”</p>

<p>I also recorded a <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/13Rp4nSgfWZ__tFs-aK94Vvl-caO9V4jS/view?usp=sharing">short, guided meditation</a> you can use to connect with a past experience of awe to use as a resource. Over time, the image or memory may fade, but the imprint of the somatic state will remain.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="additional-reading-on-awe">Additional Reading on Awe:</h3>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.noemamag.com/finding-awe-amid-everday-splendor/">Finding Awe Amid Everyday Splendor</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://lisafeldmanbarrett.com/books/how-emotions-are-made/">How Emotions are Made</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://hbr.org/2023/01/the-power-of-everyday-awe">The Power of Everyday Awe</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC10018061/pdf/10.1177_17456916221094856.pdf">Awe as a Pathway to Mental and Physical Health</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://greatergood.berkeley.edu/article/item/six_ways_to_incorporate_awe_into_your_daily_life">Six Ways to Incorporate Awe Into Your Daily Life</a></li>
</ul>

          ]]>
        </description>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Coming Back to Center</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com//words-make-worlds/the-importance-of-centering/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com//words-make-worlds/the-importance-of-centering/</guid>
        <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


        <description>
          <![CDATA[
            <p>Picture a time when someone physically grabbed you. Not necessarily in a threatening way, though these types of grabs happen too. Maybe a friend pulled you back from walking into a busy street or a colleague was trying get your attention as you walked by at a conference.</p>

<p>Do you remember what happened? How your body responded before you had a chance to think? You were probably activated in some habitual way—muscles tense, cortisol released, a little bit of a recoil as you automatically assessed the threat level.</p>

<p>Even if the person who grabbed you did it in a “friendly” way, it demanded your attention, your nervous system shifting into protective mode. You probably weren’t aware of anything else in that moment, and afterwards it might have taken you some time to return to equilibrium.</p>

<h3 id="daily-grabs">Daily Grabs</h3>

<p>Now imagine being grabbed a hundred times a day, because that's what happens! Not physically, but mentally and emotionally. Work place conflicts, news cycles, inner critics, societal expectations, uncertainty—there are so many ways we can be grabbed. And the nervous system doesn't care what the source is, so it will respond in the same way it does to a physical grab.</p>

<p>Let’s say you have an interaction with your boss that feels off. You have the thought that your boss doesn’t like you (which feels really threatening), and your body reacts—you tense up, constrict your breathing, pull away, and try and control your reaction. Which usually creates a negative feedback loop of increasing intensity—nervous system is activated, the physical sensations of discomfort become stronger, and the worry thoughts amp up.</p>

<p>What happens when this negative feedback loop continues for days, weeks, or even months? Where each day at work you are constantly on the lookout for signals of how your boss feels about you, picking apart the smallest details of a comment or obsessively comparing how your boss reacts to others in order to figure out where you stand. In this increased state of vigilance, the smallest thing can knock you over.</p>

<p>If you take this same approach in martial arts, your attacker will easily win. Your reactive state keeps you off balance and up in your head, responding from instinct while trying to “figure out” what to do.</p>

<h3 id="centering">Centering</h3>

<p>The antidote to this is centering. In the physical body, center is about two or three fingers below the belly button, and back a bit, closer to the spine. Try moving your attention there now, from your head to your physical center. Bring your breath all the way down, as if you were breathing from this place in your body. Feel what shifts.</p>

<p>You might notice some tension is released in the neck and shoulders. Or you might feel more of your legs. Maybe your peripheral vision widens, or you feel a little more connected to yourself, more present.</p>

<p>Centering doesn’t keep the grabs from happening, but it helps us see them coming. And when we can see them, we have choice in how we respond. We can choose not to engage, we can blend with the energy and move it another direction, we can block and counter attack—from a centered place the options are plenty.</p>

<p>This applies equally in the boardroom as it does on the mat. Centering helps us be more rooted, open, and responsive. And the more familiar we are with center, the easier it is to come back to it when something pulls us away.</p>

<p>Centering keeps us balanced under pressure. Think of a recent meeting you’ve been in, one that was challenging in some way or another. Your awareness was probably concentrated in your upper body from the shoulders on up. You might have noticed some tension, and that your thoughts were focused on the exchange of words, or on crafting your own verbal response. As the meeting progressed, it might have felt more and more adversarial.</p>

<p>We aren’t balanced when we center in the head. Centering from the body reminds us that interactions don’t just happen with words, but between bodies. When we shift attention to our belly center, physical tension is released, breathing deepens, and the nervous system settles. This changes how we speak, listen, and act, leading to new outcomes.</p>

<h3 id="try-it-out">Try It Out</h3>

<p>Place your hands, one on top of the other, about three fingers below your belly button. Take three slow breaths, imagining each inhale traveling all the way down to fill the space under your lower hand. As you exhale, let your shoulders drop and soften.</p>

<p>Notice what shifts—perhaps your jaw unclenches, your vision widens, or you simply feel more present in your body.</p>

<p>This same practice works beautifully in meetings. When you feel that familiar “grab”—an unexpected question, pushback on your idea, or tension in the room—take a moment to breathe into your center. You don’t need to close your eyes or make it obvious.</p>

<p>Simply shift your attention from your racing thoughts down to that steady place in your belly.</p>

<p>From there, you might find yourself listening more deeply, speaking with more clarity, or discovering a response you couldn’t access when you were centered in your head.</p>

<p>Keep practicing this during the week, especially in calm moments. The more you experience center, the easier it is to come back to it when something tries to grab you.</p>

          ]]>
        </description>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Unbundling Leadership</title>
        <link>https://methodandmatter.com//words-make-worlds/unbundling-leadership/</link>
        <guid>https://methodandmatter.com//words-make-worlds/unbundling-leadership/</guid>
        <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
        <author>Andrea Mignolo</author>


        <description>
          <![CDATA[
            <p>Unbundling is a business strategy that seeks to take things apart with the purpose of creating a more functional or competitive business. GE, under Jack Welch, spun off or sold underperforming business units in order to focus on the most profitable divisions, Craigslist unbundled classified ad revenue from traditional newspapers, and the shift to digital distribution unbundled songs from an album in the form of MP3s.</p>

<p>Leadership strikes me as something else that could benefit from unbundling. Not as a theoretical term, but as the practical application of what happens when someone steps into a formal leadership role. By this I mean a role that, in addition to vision and influence, comes with positional power, responsibility for a team and/or function, and possibly P&amp;L responsibilities.</p>

<p>When you step into a leadership role you’re often expected to get on with the work without much guidance or training. The new responsibilities, relationships, and altitude you need to think at are at best loosely defined in a career matrix, but more commonly have to be inferred from the organizational environment.</p>

<p>Faced with this murkiness, leaders take a number of approaches—mirroring the leaders around them, becoming the type of leader they always wanted but never had, or staying heads down and focusing on the work.</p>

<p>What I wish I had known, when I stepped into my first leadership role, is that leadership is a bundle of three different and somewhat distinct areas of responsibility: holding and communicating the vision, running the business, and developing talent. Each corresponds to a different role: leader, manager, and coach. While in practice the three blend together, it can be helpful to understand the distinct configuration of each.</p>

<h2 id="leader">Leader</h2>
<p>Leadership is the embodiment of vision and values in action. Leaders connect people to purpose, make meaning of challenges, and inspire collective movement towards shared goals. The mindset of a leader is oriented towards the future, possibility, and innovation.</p>

<p>Key responsibilities include creating and communicating the vision, aligning efforts with core values, listening to what is happening in organization, helping people understand the “why”, and showing how individual and team work contributes to larger organizational goals.</p>

<p>Leaders must do this both for the people on the team/function/department they are in charge of, and also for their colleagues across the organization. They are responsible for making sure that the work they are responsible for is understood across the company and <em>why</em> it matters in the first place.</p>

<h3 id="reflection-questions">Reflection questions:</h3>

<h4 id="vision--purpose">Vision &amp; Purpose:</h4>
<ul>
  <li>How effectively am I translating abstract vision into concrete, relatable terms for my team?</li>
  <li>What stories am I telling that help people see themselves in our shared future?</li>
  <li>Does our vision still resonate with the team's evolving needs?</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="influence--inspiration">Influence &amp; Inspiration:</h4>
<ul>
  <li>Am I modeling the behaviors and values I want to see in others?</li>
  <li>How do I respond when my vision meets resistance or skepticism?</li>
  <li>What legacy am I creating through my leadership decisions?</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="organizational-impact">Organizational Impact:</h4>
<ul>
  <li>How well do I understand the broader ecosystem my team operates within?</li>
  <li>Where might I be inadvertently creating silos or barriers to collaboration?</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="manager">Manager</h2>
<p>Management is the practice of running a business—orchestrating work systems and processes to achieve predictable outcomes. The mindset of a manager orients towards operational excellence and structured thinking.</p>

<p>Key responsibilities include setting clear expectations in the form of shared agreements, establishing effective processes, identifying metrics of success, ensuring efficient resource allocation, and maintaining stability and consistency.</p>

<p>It is worthwhile to note that the role of manager and leader can often be at odds. While the role of leader orients towards new possibilities through innovation, the role of manager is focused on healthy and repeatable processes. Leadership can be a destabilizing threat to management predictability.</p>

<h3 id="reflection-questions-1">Reflection Questions:</h3>

<h4 id="systems--processes">Systems &amp; Processes:</h4>
<ul>
  <li>What friction points are slowing down our team’s ability to deliver results?</li>
  <li>How do I balance standardization with the need for flexibility?</li>
  <li>Which meetings, reports, or processes could we eliminate without losing value?</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="performance--accountability">Performance &amp; Accountability:</h4>
<ul>
  <li>How quickly do I address performance gaps when they arise?</li>
  <li>Am I giving people the tools and resources they need to succeed?</li>
  <li>What would happen if I wasn't here for a week—would things run smoothly?</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="resource-optimization">Resource Optimization:</h4>
<ul>
  <li>Where am I over-investing or under-investing our team’s time and energy?</li>
  <li>How effectively am I protecting my team from organizational noise and distractions?</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="coach">Coach</h2>
<p>Coaching is way of developing talent by supporting people to achieve the results they want through self-awareness and behavior change. The mindset of a coach is one of curiosity and learning, a willingness to let go of knowing the answer and trust that each person has the capacity to figure out their own path forward.</p>

<p>Key responsibilities for the coaching role cover creating space for reflection, asking powerful questions, supporting others to connect with their inner wisdom, and expanding how people observe and understand the situations they find themselves in.</p>

<p>Mentorship also falls under the umbrella of coaching. The way I distinguish between the two is that coaching is designed to connect someone to their own inner knowing with support from the coach in the form of questions and observations, while mentorship is oriented around a more senior person sharing insights from hard-won experience in order to help a more junior person grow.</p>

<h3 id="reflection-questions-2">Reflection Questions:</h3>

<h4 id="development--growth">Development &amp; Growth:</h4>
<ul>
  <li>What assumptions am I making about what each person needs to grow?</li>
  <li>How often do I ask “What do you think?” before offering my own perspective?</li>
  <li>When have I seen someone surprise themselves with their own capability?</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="creating-safety">Creating Safety:</h4>
<ul>
  <li>How comfortable do people feel bringing me problems or admitting mistakes?</li>
  <li>What signals might I be sending that discourage open dialogue?</li>
  <li>How do I respond when someone's approach differs from what I would do?</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="letting-go">Letting Go:</h4>
<ul>
  <li>Where am I solving problems that others could solve themselves?</li>
  <li>How do I distinguish between when to step in and when to step back?</li>
  <li>What would it look like to be less helpful in service of others’ growth?</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<p>It is important to note that within each of these roles there is a wide range of variability. How you lead, manage, and coach will be shaped by your experiences, values, and beliefs about how good work gets done (and what qualifies as good work in the first place).</p>

<p>Give it a try this week—track each of your days and see where you lead, manage, and coach. You might find one role is more comfortable for you or that certain contexts require one role over the others. There is no one right way, but I hope that unbundling these three roles gives you useful insight to be more impactful as a leader.</p>

          ]]>
        </description>
      </item>

  </channel>

</rss>
